<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/wwp-store.rng"    type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/wwp-store.isosch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: sanders.aborigine.xml 31962 2017-06-23 22:20:54Z syd $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.wwp.northeastern.edu/ns/textbase" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader xml:id="TR00302.hdr">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Conversations Principally on the Aborigines of North America, 1829</title>
        <author>
          <persName ref="p:esanders.vjg" type="person-female">Sanders, Elizabeth Elkins</persName>
        </author>
        <sponsor>Brown University</sponsor>
        <sponsor>Northeastern University</sponsor>
        <funder>U.S. National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPedition)"/>    
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Northeastern University Women Writers Project</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>SL 213</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Northeastern University</addrLine>
          <addrLine>360 Huntington Avenue</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Boston, MA  02115-5005</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>url:mailto:wwp@neu.edu</addrLine>
          <addrLine>url:http://www.wwp.northeastern.edu/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno type="WWP">TR00302</idno>
        <idno type="URL">http://www.wwp.northeastern.edu/texts/sanders.aborigine.html</idno>
        <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPavailability)"/>
        <date when="2005-06-02"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="WWP">
          <p>Text is an offcut duodecimo, which the printed signatures reflect.</p>
        </note>
        <note type="textual">
          <p>Spelling in this text is somewhat variable. Our encoding only corrects obvious typographical errors, such as <mentioned>Greek</mentioned> for <mentioned>Creek</mentioned>.</p>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc n="OT00302">
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName ref="p:esanders.vjg" type="regularized">Sanders, Elizabeth Elkins</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Conversations principally on the aborigines of North America</title>
            <edition>Another printing of the 1828 edition</edition>
            <idno type="icu">E77.S2</idno>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Salem, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
              <publisher><persName ref="p:wives.mao" type="titlePage">W.</persName><persName ref="p:wives.mao" type="regularized">Ives, W.</persName>
 and 
		
<persName ref="p:sives.oii" type="titlePage">S. B. Ives</persName>
<persName ref="p:sives.oii" type="regularized">Ives, S. B.</persName>
</publisher>
              <date when="1829">1829</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure unit="page" quantity="179"/>
            </extent>
            <extent>
              <dimensions>
                <height quantity="15" unit="cm"/>
              </dimensions>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPprojectDescription)"/>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPsamplingDeclaration)"/>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPeditorialDeclaration)"/>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPcharacterDeclaration)"/>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="r.it" selector="emph, soCalled, foreign">slant(italic)</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="r.break" selector="">break(yes)</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="r.nobreak" selector="">break(no)</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="r.head" selector="head">break(yes)align(center)case(allcaps)post(#rule)</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="r.speaker" selector="speaker">break(no)slant(italic)</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="r.p" selector="p">first-indent(1)</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="r.mw" selector="mw">place(outside)break(yes)</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="r.quote" selector="quote">pre(“)post(”)</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="r.q" selector="q">pre(‘)post(’)</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPclassificationDeclaration)"/>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPlistPrefixDefinitions)"/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="unknown.zzx" scribe="unknown.zzx"/>
      </handNotes>
      <textClass>
        <catRef type="main" target="#G.non-fiction"/>
        <catRef type="other" target="#G.non-fiction"/>
      </textClass>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPcalendarDescription)"/>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPlangUsage)"/>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change n="RCS-1.31" when="2010-12-10" who="p:npeterson.gwx">added <att>type</att> to docRole.</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.26" when="2008-08-01" who="p:lmanders.vko">Fixed names beginning with M'</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.22" when="2006-08-30" who="p:jflanders.lfw">added genre data, added name keys for publishers</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.18" when="2005-06-02" who="p:pcaton.xzc">Added wwp edition and date info</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.17" when="2005-05-31" who="p:jflanders.lfw">Final checking round and review. Fixed a few typos and added textual note re: spelling variability.</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.14" when="2001-09-04" who="p:zmizuho.zgk">Correx entry from checking round. Supravalidated.</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.13" when="2001-07-16" who="p:hfielding.grh">Entered correx from first proofing, supravalidated, and printed.</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.12" when="2001-06-27" who="p:hfielding.grh">Changed persname in titlestmt to name</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.11" when="2001-06-19" who="p:hfielding.grh">Completed capture, supravalidated, and printed.</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.3" when="2001-06-11" who="p:hfielding.grh">Began capture with psgml on Unix with version 1.2.6, 2000-03-31 of wwp-store DTD.</change>
      <change when="2001-05-02" who="p:zmizuho.zgk">Captured header using emacs with psgml on Unix with
	  version 1.2.6, 2000-03-31 of wwp-store DTD.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="TR00302">
    <hyperDiv>
<notes>
<note xml:id="n01" target="#a01" rend="pre(*)place(end)align(center)">
        <p>Letter of <persName>Gen. Coffee</persName>.</p>
      </note>
<note xml:id="n02" target="#a02" rend="pre(*)place(end)align(center)">
        <p><persName>Hubbard</persName>.</p>
      </note>
<note xml:id="n03" target="#a03" rend="pre(*)place(end)align(center)">
        <p>
          <bibl>
            <title><choice><abbr>N. A.</abbr><expan>North American</expan></choice> Review</title>
          </bibl>
        </p>
      </note>
<note xml:id="n04" target="#a04" rend="pre(*)place(end)">
        <p>I apprehend the writer has mistaken the name of the
<lb/>river.</p>
      </note>
<note xml:id="n05" target="#a05" rend="pre(*)place(end)">
        <p>The travels of <persName>Abu Taleb</persName> were written by himself in
	  <lb/>the <name>Persian language</name>, and translated by <persName>Charles Stewart</persName>,
	  <lb/>Esq. M. A. S. Professor of <name>Oriental languages</name>, in the
	  <lb/><name>Honorable East India Company's College</name>, <placeName>Herts</placeName>.</p>
      </note>
</notes></hyperDiv>
    <front>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <milestone unit="sig" n="A1r"/>
      <titleBlock>
        <titlePart><lb/>Conversations
<lb/>Principally on
	    <lb/>The <name>Aborigines</name><lb/>of
	    <lb/><placeName>North America</placeName>.</titlePart>
        <respLine>
          <docRole type="author">
            <add hand="#unknown.zzx">[By <persName>Mrs. Elizabeth (Elkins) 
Sanders</persName>]</add>
          </docRole>
        </respLine>
        <epigraph rend="pre(#rule)post(#rule)">
          <quote rend="pre()post()">
            <lg type="poem" rend="indent(+1)" subtype="indeterminate">
              <l rend="indent(+2)">With pious awe</l>
              <l>Their eye uplifted sought the bidden path</l>
              <l>Of the Great Spirit. The loud midnight storm,</l>
              <l>The rush of mighty waters, the deep roll</l>
              <l>of thunder gave his voice; the golden sun,</l>
              <l>The soft effulgence of the purple morn,</l>
              <l>The gentle rain distilling, was his smile</l>
              <l>Dispensing good to all.</l>
            </lg>
          </quote>
          <bibl rend="align(right)">
            <title>Traits of the <name>Aborigines</name>.</title>
          </bibl>
        </epigraph>
        <lb/>
        <docImprint rend="case(allcaps)align(center)"><pubPlace><placeName>Salem</placeName></pubPlace>:
	  <lb/><docRole type="publisher"><persName>W.</persName> and <persName>S. B. Ives</persName></docRole>, <placeName>Washington Street</placeName>.
<lb/><docDate when="1829">1829</docDate></docImprint>
        <pb n="2"/>
        <milestone unit="sig" n="A1v"/>
        <lb/>
        <docImprint rend="case(mixed)align(center)pre(#rule)">Printed at the 
	  <name><title>Salem Observer</title> Office</name></docImprint>
      </titleBlock>
      <pb n="3"/>
      <milestone unit="sig" n="A2r"/>
      <div type="prefatory">
        <head>Introduction.</head>
        <p>In making this compilation it has been my earnest
<lb/>wish to engage the sympathy of the youth of our country
	  <lb/>in favour of our <name>Aborigines</name>, in the hope that by being
<lb/>made acquainted with their character and unmerited suf­
<lb/>ferings, an interest would be excited which might rescue
<lb/>from utter ruin this persecuted and ill fated race. The
<lb/>digressions were principally made with a view to prove
<lb/>that colour or climate have no influence over the mind,
	  <lb/>and (in conformity with <name>Scripture</name>) to show that the Al­
<lb/>mighty is without any variableness or shadow of turning.
<lb/>The same yesterday, to day, and forever, and that His
	  <lb/>tender mercies are over <emph>all</emph> His works. Could these im­
<lb/>pressions be firmly implanted in the mind, we, who bear
	  <lb/>the name of <name>Christians</name>, should be freed from those nar­
<lb/>row prejudices, and supercilious feelings, which lead us
<lb/>vainly to imagine ourselves to be the peculiar favourites
<lb/>of heaven; and thus to foster our pride by the notice
<lb/>that, notwithstanding our multiplied offences, we are still
<lb/>superiour to all who have existed before our era, and to
<lb/>most of the present inhabitants of the earth.—Whilst we
<lb/>fondly cling to these unworthy prejudices it appears to
<lb/>me obvious, that we shall be wanting in a stimulous to
<lb/>improvement, or to reform abuses.</p>
        <pb n="4"/>
        <milestone unit="sig" n="A2v"/>
        <mw type="pageNum">iv</mw>
        <p>I have also endeavored to show that the light which
<lb/>lighteth every one that cometh into the world, is all suffi­
<lb/>cient, if rightly improved, to secure his present and eter­
<lb/>nal happiness; and that it is the same true and divine
	  <lb/>light which the ever blessed Jesus was sent to restore
<lb/>and confirm; but which had been greatly obscured by
<lb/>the indulgence of corrupt propensities and passions.</p>
        <p>It is a solemn truth, which cannot be too strongly im­
<lb/>pressed on the mind, that nations, like individuals, have
<lb/>their periods of growth, maturity and decline; like them
<lb/>enjoy happiness and prosperity, or decay and adversity,
<lb/>in proportion as they improve or abuse the gifts of 
<lb/>heaven.</p>
        <p>From the impartial investigations  of some of the best
<lb/>and most intelligent men, we find that in all the great
<lb/>nations who have passed away, the arts and sciences 
<lb/>have been cultivated with success, and philosophical in­
<lb/>vestigations pursued with nearly the same results as at
<lb/>the present period. Above all, One Supreme Father of
<lb/>the Universe has ever received the true adoration and
<lb/>gratitude of mankind, however varied may have been
<lb/>their forms of worship. It is however painful and humil­
<lb/>iating to find that, notwithstanding much superstition
<lb/>and ignorance prevailed in former ages, and prevails at
<lb/>present in heathen countries, respecting the moral attri­
<lb/>butes of God, nothing is found so truly debasing and de­
<lb/>rogatory to the character of the Universal Parent, as the
	  <lb/>dogmas maintained by the great portion of nominal <name>chris­
<lb/>tians</name>, at the present period.</p>
        <p>Notwithstanding the strong desire manifested by many
<lb/>to support the superiority of the moderns, over the an­
<pb n="5"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="A3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">v</mw>
<lb/>cient inhabitants of the earth, it is demonstrable from the
<lb/>works which still remain, to attest their wonderful inge­
<lb/>nuity and perseverance both in sculpture and architec­
<lb/>ture, that in these we are greatly their inferiors. If in
<lb/>some instances we have carried to greater perfection
<lb/>some of the arts, they may serve as a counterpoise to
<lb/>those in which the ancients excelled; and the progress
	  <lb/>made by the <name>Hindoos</name>, and others, in the science of astro­
<lb/>nomy, proves beyond doubt that their knowledge, how­
<lb/>ever obtained, produced the same results, as the most
<lb/>approved methods or systems of the moderns.</p>
        <p>In closing this brief analysis I ask, are we better than
<lb/>those nations who have been doomed to destruction for
<lb/>their cruelty, their stupid bigotry, and overweening pride?
<lb/>Has there ever been in former ages any system of servi­
<lb/>tude so truly shocking to humanity, as the slavery to
	  <lb/>which we have subjected the natives of <placeName>Africa</placeName>? Is not
<lb/>the land perpetually moistened with the blood of its na­
<lb/>tive children, and do we not with the most persevering
<lb/>barbarity persist in forcing them from every place where
<lb/>they have found rest, and pertinaciously insist that they
<lb/>are incapable of civilization; whilst we compel them to
<lb/>quit their cultivated fields, and the beloved homes of their
<lb/>fathers, and banish them to a wilderness, to which they 
<lb/>have expressed a decided aversion, to gratify an insatia­
	  <lb/>ble cupidity. Influenced by the same spirit, our <name>Aborigi­
<lb/>nes</name> are represented as heathen, who are unable to com­
	  <lb/>prehend the sublime doctrines of <name>Christianity</name>, because
<lb/>they cannot bend their reason to embrace the debasing
<lb/>superstitions which have been presented to them, and
<lb/>how before the idols we have set up. Can we then hope
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">A2</mw>
<pb n="6"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="A3v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">vi</mw>
<lb/>to escape the fate of those nations who founded their em­
<lb/>pire in blood and perfidy. The agonized cries and groans,
<lb/>of the miserable victims we hold in bondage, will call
<lb/>down the vengeance of heaven on our blood stained
<lb/>country, and the burning tears which furrow the manly
	  <lb/>cheeks of our indignant <name>Indians</name>, exasperated almost to
<lb/>frenzy by their wrongs, will rise up as a memorial against
<lb/>us before the Throne of God.</p>
        <p>The hour of retribution must arrive, and will not long
<lb/>be delayed, unless we allow the divine influences of our
<lb/>benign religion to direct our ways, and lying aside all
<lb/>unhallowed prejudices, and the sins which most easily
	  <lb/>beset us, unite as <name>christians</name>, to undo the heavy burdens,
<lb/>and let the oppressed go free. <quote>We need not search out
<lb/>the dark corners of the earth</quote> to reform abuses, or to
<lb/>overcome superstition, too much is required at home, and
<lb/>nothing would, in my apprehension, so greatly facilitate
<lb/>our success abroad, as the glorious example we have it in
<lb/>our power to exhibit, and thus should we fulfil the divine
<lb/>behest, and let our light so shine before men, that they
<lb/>seeing our good works may glorify our heavenly Father.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <pb n="7"/>
    <milestone unit="sig" n="A4r"/>
    <body type="tract">
     
        <head>Conversations.</head>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> What is meant Mother by the con­
	  <lb/>troversy between <placeName>Georgia</placeName> and the <name>Creeks</name>, of
<lb/>which so much is said in the papers, and who
	  <lb/>are the <name>Creeks</name>?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> The <name>Creeks</name> were once a powerful
<lb/>people who possessed a large tract of country in
	  <lb/><placeName>Georgia</placeName>. In a late number of the <name>New York
<lb/>Review</name> there is an article, entitled <title>an examina­
	  <lb/>tion of the controversy between <placeName>Georgia</placeName> and the
	  <lb/><name>Creeks</name></title>, which states <quote>that shortly after the ac­
	    <lb/>cession of the patriotic and venerable <persName>Washing­
<lb/>ton</persName> to the chief magistracy of the republic, a
	    <lb/>treaty was concluded at <placeName>New York</placeName> in his very
	    <lb/>presence with the <name>Creek Nation</name>. These par­
<lb/>ticulars are mentioned, that the sanction of that
<lb/>great and good man to the humane policy of the
<lb/>government may have its due weight with all
<lb/>who respect the purity and sagacity of the father
<pb n="8"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="A4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">8</mw>
	    <lb/>of his country. By this treaty the <placeName>United States</placeName>
	    <lb/>took the <name>Creeks</name> under their protection, guaran­
<lb/>teed to the tribes their land within specific limits;
<lb/>settled the manner in which offenders should be
<lb/>punished; and in order to lead them to a great­
<lb/>er degree of civilization, instead of remaining in the
	    <lb/>state of hunters, the <placeName>United States</placeName> agreed to fur­
	    <lb/>nish, gratuitously, the <name>Creeks</name>, from time to time,
<lb/>with useful domestic animals, and implements of 
	    <lb/>husbandry.</quote> This treaty bears date <date when="1790-08-07"><name>August</name> 7th,
	    <lb/>1790</date>. <quote>Thus it appears that the <placeName>United States</placeName>
	  <lb/>at that time offered inducements to the <name>Creeks</name>
<lb/>to become cultivators of the soil, and to appro­
<lb/>priate it for the purposes of civilized life, instead
<lb/>of using it as mere hunting ground. If they
<lb/>yielded to these inducements, the public faith is
<lb/>pledged to sustain them in that course. Our
<lb/>government is bound, our national character
<lb/>plighted, to encourage them in the wise resolu­
<lb/>tion they have taken, to become civilized men,
<lb/>and to preserve the remnant of their tribe under
<lb/>the protection of this republic.</quote></p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> Have the <name>Creeks</name> yielded to the
<lb/>proposal of our government, and are they now 
<lb/>civilized?</p>
        <pb n="9"/>
        <milestone unit="sig" n="A5r"/>
        <mw type="pageNum">9</mw>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> The writer of this article proceeds to
<lb/>say, <quote>the pledge has been accepted, and on our
<lb/>part it only remains to fulfil it. In <date when="1796">1796</date>, another
	    <lb/>treaty was concluded between the <placeName>United States</placeName>
	    <lb/>and the <name>Creeks</name>, and they bargained for black­
	    <lb/>smiths and strikers to be furnished by the <placeName>United
<lb/>States</placeName>; thus plainly showing their intention to ac­
<lb/>cept the humane offer of civilization from our
<lb/>hands.</quote> I will, my dear girls, hereafter give you
	  <lb/>some accounts of the <name>Creeks</name>, from the very inter­
	  <lb/>esting travels of <persName>Bartram</persName>, who visited this people
<lb/>on his tour through that part of the country they
<lb/>inhabit, and gives a most pleasing picture of the
<lb/>rural simplicity, and hospitality which prevails in
	  <lb/>the <name>Creek Nation</name>. You will then be able to judge
<lb/>how far they have complied with the requisition
	  <lb/>made them by the <placeName>United States</placeName>; but I must
<lb/>now proceed as briefly as I may to state the
<lb/>grounds of the controversy. <quote>With these obli­
	    <lb/>gations subsisting on the part of the <placeName>United
	      <lb/>States</placeName>, an agreement was entered into with <placeName>Geor­
	      <lb/>gia</placeName> in <date when="1802">1802</date>, by which the <placeName>United States</placeName> agreed
<lb/>to extinguish at their expense, for the use of 
	    <lb/><placeName>Georgia</placeName>, the Indian title to all the lands within
<lb/>the limits of the State, <quote rend="pre(‘)post(’)">as early as the same 
<lb/>could be peaceably obtained on reasonable
<pb n="10"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="A5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">10</mw>
	      <lb/>terms.</quote> The consideration given by <placeName>Georgia</placeName>,
<lb/>on her part, was the relinquishment of all claims
<lb/>to the vacant territory in the West, included
<lb/>within her boundary.</quote></p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> Why did the <placeName>United States</placeName> agree to
<lb/>extinguish the Indian title to these lands? Did 
	  <lb/>they suppose the <name>Creeks</name> would ever part with 
<lb/>their native country voluntarily?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> It was certainly wrong to make such
<lb/>a compromise with the <name>Georgians</name>, as the strong
	  <lb/>attachment of the <name>Indians</name> for their native soil
<lb/>was well known; but since we have become
	  <lb/>powerful, little attention has been given to the 
	  <lb/>rights of the <name>Indians</name>; the <name>Georgians</name> in particu­
<lb/>lar, appear wholly insensible to the claims of
<lb/>justice or humanity, and evince a determination
<lb/>at all events to drive the natives from the small
<lb/>portion of territory they still possess, though the
	  <lb/><name>Creeks</name> with the expectation of being suffered to
<lb/>remain in their country, <quote>have at different peri­
	    <lb/>ods ceded to the <placeName>United States</placeName> 15,000,000 of
<lb/>acres which have been vested in Georgia, which
<lb/>State has also received 1,250,000 dollars as an
	    <lb/>equivalent for the lands ceded to the <placeName>United
<lb/>States</placeName> by it. During the last war a portion of the
	    <lb/><name>Creeks</name>, instigated by hostile emissaries, and in­
<pb n="11"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="A6r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">11</mw>
<lb/>fluenced by misrepresentations as to the inten­
	    <lb/>tions of the <placeName>United States</placeName> with regard to the
	    <lb/><name>Indians</name>, took up arms against the whites, and
	    <lb/>were severely chastised by the army under <persName>Gen.
<lb/>Jackson</persName>. In <date when="1814">1814</date>, articles of agreement were
<lb/>concluded with the whole nation, including the
<lb/>hostile party, by which peace was restored, a
<lb/>certain portion of Indian territory ceded, and in
	    <lb/>the second article the <placeName>United States</placeName> guaranty
<lb/>the integrity of all the Creek territory not ceded
<lb/>in the first article. This treaty or agreement,
	    <lb/>the <name>Creeks</name> considered as definitive, and as set­
<lb/>tling the boundaries within which they were to
<lb/>reside as a civilized people, according to the
<lb/>promises of our government. In conformity with
<lb/>that sentiment, shortly after that treaty, they
<lb/>passed laws constituting it a capital crime to pro­
<lb/>pose any further alienation of their land.</quote></p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> In what manner were these unfor­
	  <lb/>tunate <name>Indians</name> chastised?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> An account is given of this bloody
<lb/>transaction in a beautifully written article, on
<lb/>traits of Indian character, which appeared in the
	  <lb/><title>Analectic Magazine</title> during the late war. <quote>The
	    <lb/>punishment of the <name>Creeks</name> has been pitiless and
<lb/>terrible,</quote> says this humane and truly philosophic
<pb n="12"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="A6v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">12</mw>
<lb/>writer, <quote>vengeance has gone like a devouring
<lb/>fire through their country—the smoke of their
<lb/>villages yet rises to heaven, and the blood of the 
	    <lb/>slaughtered <name>Indians</name> yet reeks upon the earth.
<lb/>Of this merciless ravage an idea may be formed
<lb/>by a single exploit, boastfully set forth in an offi­
<lb/>cial letter that has darkened our public journals.<anchor xml:id="a01" rend="pre(*)" corresp="#n01"/>
<lb/>A detachment of soldiery had been sent under
	    <lb/>the command of one <persName>Gen. Coffee</persName> to destroy the
	    <lb/><name>Tallushatches</name> towns, where the hostile <name>Creeks</name>
<lb/>had assembled. The enterprise was executed,
<lb/>as the commander in chief expresses it, <soCalled>in style</soCalled>— 
<lb/>but in the name of heaven what style! The
<lb/>towns were surrounded before the break of day.
<lb/>The inhabitants starting from their sleep flew to
<lb/>arms, with beat of drums, and hideous cries.
<lb/>The soldiery pressed upon them on every side,
<lb/>and met with a desperate resistance—but what was
<lb/>savage valour against the array and discipline of
	    <lb/>scientific warfare? The <name>Creeks</name> made gallant
<lb/>charges, but were beaten back by overwhelming
<lb/>numbers. Hemmed in like savage beasts sur­
<lb/>rounded by the hunters, wherever they turned 
<lb/>they met a foe, and in every foe they found a
<lb/>butcher. <quote rend="pre(‘)post(’)">The enemy retired firing,</quote> says <persName>Cof­
<pb n="13"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="B1r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">13</mw>
<lb/>fee</persName> in his letter, <quote rend="pre(‘)post(’)">until they got around, and in
<lb/>their buildings, where they made all the resist­
<lb/>ance that an overpowered soldiery could do;
<lb/>they fought as long as one existed, but their
<lb/>destruction was very soon completed; our men
<lb/>rushed up to the doors of the houses, and in a
<lb/>few minutes killed the last warrior of them; the 
<lb/>enemy fought with savage fury, and met death
<lb/>with all its horrors, without shrinking or com­
<lb/>plaining; not one asked to be spared, but fought 
<lb/>so long as they could stand or sit. In conse­
<lb/>quence of their flying to their houses, and mixing
<lb/>with their families, our men in killing the males,
<lb/>without intention <emph>killed and wounded a few of
<lb/>the squaws and children</emph>. So unsparing was the
<lb/>carnage of the sword, that not one of the war­
<lb/>riors escaped to carry the heart-breaking tidings
<lb/>to the remainder of the tribe.</quote> Such is what is
<lb/>termed executing hostilities <soCalled>in style</soCalled>! Let those
<lb/>who exclaim with abhorrence against Indian 
<lb/>inroads—those who are so eloquent about the
<lb/>bitterness of Indian recrimination—let them turn
	    <lb/>to the horrible victory of <persName>Gen. Coffee</persName>, and be
<lb/>silent.</quote></p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> I thought mother that <name>christians</name>
	  <lb/>were not so cruel as <name>Indians</name>, but I hope none of
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">B</mw>
<pb n="14"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="B1v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">14</mw>
	  <lb/>our countrymen, beside this <persName>Gen. Coffee</persName>, could
<lb/>have acted so barbarously and so basely?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> It would indeed be highly consola­
<lb/>tory to be assured of this, but though the details
	  <lb/>of our warfare against the unfortunate <name>Creeks</name>
<lb/>appear to have been studiously concealed from
	  <lb/>the public eye, we know that a similar outrage 
<lb/>was perpetrated by <persName>Gen. Jackson</persName>, <quote>who, in <date when="1818">1818</date>,
	    <lb/>destroyed the <placeName>Chehaw villages</placeName>, when for the 
<lb/>space of three days the country was ravaged, the
<lb/>houses burned, the provisions destroyed, the men
<lb/>slaughtered, and the women made captives.</quote></p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> Was it not <persName>Gen. Jackson</persName> who so
<lb/>bravely defended the country when invaded by
	  <lb/>the <name>Britons</name>?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> Yes he did so, and gained great ap­
<lb/>plause, but his conduct subsequently has proved
<lb/>that he was influenced more by passion, and
<lb/>hatred, than by principle or patriotism. In his
	  <lb/>campaign against the <name>Creeks</name> he evinced a total
<lb/>disregard for justice or humanity—by his own au­
<lb/>thority, and in defiance of the award of a Court 
<lb/>Martial, he condemned to an ignominious death
	  <lb/>two <name>Englishmen</name>, who had resided for sometime
<lb/>in the Creek country as traders, on the pretext
	  <lb/>of their having incited the <name>Creeks</name> to resent the 
<pb n="15"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="B2r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">15</mw>
<lb/>injuries they had sustained; and a venerable In­
<lb/>dian sage, whom they called the prophet, was put
<lb/>to death for a like offence, with barbarous exul­
	  <lb/>tation. That <persName>Gen. Jackson</persName> only wanted power
	  <lb/>to become a second <persName>Robespiere</persName>, we are assured
<lb/>from his own declaration. Writing to a friend
<lb/>he hesitates not to declare, that he would with­
<lb/>out scruple have hanged a number of our best,
<lb/>and most intelligent citizens, who during the
	  <lb/>late war convened at <placeName>Hartford</placeName> to consult on the
<lb/>best means of defence, and for the restoration of
<lb/>peace on just and honorable terms.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> What objection could <persName>Gen. Jack­
	    <lb/>son</persName> have to this meeting at <placeName>Hartford</placeName>?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> None I believe, except his desire to
<lb/>prolong the horrours of war, which it appears
<lb/>was the sphere of action best suited to his feel­
<lb/>ings and interest. I have been told he pos­
<lb/>sesses a large and valuable tract of land which
	  <lb/>he has wrested from the <name>Indians</name>. In destroying
	  <lb/>the <placeName>Chehaw villages</placeName>, which were beautifully situ­
	  <lb/>ated in the vale of the <placeName>Flint river</placeName>, another con­
<lb/>siderable portion of Indian territory was ceded
<lb/>to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, as I have before mentioned,
	  <lb/>and the <name>Creeks</name> vainly hoped they should be per­
<lb/>mitted to occupy as a civilized people, (relying
<pb n="16"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="B2v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">16</mw>
<lb/>on the faith of our Government,) the little that
<lb/>remained of their extensive domain. <quote>Under
	    <lb/>these circumstances <persName>Troup</persName> became Governor of
	    <lb/><placeName>Georgia</placeName> by a very small majority of votes, and
<lb/>in order, it is presumed, to secure his future
<lb/>election, he determined at any rate to get pos­
<lb/>session of the lands which remained in the
	    <lb/>posession of the <name>Creeks</name>, for the purpose of dis­
<lb/>tributing them by a land lottery, that he might
<lb/>thus have an opportunity of presenting his ad­
	    <lb/>herents with each a ticket. <persName>Gov. Troup</persName>, influ­
<lb/>enced by this desire, sought to drive the govern­
	    <lb/>ment of the <placeName>United States</placeName> into a hostile attitude
	    <lb/>towards the <name>Creeks</name>, by insisting on the right of
	    <lb/><placeName>Georgia</placeName> to their lands. The general govern­
<lb/>ment, in compliance with its agreement with
	    <lb/>that State, endeavoured to persuade the <name>Indians</name>
<lb/>to cede their land or a portion of it, and appro­
	    <lb/>priations were made to <choice><sic>o</sic><corr>a</corr></choice>ffect that object. The
	    <lb/><name>Creeks</name>, by their acknowledged representatives,
<lb/>declared their determination not to sell another
	    <lb/>acre. At the conference in <date when="1824-11"><name>November</name></date>, <persName>Col's.
	      <lb/>Campbell</persName> and <persName>Merriwether</persName>, the Creek chieftains,
<lb/>declared, that in conformity with our recommen­
<lb/>dations, they had undertaken to cultivate the
<lb/>soil, and <unclear reason="flawed-reproduction">to bree</unclear>d cattle; that they had no more
<pb n="17"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="B3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">17</mw>
<lb/>land than was sufficient for their purpose; and
<lb/>that upon no consideration, would they part with
	    <lb/>another acre. These <placeName>Georgia</placeName> commissioners,
<lb/>acting no doubt with the advice and knowledge
	    <lb/>of the Governor, then proceeded to <placeName>Washington</placeName>,
	    <lb/>where they arrived in <date when="1824-12"><name>December</name></date>, and represent­
	    <lb/>ed the inclinations of the <name>Creeks</name> to sell to favour­
<lb/>ably, as to procure a farther appropriation for that
<lb/>purpose, carefully suppressing their declared re­
<lb/>solution not to part with another acre. This was
<lb/>the commencement of a system of fraud and mis­
<lb/>representation highly discreditable to all concern­
	    <lb/>ed in it. <persName>Gen. William M‘Intosh</persName>, a known and 
	    <lb/>steady friend of <placeName>Georgia</placeName>, was inclined to yield to
<lb/>the wishes of the State government. He was
	    <lb/>the head chief of the <name>Coweta tribe</name>, and the
<lb/>State authorities, together with the commission­
<lb/>ers, determined to use him and his partizans to 
<lb/>defraud the nation of its territory. In order to
	    <lb/>secure the influence of <persName>M‘Intosh</persName>, he was ap­
<lb/>pointed agent for the lands which were to be 
<lb/>transferred, and by a separate or additional arti­
<lb/>cle of this treaty, it was stipulated to give <emph rend="face(blackletter)slant(upright)">25,000</emph>
<lb/>dollars for a piece of land belonging to him,
	    <lb/>called the <placeName>Indian Spring Reservation</placeName>—a price,
<lb/>which to say the least, was very liberal. A sum­
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">B2</mw>
<pb n="18"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="B3v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">18</mw>
	    <lb/>mons was then issued to the <name>Creeks</name>, calling a
	    <lb/>meeting at these very springs, <persName>M‘Intosh</persName> not dar­
<lb/>ing to trust himself in the midst of the nation,
<lb/>as he knew he was answerable to the law, mak­
<lb/>ing it a capital offence to propose a further al<choice><sic>eni</sic><corr>ien</corr></choice>a­
	    <lb/>tion of lands. This law was proposed at <placeName>Broken
	      <lb/>Arrow</placeName>, shortly after <persName>Jackson's</persName> treaty in <date when="1811">1811</date>, by
	    <lb/><persName>M‘Intosh</persName> himself, and formally re-enacted at a
	    <lb/>meeting of the <name>Creeks</name> at <placeName>Polecat Springs</placeName> in
<lb/><date when="1824">1824</date>, in order to put a stop to the negotiations
	    <lb/>concerning their lands. As the <placeName>Indian Springs</placeName>
<lb/>were at a distance from a majority of the tribes,
<lb/>and the notice to attend was given but a few 
<lb/>days before the time of the meeting, only a few of
<lb/>the chieftains met the commissioners, and of
<lb/>these, only two signed the treaty, one of whom,
	    <lb/>it is asserted by one of the <placeName>United States</placeName> agents,
<lb/>is not a head chief, or representative of any In­
<lb/>dian town. The other chiefs, four in number,
<lb/>upon being informed that the object of the meet­
<lb/>ing was to purchase their land, refused to give
<lb/>their consent, and left the council. The nego­
	    <lb/>ciation was however continued by the commis­
	    <lb/>sioners, with <persName>M‘Intosh</persName> and his party, and a treaty
<lb/>concluded by which all the Creek lands in the 
	    <lb/>State of <placeName>Georgia</placeName> were ceded to the <placeName>United States</placeName>.
<pb n="19"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="B4r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">19</mw>
	    <lb/>This treaty was signed by <persName>M‘Intosh</persName> and one
<lb/>more chief, the other Indian signers not being
<lb/>chiefs nor representatives of towns, and having
<lb/>no legal right to sign the treaty on behalf of the 
	    <lb/><name>Creeks</name>, which they did at the instigation of
	    <lb/><persName>M‘Intosh</persName>. It is a strong argument against its
	    <lb/>validity, that with the exception of <persName>M‘Intosh</persName>, and
	    <lb/><persName>Etomine Tustunnuggee</persName>, none of the Creek chief­
<lb/>tains with whom the Creek treaties have been
<lb/>usually concluded, appear to have signed or sanc­
<lb/>tioned this treaty, so vitally important to their
<lb/>welfare.</quote></p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> What a base transaction, but I trust 
<lb/>our government will not suffer the <name>Creeks</name> to be
<lb/>driven from their pleasant homes, which they so
<lb/>highly value?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> The writer from whom I have ex­
<lb/>tracted the circumstances I have related to you,
<lb/>after narrating many other facts in proof of the
	  <lb/>fraud and corruption of <persName>Troup</persName> and his partizans,
<lb/><quote>all of which,</quote> he says, <quote rend="post()">is openly, and un­
	    <lb/>blushingly defended by the executive of <placeName>Georgia</placeName>,
<lb/>the indecorous style of whose notes to the late
	    <lb/>President of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and the Secretary
<lb/>of War, would be unworthy of observation, did
<lb/>they not evince the character of the person at
<pb n="20"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="B4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">20</mw>
<lb/>the head of that unfortunate State. They prove
<lb/>him,</quote> (he continues,) <quote rend="pre()">to be entirely regardless of
<lb/>public opinion and public faith, and show a ne­
<lb/>cessity of energetic measures on the part of the
<lb/>constitutional authorities, to preserve the quiet
<lb/>and the character of the country.</quote> At the close of
<lb/>this article the writer proceeds to say, <quote>that in
<lb/>order to prevent any examination of these dis­
<lb/>graceful transactions by the National govern­
	    <lb/>ment, this treaty was sent to <placeName>Washington</placeName> with 
<lb/>the greatest despatch, on the nineteenth day after
<lb/>it had been concluded in the western wilderness
	    <lb/>of <placeName>Georgia</placeName>; it was laid before the <orgName>Senate</orgName> of the
	    <lb/><placeName>United States</placeName> at <placeName>Washington</placeName>, the very last day
<lb/>of its session. The treaty was concluded on the
	    <lb/><date when="1825-02-12">12th of <name>February</name> last</date>, and was transmitted to
	    <lb/><persName>Mr. Calhoun</persName>, and by him handed to the then
	    <lb/>President on the <date when="1825-03-02">2d of <name>March</name></date>, with his advice of
<lb/>course for its ratification, as it was fair upon its
<lb/>face, and accomplished an object which the
	    <lb/><placeName>United States</placeName> felt desirous of effecting when it
<lb/>could properly be done. The next day, having
<lb/>been approved of by the President, it was sent to
<lb/>the <orgName>Senate</orgName>, and thus committed to that body be­
	  <lb/>fore the inauguration of <persName>Mr. Adams</persName>, who receiv­
<lb/>ed it after his accession to the Presidency from
<pb n="21"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="B5r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">21</mw>
<lb/>the <orgName>Senate</orgName>, for his signature, that body having
<lb/>ratified it. It thus appears, that the managers
<lb/>of this business transmitted the treaty from the
	  <lb/>western part of <placeName>Georgia</placeName> with such despatch, as
	  <lb/>to prevent those <name>Indians</name> who might be opposed
<lb/>to the sale of the lands, from being heard at 
	  <lb/><placeName>Washington</placeName> before its ratification. It is more­
	  <lb/>over asserted by <persName>Mr. Compere</persName>, the resident mis­
	  <lb/>sionary in the <name>Creek nation</name>, that the <name>Creeks</name>,
<lb/>confiding in the benevolence and justice of our
<lb/>government, were persuaded that the govern­
<lb/>ment would not regard this as a treaty, because 
<lb/>it was not made with the consent of the nation.
<lb/>If this be the case, and there is no reason to
<lb/>doubt it, a fraud has been practised upon the <name>In­
<lb/>dians</name>, which it concerns the character of the
<lb/>country to disclaim.</quote></p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> But mother our government would
<lb/>not assuredly consent to ratify such a treaty, and
	  <lb/>allow the <name>Creeks</name> to be driven from their country
	  <lb/>by these rapacious <name>Georgians</name>?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> The President with dignified firm­
<lb/>ness disannuled the treaty, when informed of the
<lb/>fraudulent manner by which it was obtained, and
	  <lb/>insisted that the <name>Georgians</name> should discontinue
<lb/>the survey of the land which they had already
<pb n="22"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="B5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">22</mw>
<lb/>begun, and an armed force was commanded to
<lb/>see the order carried into execution. Neverthe­
	  <lb/>less the menaces and insults of <persName>Gov. Troup</persName> ap­
<lb/>pears to have silenced the spirit of indignant
<lb/>rebuke, and chastisement, which was at first
	  <lb/>called forth to defend the rights of the <name>Indians</name>,
<lb/>and thus maintain the honor and integrity of the
<lb/>country; but amid the commotions of faction, and
<lb/>desire of popularity, our government now ap­
	  <lb/>pears willing to aid the <name>Georgians</name> in their nefa­
	  <lb/>rious bargain, and we are told that the <name>Creeks</name>
<lb/>have consented to sell their country and depart
<lb/>to a land which has little to recommend it, ex­
	  <lb/>cept its being so undesirable, that the <name>Indians</name>
<lb/>may remain there unmolested. Here however
<lb/>they will come in contact with hostile tribes, and
<lb/>be moreover subjected to an uncontroled military 
<lb/>force, which under various pretences may per­
<lb/>petually harass, and finally destroy them—nor
<lb/>do I hazard any thing by these suggestions, as
<lb/>the numerous tribes who have thus miserably
<lb/>perished attest they are not the idle anticipations
<lb/>of fancy. I have here the talk of an aged Indian
	  <lb/>chief, of the <name>Creek nation</name>, to <persName>Gen. Jackson</persName>, which
	  <lb/>is expressive of the strong sense the <name>Indians</name>
<lb/>have of their wrongs, and their attachment to
<pb n="23"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="B6r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">23</mw>
<lb/>their country:—<said rend="pre(“)post(”)">Brother! the Red people
<lb/>were very numerous. They covered the land
<lb/>like the trees of the forest, from the big waters
<lb/>of the east to the great sea, where rests the set­
<lb/>ting sun. The white people come—they drove
<lb/>them from forest to forest, from river to river—
<lb/>the bones of our fathers strewed the path of their
<lb/>wandering. Brother, you are now strong: we
<lb/>melt away like the snow of spring before the
<lb/>rising sun. Wither must we now go? Must
<lb/>we leave the home of our fathers, and go to a
<lb/>strange land beyond the great river of the West?
<lb/>That land is dark and desolate—we shall have
<lb/>no pleasure in it. Pleasant are the fields of our
<lb/>youth—We love the woods where our fathers,
<lb/>led us to the chase—Their bones lie by the run­
<lb/>ning stream, where we sported in the days of our
<lb/>childhood—When we are gone, strangers will
<lb/>dig them up—The Great Spirit made us all—
<lb/>you have land enough—Leave us then the fields
<lb/>of our youth, and the woods where our fathers
<lb/>led us to the chase—Permit us to remain in
<lb/>peace under the shade of our own trees—Let us
<lb/>watch over the graves of our fathers, by the
<lb/>streams of our childhood—May the Great Spirit
<lb/>move the heart of our father, the President, that
<pb n="24"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="B6v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">24</mw>
<lb/>he may open his ear to the voice of his children,
<lb/>for they are sorrowful.</said></p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> Oh mother, if <persName>Washington</persName> had
	  <lb/>been President, the <name>Creeks</name> would not have in­
	  <lb/>treated for justice in vain, he would have been 
<lb/>the friend and protector of the <name>Indians</name>.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> <persName>Washington</persName> was truly great and 
<lb/>magnanimous, he was ever guided by wisdom 
<lb/>and an intuitive sense of justice, which prompted
<lb/>him to disdain artifice or collusion, (the steady
<lb/>purposes of his soul were unchanged by the com­
<lb/>motions of faction or the workings of ambition,)
<lb/>and the defenceless state of the <name>Indians</name> would 
<lb/>unquestionably have engaged his sympathy and
<lb/>protection; yet with avaricious and unprincipled
<lb/>men, the weakness of the <name>Indians</name> is a powerful
<lb/>incentive to take advantage of the<choice><sic/><corr>i</corr></choice>r inability to 
<lb/>resist their unjust demands. Men, like <persName>Wash­
<lb/>ington</persName>, seldom appear to bless mankind, they
<lb/>are found like, <quote>angels visits, few and far be­
<lb/>tween;</quote> nevertheless, we might surely expect 
<lb/>that those who have filled his exalted station,
<lb/>would emulate those high endowments which
<lb/>have made <persName>Washington</persName> the benefactor of his
<lb/>country and insured for him immortal renown.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> But why have the <name>Creeks</name> consented
<pb n="25"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="C1r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">25</mw>
<lb/>to sell their land, after having so repeatedly de­
<lb/>clared their resolution not to part with another
<lb/>acre?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> If it be true, it is doubtless in con­
<lb/>sequence of their having been made sensible that
<lb/>they will no longer be protected by the govern­
<lb/>ment; we were informed by the public journals,
<lb/>some time since, that the troops stationed for
<lb/>their defence, were ordered to remove, and the
	  <lb/><name>Creeks</name> well knew what to expect from neigh­
	  <lb/>bours like the <name>Georgians</name>. The <name>Creeks</name> may
<lb/>plant, but will not be allowed to gather the in­
	  <lb/>crease—they may raise cattle, but the <name>Georgians</name>
<lb/>will appropriate them to their own use—and
<lb/>should any resistance be made, it will be a sig­
<lb/>nal for hostile incursions into the territory of the 
	  <lb/><name>Creeks</name>, which would without doubt involve in
<lb/>ruin the whole nation—similar to that, which on
<lb/>a like occasion, not long since, swept with
	  <lb/>destructive violence over the <placeName>Ricaree Villages</placeName>,
<lb/>and blotted them from the face of the earth.
<lb/>Such too has been the fate of many other tribes,
<lb/>which might here be mentioned.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> You remember <persName>Eliza</persName>, when we
<lb/>looked at that map the other day, what a long
<lb/>way the whole nation would be obliged to travel,
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">C</mw>
<pb n="26"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="C1v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">26</mw>
<lb/>and you fancied that you heard the lamentations
<lb/>of the Creek women.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> Oh yes, I pictured to myself their
<lb/>sufferings, and their despair on leaving their
<lb/>habitations,—their fruitful orchards, and delight­
<lb/>ful country, to encounter a journey so long and
<lb/>fatiguing, so replete with hardships—I thought
<lb/>how many of the aged and infirm would droop
<lb/>and die in the wilderness, and what would be­
<lb/>come of the little children who, unused to hard­
<lb/>ships, had passed their days sporting on the
<lb/>green turf before the doors of their rural habita­
<lb/>tions. I reflected how comfortless would be the
<lb/>place assigned them for their abode, when those
<lb/>who survived the perilous journey had reached
<lb/>their destined home, surrounded by hostile tribes,
<lb/>with no friendly eye to greet them, and I fancied
<lb/>I heard them indignantly exclaim, after so many
<lb/>promises broken, <quote>what new pledges can you 
<lb/>give us that we will not again be exiled, when
<lb/>it is your wish to possess these lands.</quote> But 
<lb/>mother, when I speak of this to some they smile,
<lb/>and appear to think me an enthusiast.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> Unfortunately there are many who
<lb/>appear to think it vain to oppose the doom of ex­
<lb/>termination, which they contend has gone out
<pb n="27"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="C2r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">27</mw>
	  <lb/>against our <name>Aborigines</name>, and <quote>which threatens
<lb/>to leave us at no distant day, without a living
	    <lb/>proof of Indian sufferings, from the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName> to
<lb/>the immense desert, which sweeps along the
	    <lb/>base of the <placeName>Rocky Mountains</placeName>.</quote> These there­
<lb/>fore behold unmoved, and without an effort to
<lb/>saye, the accumulated suffering of these unhappy 
<lb/>Natives; and there are others, from whom bet­
<lb/>ter things might be expected, who coolly tell us,
<lb/><quote>that in the order of things it is right for civi­
	    <lb/>lized christian men, to take place of the wretch­
<lb/>ed and barbarous natives,</quote> and they affect to
	  <lb/>sneer at those who compassionate the <name>Indians</name>,
<lb/>and strive to excite feelings for their misfortunes,
<lb/>and prevent their final extinction, by exhibiting
<lb/>those high qualities which formed prominent
<lb/>traits in the character of those children of nature,
<lb/>before they were contaminated by the vices of 
<lb/>civilization—Yet we are compelled to pity those 
<lb/>cold and arid minds, who have no relish for those
<lb/>primitive virtues so honourable to human nature,
<lb/>and who can so readily sacrifice justice to the
<lb/>base calculations of self interest. Ridicule rises
<lb/>in importance, in proportion as its influence is
<lb/>felt; but when from conscious superiority it is
<pb n="28"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="C2v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">28</mw>
<lb/>treated with merited contempt, it recoils on its
<lb/>author.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> Is it consistent with the precepts
	  <lb/>of <name>Christianity</name> to take their land from the <name>In­
	    <lb/>dians</name>?—has not Christ said, whatsoever ye
<lb/>would that men should do unto you, do ye also
<lb/>unto them?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> <name>Christianity</name> appears to have exer­
<lb/>cised but little power over the evil passions of
<lb/>men—Not assuredly because it is not intrinsically
<lb/>pure, and designed to prepare us for a state of
<lb/>felicity by enabling us to subdue our wayward
<lb/>passions, and to be <quote>pure and peaceable and full
<lb/>of mercy and good fruit.</quote> That it has failed of
<lb/>producing this effect, results doubtless from its
<lb/>unnatural mixture with the history and the insti­
	  <lb/>tutions of the <name>Jews</name>. It has been the fate of all
<lb/>religious systems, however good and holy, in the
<lb/>beginning, to be perverted and associated with 
<lb/>evil practices, which furnish a pretext, and give
<lb/>scope to the designs of wicked men, who are
<lb/>thus enabled to shelter themselves under the
<lb/>broad mantle of superstition. Nothing can be
<lb/>so important, as pure and elevated conceptions of 
<lb/>the character and attributes of the Supreme Be­
<lb/>ing; these will lead us to reject all that can de­
<pb n="29"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="C3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">29</mw>
<lb/>file or lower the standard of perfection which 
<lb/>we strive to obtain, and thus we shall perceive
<lb/>that men can at no time be cruel or unjust, with­
<lb/>out incurring the divine displeasure; that tribu­
<lb/>lation and anguish, are denounced against every
<lb/>soul that doeth evil; and glory, honour, and im­
<lb/>mortality are promised to those who persevere in 
<lb/>well doing. Children are frequently at a loss to
<lb/>comprehend the reason why they are denied in­
<lb/>dulgences, which they think are essential to their
<lb/>happiness, though as they advance in life they
<lb/>become sensible, that the restraint to which they
<lb/>unwillingly submitted, was productive of much
<lb/>good. In like manner, the wisest are unable to
<lb/>perceive in many events, traces of that benignity
<lb/>and justice, which form the essential attributes
<lb/>of Him, whose tender mercies are over all His
<lb/>works. Nevertheless, we feel assured, from the
<lb/>entire confidence we have of the wisdom, and
<lb/>paternal goodness of God, that when the future
<lb/>is unveiled to our view, we shall perceive with 
<lb/>exultation that all is essentially right.—The
	  <lb/>minds of Children should be early imbued with 
<lb/>pure and undefiled <name>christianity</name>, unmingled with
<lb/>aught that could lead them astray. This can
<lb/>only be effected by enlightened mothers, who
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">C2</mw>
<pb n="30"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="C3v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">30</mw>
<lb/>themselves give an example of disinterested be­
<lb/>nevolence and pure devotion. Children will
<lb/>thus be formed to virtue, and made to feel the
<lb/>pleasure of doing good; they will be made happy,
<lb/>and their homes will be the centre of attraction.
<lb/>To render this order of things complete, atten­
<lb/>tion should be given to the comfort and conven­
<lb/>ience of the domestics, whose rights should
<lb/>never be infringed—nor should any creature be
<lb/>injured; more especially, that class of animals who
<lb/>labour for our benefit, should receive kind treat­
<lb/>ment, and never be forced to work beyond their 
<lb/>strength. There are many who ride very fast,
<lb/>because the motion gives them pleasure, and who
<lb/>perpetually urge on their horses to their full
<lb/>speed, without regarding the pain they inflict—
<lb/>this abuse of the power delegated to us by God,
	  <lb/>is highly reprehensible. The belief of the <name>Hin­
<lb/>doos</name> in the transmigration of souls, is very fa­
<lb/>vourable to animals, whom they fear to injure,
<lb/>lest they should be condemned to expiate their
<lb/>offences, in the form of the creature they have in
<lb/>this life abused.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> Do you mother think the <name>Hindoos</name>
<lb/>are right in believing in the transmigration of
<lb/>souls?</p>
        <pb n="31"/>
        <milestone unit="sig" n="C4r"/>
        <mw type="pageNum">31</mw>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> I do not pretend to determine in
<lb/>what manner people who are unmerciful will be
<lb/>punished, though I doubt not they will be made
	  <lb/>to suffer,—you know that Christ has said, blessed
<lb/>are the merciful, for they shall obtain mercy,
<lb/>and you should strive to gain this divine bene­
<lb/>diction by cultivating feelings of compassion for
<lb/>every living thing; even those troublesome in­
<lb/>sects who annoy us should be destroyed with as
<lb/>little pain as possible—the great law of love
<lb/>which binds us to the whole creation, will thus
<lb/>be fulfilled. Nevertheless, we should not suffer
<lb/>any advantage to be taken of this kindness of
<lb/>disposition, or submit to any imposition; this
<lb/>would be encouraging acts of injustice; for the
<lb/>being who can tamely yield to injustice or arro­
<lb/>gance, will soon lose that self respect which is
<lb/>essential to rectitude, and true delicacy of mind.
	  <lb/>A fine trait in the character of our <name>Aborigines</name>,
<lb/>is the kindness and urbanity which prevails in
<lb/>their domestic intercourse; no harshness is ever
<lb/>allowed, which corrodes affection, and destroys 
<lb/>confidence; but when they think wrong has 
<lb/>been done, they testify their feelings by coldness
<lb/>and inattention. This has been too often no­
<lb/>ticed, both by early and late writers, to admit of
<pb n="32"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="C4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">32</mw>
<lb/>dispute. One of the missionary ladies, in a letter
<lb/>to a friend, says, you can scarcely imagine how
<lb/>kindly the Indian girls, who are in our school,
<lb/>treat our children; we can trust them to their
<lb/>care with the utmost confidence, very different
<lb/>from that which is felt when we commit our 
<lb/>children to domestics, even when we rely on
<lb/>their good disposition.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> How is it that the Indian children
<lb/>are so good?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> I suppose it is in consequence of their
<lb/>being so kindly treated and so seldom reproved.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> It must be so <persName>Elizabeth</persName>, the In­
<lb/>dian children are not obliged to con over lessons
<lb/>when they wish to recreate themselves, and they
<lb/>do not fear to soil or injure their dress.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> You are unquestionably right, my
<lb/>children, the primitive simplicity to which our
	  <lb/><name>Indians</name> are accustomed, affords ample scope for
<lb/>the developement of those high endowments
<lb/>which the Great Author of life has bestowed on
<lb/>the creatures of His power, and those impressions
<lb/>have not been paralized by the forms of civilized
<lb/>society. Yet civilization has enabled man to pene­
<lb/>trate into the secrets of nature, and to make dis­
<lb/>coveries which exalt our conceptions of the wis­
<pb n="33"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="C5r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">33</mw>
<lb/>dom, and power, and goodness, of God; and
<lb/>some great and good men have attained a supe­
<lb/>riority, which has forcibly pointed out the high
<lb/>culture of which the human mind is susceptible,
<lb/>and the glorious destination that awaits them in
<lb/>the life to come; where they will enjoy that
<lb/>felicity, for which they are capacitated; but
<lb/>which in this feverish state of existence has ever
	  <lb/>eluded their pursuit. <persName>Charlevoix</persName> says: <quote>the <name>In­
<lb/>dians</name> were perhaps the only happy mortals on
<lb/>the face of the earth before they were acquaint­
<lb/>ed with those objects which seduce and pervert
	    <lb/>us.</quote> The observations of <persName>Charlevoix</persName>, I have
<lb/>often repeated, as he had the fairest opportunities
<lb/>of making himself acquainted with the customs
	  <lb/>of the <name>North American Indians</name>, and his remarks
<lb/>so well accord with those, who before and since 
<lb/>his time, have written on this subject, in the
<lb/>spirit of truth and impartiality. I will now pro­
	  <lb/>ceed with some of <persName>Charlevoix's</persName> remarks. <quote>The
<lb/>beauty of their imagination,</quote> says this intelli­
<lb/>gent writer, <quote>equals its vivacity which appears
<lb/>in all their discourse; they are quick at repar­
<lb/>tees, and their harangues are full of shining pas­
<lb/>sages, which would have been applauded at
	    <lb/><placeName>Rome</placeName> and <placeName>Athens</placeName>. Their eloquence has a
<pb n="34"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="C5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">34</mw>
<lb/>strength, nature and pathos, which no art can
<lb/>give. They have a clear and solid judgment
<lb/>and come at once to the point. Most of them
<lb/>have a nobleness of soul, and constancy of mind,
<lb/>at which we rarely arrive, with all the assistance
<lb/>of philosophy and religion. They moreover
<lb/>treat one another with a gentleness and respect,
<lb/>unknown to the common people in the most po­
<lb/>lite nations. Their care of orphans, widows,
<lb/>and infirm persons, and the hospitality which
<lb/>they exercise is admirable. Nothing can exceed
<lb/>the care which mothers take of their children 
<lb/>when in the cradle. Nothing can be neater 
<lb/>than these cradles in which the child lies as
<lb/>commodiously as possible. Every one has a
<lb/>friend nearly the same age with himself, to whom
<lb/>he attaches himself by the most indissoluble 
<lb/>bonds. Two persons thus united by one com­
<lb/>mon interest are capable of undertaking and
<lb/>hazarding every thing, in order to aid and mutu­
<lb/>ally succour each other: death itself, according
<lb/>to their belief, can only separate them for a time:
<lb/>they are well assured of meeting again in the
<lb/>other world never to part. At first view one
<lb/>would imagine them without any form of govern­
<lb/>ment; they notwithstanding enjoy all the advan­
<pb n="35"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="C6r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">35</mw>
<lb/>tages which the best regulated authority is capa­
<lb/>ble of procuring in the most enlightened Nations.
<lb/>They have a natural repugnance to restraint of
<lb/>every sort, but reason alone is capable of retain­
<lb/>ing them in a kind of subordination, not less
<lb/>effectual, for being entirely voluntary.</quote>—This
<lb/>remark is confirmed and illustrated by a late
	  <lb/>writer, on the <name>North American Indians</name>, in the
	  <lb/><title>North American Review</title> for <date when="1826-01"><name>January</name>, 1826</date>.
	  <lb/><quote>We say the <name>Indians</name> have no government. 
<lb/>And they have none whose operation is felt either
<lb/>in rewards or punishments. And yet their lives
<lb/>and property are protected, and their politi­
<lb/>cal relations among themselves, and with
<lb/>other tribes, are duly preserved. Have they 
<lb/>then no passions to excite them to deeds of vio­
<lb/>lence, or have they discovered and reduced to 
<lb/>practice, some unknown principle of action in
<lb/>human nature, equally efficacious and with the two 
<lb/>great motives of hope and fear, upon which all
<lb/>other governments have heretofore rested? Why
	    <lb/>does an <name>Indian</name>, who has been guilty of murder,
<lb/>tranquilly fold his blanket about his head, and
<lb/>seating himself upon the ground await the retri­
<lb/>butive stroke from the relation of the deceased.
<lb/>Within the last year, we ourselves, (continues
<pb n="36"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="C6v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">36</mw>
<lb/>this writer,) far in the interior of the country,
<lb/>while surveying the initiatory ceremonies of the
<lb/>Indian <foreign xml:lang="mus">Mealay</foreign>, one of their mystical societies,
	    <lb/>saw a <name>Chippewa</name>, whose grave and serious de­
<lb/>meanor attracted our observation. His appear­
<lb/>ance led to the inquiry, whether any peculiarity
<lb/>in his situation impressed upon his deportment
<lb/>the air of seriousness, which was too evident to 
<lb/>be mistaken. It was ascertained that he had
	    <lb/>killed a <name>Potawatamie Indian</name>, during the preced­
	    <lb/>ing season, and that the <name>Potawatamies</name> had made
<lb/>the usual demand for his surrender. On a re­
<lb/>presentation, however, that he was deeply in
<lb/>debt, and that his immediate death would cause
<lb/>much injustice to some of the traders, the injured
<lb/>tribe at length agreed to postpone his execution,
<lb/>till another season, that the produce of his win­
<lb/>ter's hunt might be applied to the discharge of
<lb/>his debts. He had been successful in his exer­
<lb/>tions, and had paid the claims against him. He
<lb/>was now about to leave his friends, and to re­
<lb/>ceive with the fortitude of a warrior the doom
<lb/>which awaited him. He was now for the last 
<lb/>time, enjoying the society of all who were dear
<lb/>to him. No one doubted his resolution, and no
<lb/>one doubted his fate. Instructions however were
<pb n="37"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="D1r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">37</mw>
<lb/>given, to redeem his life at the expense of the
	    <lb/><placeName>United States</placeName>.</quote></p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> Do the laws of the <name>Indians</name> allow a
<lb/>compensation to be given as the price of blood?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> They do so, but, its acceptance, or
<lb/>rejection, is purely voluntary on the part of the
<lb/>friends of the person murdered, who are sup­
<lb/>posed to be the best judges whether malice or
<lb/>accident caused the murder.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> But, mother, is it not strange to
<lb/>find a sense of justice so much stronger in the
	  <lb/>breasts of the uncivilized <name>Indians</name>, than in civil­
	  <lb/>ized christian men?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> I have before observed to you, my
<lb/>dearest girls, that the primitive simplicity which
	  <lb/>prevails among our <name>Indians</name>, is highly favourable
<lb/>to the developement of those lofty sentiments,
<lb/>and pure notions of justice and kindness, which
<lb/>are the gifts of God to man, and the competitions 
<lb/>of interest and ambition which pervert and paral­
<lb/>ize these gifts, in a state of civilization, are felt
<lb/>in a slight degree, where so much liberty and
<lb/>equality prevails.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> But, mother, are not the Indian women
<lb/>obliged to do almost all the labour? do not they
<lb/>cultivate the ground and raise corn and other
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">D</mw>
<pb n="38"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="D1v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">39</mw>
<lb/>vegetables, for the supply of their families, while
<lb/>the men are idle.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> The labour required to supply a 
<lb/>family with grain and vegetables is not burden­
<lb/>some, when we reflect how slight is their task 
<lb/>within their dwellings, when compared with the
<lb/>labours of women in our lower classes of society.
	  <lb/>We learn from the <persName>Rev. Mr. Heckewelder</persName>, whose
<lb/>veracity is undoubted, that in hunting, the men
<lb/>encounter much greater hardships, than any
<lb/>which fall to the share of the women. The old
<lb/>men frequently assist the women in their work,
<lb/>and the young men, when not engaged in hunt­
<lb/>ing, labour, to recommend themselves to her
<lb/>whom they love, and to find an opportunity of
<lb/>communicating their secret wishes to the object
<lb/>of their affections.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> If we may confide in <persName>Mr. Hecke­
<lb/>welder</persName>, why are we so often told that Indian wo­
<lb/>men are mere slaves?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> Many mistakes are made by people
<lb/>who are unaccustomed to reflect, and compare,
<lb/>and when they observe customs which vary from
<lb/>such as are familiar to them, they are led to ima­
<lb/>gine something monstrous and unnatural, and
<lb/>inveigh against them with great bitterness; with­
<lb/>out perceiving any good which may overbalance
<pb n="39"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="D2r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">39</mw>
<lb/>the evil: this reflection will, I trust, admonish
<lb/>you to attend, and compare one thing, or custom,
<lb/>with another, and determine with impartiality 
<lb/>the results.</p>
        <p>Thus, notwithstanding so many are ready to
<lb/>point out what appears degrading in the condi­
<lb/>tion of the Indian women, there are few who
<lb/>have borne testimony to the superior privileges
	  <lb/>they enjoy. <persName>Charlevoix</persName> says, <quote>the women have
<lb/>the chief authority amongst all the nations of the 
	    <lb/><name>Illuron language</name>; if we except the Irequois can­
	    <lb/>ton of <placeName>Onneyouth</placeName>, in which it is both sexes alter­
<lb/>nately. I have been assured that the women
<lb/>always deliberate first on whatever is proposed
<lb/>in council, and they always give the result of
<lb/>their deliberations to the chiefs, who make the
<lb/>report of it to the general council, composed of
	    <lb/>the elders.</quote> <persName>Charlevoix</persName> adds; <quote>but in all pro­
<lb/>bability this is done only for forms sake.</quote> Be
<lb/>this is as it may, it evinces a degree of respect and
<lb/>attention, which we should in vain seek to find
<lb/>in nations who are styled civilized. Unques­
<lb/>tionably different customs prevail in different
<lb/>tribes, but we have abundant proof that in all,
<lb/>women have a voice in the public deliberations,
<lb/>and their consent is deemed essential in the rati­
<lb/>fication of treaties. Our much respected friend,
<pb n="40"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="D2v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">40</mw>
	  <lb/><persName>Col. P.</persName>, who some years since was deputed with
<lb/>several others, to settle the terms of a treaty with
	  <lb/>the neighbouring <name>Indians</name>, informed me, that af­
<lb/>ter waiting some days at the place appointed, the
	  <lb/><name>Indians</name> at length arrived, with the celebrated
	  <lb/>chief <persName>Red Jacket</persName> at their head, who bore on his
<lb/>back his child, to relieve his wife from the bur­
<lb/>den. The Comissioners, impatient of delay,
<lb/>asked why it was thought necessary for the whole
<lb/>tribe to accompany the chiefs? One of the chiefs
<lb/>in reply, assured the commissioners, that it was
<lb/>deemed essential to the validity of a treaty, that
<lb/>not only the chief and warriors should be pre­
<lb/>sent, but that the women of the tribe should
<lb/>testify their approbation by presenting a
<lb/>string of wampom. The Colonel assured me
<lb/>that the Indian women, particularly those who
<lb/>are young, were remarkable for their modesty,
<lb/>and sweetness of voice and manner. Their
	  <lb/>chief, <persName>Red Jacket</persName>, addressed the commissioners
<lb/>in a style of lofty eloquence, and impressive ges­
<lb/>ture, quite equal to what our venerable friend
<lb/>has heard of Indian oratory.</p>
        <p>When this country was first settled, many
<lb/>queens, or squaw-sachems, as they were styled,
<lb/>were found, possessing equal authority with the
<lb/>male sachems. We have no means of ascertaining 
<lb/>their laws of succession, as the numerous tribes
<pb n="41"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="D3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">41</mw>
	  <lb/>in <placeName>New England</placeName> were so speedily swept away
<lb/>by the settlers, who appear to have given them­
<lb/>selves little time or trouble in ascertaining the
<lb/>laws or customs of the natives, except such as
<lb/>would assist them in supplanting, or reducing
	  <lb/>them to a state of subjugation. <persName>Wetamoe</persName>, the
	  <lb/>squaw sachem of <persName>Pocasset</persName>, appears to have been
<lb/>most active in defending the country from the
<lb/>usurpations, of the whites, and was, we are told,
	  <lb/><quote>next to <persName>Philip</persName> in respect to the mischief that
<lb/>had been done, and the blood that had been shed
	    <lb/>in this war.</quote> She joined her kinsman <persName>Philip</persName>,
	  <lb/>and was found dead near <placeName>Taunton river</placeName>, which
<lb/>it was supposed she had attempted to cross on a 
<lb/>raft. <quote>Her head was cut off, and set upon a pole
	    <lb/>in <placeName>Taunton</placeName>, when the <name>Indians</name> who were prison­
<lb/>ers there knew it presently, and made a most
<lb/>horrid and diabolical lamentation, crying out
<lb/>that it was their queen's head.</quote> <seg xml:id="a02" corresp="#n02" rend="post(*)">The writer</seg>
<lb/>proceeds to observe, <quote>that God himself by his own 
<lb/>hand brought this enemy to destruction. For in
<lb/>that place, where the last year, she furnished
	    <lb/><persName>Philip</persName> with canoes for his men, she could not
<lb/>meet with a canoe to save herself.</quote></p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> But was not <persName>Wetamoe</persName> right in
	  <lb/>aiding <persName>Philip</persName>, and endeavouring to preserve
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">D2</mw>
<pb n="42"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="D3v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">42</mw>
<lb/>the liberty, and independence of her country?
<lb/>Instead of being treated so barbarously, she
<lb/>should I think have been honoured as a heroine.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> Unhappily the first settlers of this
<lb/>country were unable or unwilling to appreciate
	  <lb/>in the <name>Indians</name>, those feelings of independence,
<lb/>and attachment to their early religious opinions,
<lb/>which constituted their own peculiar merit.
	  <lb/>When the <name>Indians</name> assembled to worship the
<lb/>Great Spirit, or to deprecate his anger; they 
<lb/>were supposed by the whites to be employed in 
<lb/>magical incantations, to appease the evil spirit,
<lb/>and dispose him to entangle and destroy the
	  <lb/>white people. Did the <name>Indians</name> practice the heal­
<lb/>ing art, and by their knowledge of simples re­
<lb/>lieve pain, and restore the sick, as it was ascribed
<lb/>to the power of that same evil being, whom they
<lb/>delighted to worship and obey. Any attempts on
	  <lb/>the part of the <name>Indians</name> to resist the encroach­
<lb/>ments or usurpations of the whites, were constru­
<lb/>ed as evincing hostile designs, and were followed
<lb/>by the most severe and cruel treatment. The
<lb/>courtesy and hospitable manner with which the 
	  <lb/>pilgrims had been received and cherished, when
<lb/>they were strangers and had none to help them,
<lb/>had no power to mollify them, when by continual
<lb/>additions to their numbers, and by their knowl­
<pb n="43"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="D4r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">43</mw>
<lb/>edge of the arts, they acquired sufficient strength
<lb/>to subdue their generous entertainers.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> Were not the <name>Indians</name> extremely
<lb/>vindictive, and cruel? I have often heard of
<lb/>their bloody deeds, Mother.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> The <name>Indians</name>, <persName>Caroline</persName>, were long
<lb/>ago made sensible that not only their safety, but
<lb/>their existence depended on their expelling the
<lb/>invaders of their country. They have been
<lb/>roused to vengeance, by the injuries, injustice,
<lb/>and insults of the whites, who have thus been
<lb/>subjected to a fearful retribution; yet in my es­
	  <lb/>timation the cruelties of the <name>Indians</name> were tender
<lb/>mercies when compared with those which they
<lb/>have suffered from the whites. Even the horrid
<lb/>death by torture, can bear no comparison with 
<lb/>the protracted and hopeless misery to which so
	  <lb/>many <name>Indians</name> were doomed, who were trans­
<lb/>ported to the Islands and sold for slaves. Neith­
<lb/>er rank or sex could claim exemption, and the
	  <lb/>wife of the heroic <persName>Philip</persName>, and the young prince
<lb/>his son, were sentenced to endure this appalling
<lb/>servitude, and thus forever exiled from their be­
<lb/>loved country. The greater part of the Indian 
<lb/>prisoners were put to death, and many noble
<lb/>chieftains, after the strife of the battle had ceased,
	  <lb/>were ignominiously hanged publicly in <placeName>Boston</placeName>.
<pb n="44"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="D4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">44</mw>
<lb/>We are nevertheless assured that a few only of
<lb/>the white people who fell into the hands of the
	  <lb/><name>Indians</name> suffered death or torture but most of 
<lb/>them were ransomed, or returned unhurt to their 
<lb/>friends, having encountered only such hardships
<lb/>as were incident to the wandering life and pre­
<lb/>carious subsistence to which they were com­
<lb/>pelled to submit. The honourable treatment
<lb/>which female captives received from these untu­
<lb/>tored children of nature, should cause the civ­
<lb/>ilized man to feel with deep humiliation <gap extent="6-8 letters" desc="printed" reason="flawed-reproduction"/>
<lb/>inferiority.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> You say, mother, that it is the duty 
<lb/>of all to seek truth, but I must confess I am mor­
<lb/>tified to find our pilgrim fathers who are so
<lb/>much extolled, guilty of deeds <unclear reason="flawed-reproduction">so</unclear>criminal; what
<lb/>are we to think when such men are praised for
<lb/>their piety and christian virtue?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> You must recollect, that <name>christianity</name>
<lb/>has been very imperfectly comprehended by the
<lb/>mass of mankind; a better state of things is dawn­
<lb/>ing upon us, I trust, and pure and undefiled reli­
<lb/>gion, as it was taught and exemplified by our
<lb/>divine teacher, will be restored apart from those
<lb/>corrupt doctrines, which have so long marred its
<lb/>splendour, and retarded its efficacy. You must
<lb/>also remember that the descendants of the pil­
<pb n="45"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="D5r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">45</mw>
<lb/>grims have received from them this goodly land,
<lb/>and that the fortitude which led them to brave
<lb/>so many dangers, and endure so many privations
<lb/>in support of freedom, and what they believed to 
<lb/>be truth, has made them to be viewed through
<lb/>the medium of prejudice, and invested them with
<lb/>a lustre, which will fade before the perfect light
<lb/>of truth. The God of purity and love, as he is
	  <lb/>presented to us by Christ; whose tender mercies
<lb/>are over all His works; who is the same yester­
<lb/>day, to day and forever, cannot surely be the
	  <lb/>same being whom <persName>Moses</persName>, and many other writers
<lb/>represent as partial, revengeful, and unjust; and 
<lb/>I should feel myself highly culpable should I suf­
<lb/>fer you to believe that men who have allowed
<lb/>themselves to be rapacious, and cruel, could have
<lb/>acted thus in conformity with the high behest of
	  <lb/>the God and Father of our <persName>Lord Jesus Christ</persName>.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> I can never read those parts of the
	  <lb/><name>Old Testament</name> which relate to the treatment of 
	  <lb/>the <name>Canaanites</name> without feeling great compassion
<lb/>for that people, and disgust and indignation to­
	  <lb/>ward the <name>Israelites</name> for their wicked and abom­
<lb/>inable conduct; and I shall rejoice to find they
<lb/>were not authorized to destroy the inhabitants of 
	  <lb/><placeName>Canaan</placeName>, for were it true, we should be unable to
<pb n="46"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="D5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">46</mw>
<lb/>distinguish good from evil—but how came this 
<lb/>to be believed, mother?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> Among all ancient nations it was
<lb/>common to indulge in a style of writing highly
<lb/>figurative, more especially when they desired to
<lb/>veil in obscurity, transactions which would not
<lb/>bear the light; nevertheless, all nations, however 
<lb/>varied were their forms of belief, acknowledged
<lb/>and adored one Supreme Ruler of the Universe,
<lb/>by whose sovereign will and pleasure all the
<lb/>events of this life were ordained, none having pow­
<lb/>er to alter, or withstand His decrees. Their ideas
<lb/>were extremely confused, like many of the pre­
<lb/>sent day, as they perceived both from the light
<lb/>of nature, and of revelation, that except freedom
<lb/>of will be allowed to man, he of course ceases to 
<lb/>be an accountable creature; they nevertheless
<lb/>represented him as bound in the adamantine
<lb/>chains of fate, thus making God the author of
<lb/>evil, and themselves the instruments of His will,
<lb/>to whom sin was not imputed. Unhappily our
	  <lb/>ancestors believed that the <name>Israelites</name>, in conform­
<lb/>ity with their own hyperbolic representations,
<lb/>were a people chosen by God, to execute his
	  <lb/>vengeance on the <name>Canaanites</name>, whom they were
<lb/>commanded to exterminate, and possess their
<lb/>heritage; therefore, as the odious transactions
<pb n="47"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="D6r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">47</mw>
	  <lb/>of the <name>Israelites</name>, have been associated with
	  <lb/><name>Christianity</name>, though nothing can be more ad­
<lb/>verse to the spirit of our holy religion, they readi­
<lb/>ly adopted the notion, that they also were favour­
	  <lb/>ites of heaven, and privileged like the <name>Israelites</name>
<lb/>to destroy the native inhabitants of this land, and
<lb/>convert it to their own use. Impressed with 
<lb/>these convictions, they appear to have lost sight
	  <lb/>of the benign precepts of Jesus, and identified
	  <lb/>themselves with the <name>Israelites</name>. Yet I would not
<lb/>have you imagine that this people were igno­
<lb/>rant of the essential attributes of the high and
	  <lb/>lofty one who inhabiteth eternity. <persName>David</persName>, in his
<lb/>ascriptions of praise, gives the most vivid and ex­
<lb/>alted views of the One only God, and bows be­
<lb/>fore the most High, confessing His justice and
<lb/>mercy, in having afflicted him for his manifold
<lb/>transgressions, and thus afforded him opportunity,
<lb/>and space for repentance. Throughout the
	  <lb/><name>Scriptures</name> we find the most sublime and beauti­
<lb/>ful representations of the Deity, which fully at­
<lb/>test that the unworthy views I have before notic­
<lb/>ed, must be deemed altogether hyperbolical, and 
<lb/>calculated to blind the judgment, and stifle the
<lb/>voice of nature.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> I suppose the <title>Iliad</title> of <persName>Homer</persName>
<pb n="48"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="D6v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">48</mw>
<lb/>which we are now reading at school, must be
<lb/>written in the figurative style you describe?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> You will find the same inconsisten­
	  <lb/>cies in <persName>Homer</persName>, who is supposed to have been
	  <lb/>contemporary with <persName>Solomon</persName>, and the extrav­
<lb/>agant notions which some have entertained of
<lb/>the religion of the Heathen, would be justified,
	  <lb/>could we imagine that <persName>Homer</persName> in reality, designed
<lb/>to convey the idea, that gods, and goddesses, 
<lb/>were personally engaged in the strife of mortal
	  <lb/>men. <persName>Homer</persName>, who has been the wonder and
<lb/>delight of ages, who has, under various forms,
<lb/>conveyed the most impressive, religious, and
<lb/>moral instruction, was unquestionably influenced 
<lb/>by the conviction, that every good, and every
<lb/>perfect gift came from God; he therefore repre­
<lb/>sented, wisdom, and valour, &amp;c. as personified
<lb/>in his heroes, and thus designed to impress the 
<lb/>belief of the overruling power, and attributes of 
	  <lb/>the Olympian <persName>Jove</persName>. Of this, all must be con­
<lb/>vinced, who attend to the noble description given
	  <lb/>by <persName>Homer</persName>, of the power and supremacy of the
<lb/>Father of gods and men, in the eighth Book of 
	  <lb/>the <title>Iliad</title>. Here also you will acquaint your­
<lb/>selves with the manners and feelings, of many
<lb/>of the celebrated men of antiquity, and will be
<lb/>assured that they possessed in a high degree
<pb n="49"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="E1r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">49</mw>
<lb/>all those sentiments and feelings, which superfi­
<lb/>cial observers imagine are peculiarly our own.
<lb/>It would, I apprehend, be difficult to produce
	  <lb/>any character more perfect than that of <persName>Hector</persName>,
<lb/>in all the relations of life. It is in my opinion
<lb/>impossible to find any scene more highly des­
<lb/>criptive of refined sensibility and noble feeling,
	  <lb/>than is the interview between <persName>Hector</persName> and <persName>An­
	  <lb/>dromache</persName>. Every circumstance conspires to
	  <lb/>render this parting unequalled. When <persName>Hector</persName>
<lb/>relates the prophetical denunciation of the fall of
	  <lb/>imperial <placeName>Troy</placeName>, when her glories shall be blended
<lb/>with the dust, and his kindred and people slain,
<lb/>yet declares, although oppressed, with this weight
<lb/>of woe, that no sorrow so wounds his mind, as
<lb/>the sad presage, of the grief and degradation
	  <lb/>which awaits <persName>Andromache</persName>. When to relieve
	  <lb/>the fears of his child, <persName>Hector</persName> unbinds the beam­
<lb/>ing helmet from his brows, and places it on the
<lb/>ground, then lifts him high in air, whilst he feverent­
<lb/>ly supplicates Him, whose glories fill the ethereal
<lb/>throne, to protect and  bless his son, and grant
	  <lb/>that he may guard the <name>Trojans</name> and defend the
<lb/>crown, when he shall be no more; I am com­
<lb/>pelled to acknowledge that this scene surpasses
<lb/>all I have ever known. Nor must we pass over
	  <lb/>in silence the part of <persName>Andromache</persName>, who in truth
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">E</mw>
<pb n="50"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="E1v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">50</mw>
<lb/>appears worthy of such a husband, in her fulness
<lb/>of affection, and tender solicitude; and though
<lb/>oppressed with sorrow, the voice of loud lament
	  <lb/>was not heard, nor efforts made to detain <persName>Hector</persName>
<lb/>from the embattled plain.</p>
        <p>It must be confessed, that in the days of <persName>Ho­
<lb/>mer</persName>, all the endearing charities of life were cher­
<lb/>ished in their fairest forms, and produced the
<lb/>purest results; nor will unprejudiced observers,
<lb/>contend that women are indebted for the estima­
<lb/>tion in which they are now held, to the gener­
<lb/>osity, and superior refinement of modern nations;
<lb/>as it is manifest that not only did they receive
<lb/>those delicate and affectionate attentions, now
<lb/>deemed essential, but were invested with the
<lb/>sacred office of priestesses, and officiated pub­
<lb/>licly in the temples and in solemn processions,
	  <lb/>in honour of the gods. The testimony of <persName>Homer</persName>
<lb/>is corroborated by other writers, both sacred and
<lb/>profane, of which I could cite abundant proof,
<lb/>but I will mention one only, which is the au­
	  <lb/>thority <persName>Sarah</persName> exercised over <persName>Abraham</persName>, in regard
	  <lb/>to <persName>Hagar</persName> and her son, though she has been ex­
	  <lb/>tolled for her submission in calling <persName>Abraham</persName>
<lb/>lord. You know too well my sentiments to ima­
	  <lb/>gine I would recommend the example of <persName>Sarah</persName>;
<lb/>it is only noticed here to show the prevailing
<pb n="51"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="E2r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">51</mw>
<lb/>manners of that early period; you cannot too
<lb/>conscientiously guard against all desires that are
<lb/>unjust or unreasonable, and you should be equal­
<lb/>ly regardful to receive no wrong treatment from
<lb/>others, if it be in your power to prevent it. I 
<lb/>can with confidence affirm, that no one will en­
<lb/>gage respect or esteem who willingly submits to
<lb/>impositions. Yet frail beings, conscious of their
<lb/>own defects, should be kind and forbearing, and
<lb/>not provoke strife, or aversion, by their perversity,
<lb/>or unaccommodating temper.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> I wish to know how it happened,
	  <lb/>mother, that <persName>Hector</persName> was so confident that <placeName>Troy</placeName>
<lb/>must fall?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> <persName>Hector</persName> was conscious that the <placeName>Tro­
<lb/>jans</placeName> merited severe retributions, for having re­
	  <lb/>ceived <persName>Helen</persName>, in compliance with the wishes of
	  <lb/><persName>Paris</persName>, and in refusing to restore her and her
<lb/>treasures, to her lawful lord. You will call to
	  <lb/>mind the challenge of <persName>Paris</persName>, and its acceptance
<lb/>by the Spartan king, on the condition, that should
<lb/>he prove victorious in the strife, the beauteous
<lb/>queen should be his, with the treasure she
<lb/>brought, and differing nations should part in 
<lb/>leagues of peace. These solemn engagements,
<lb/>made under the most imposing sanctions, by sac­
<lb/>rifices, prayers, and imprecations: was most
<pb n="52"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="E2v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">52</mw>
	  <lb/>shamefully violated by the <name>Trojans</name>; <persName>Hector</persName> was
<lb/>therefore convinced, that his people had forfeited
<lb/>all right to the protection, and favour of heaven,
<lb/>though he strove to procrastinate their doom.
	  <lb/>The character of <persName>Hector</persName> is always well supported.
<lb/>Conscious of his own integrity, his confidence
<lb/>in the Almighty never forsakes him, and though
<lb/>we find him complying with the religious rites
<lb/>and ceremonies, common to his country, he re­
	  <lb/>fuses with disdain to follow the advice of <persName>Poly­
<lb/>damas</persName>, who endeavoured to prevent him from his
<lb/>intended attack on the Grecian fleet, as the
	  <lb/>omens were unpropitious. The reply of <persName>Hector</persName>
<lb/>is full of dignity, and indicates a firm reliance on
<lb/>what he believes to be the will of heaven, un­
	  <lb/>moved by inferior auguries. <persName>Homer's</persName> descrip­
<lb/>tions are truly admirable, and impress the mind
<lb/>with lofty images, and sublime conceptions of
<lb/>moral grandeur and beauty. The more you at­
<lb/>tend to history, the firmer will be your convic­
<lb/>tion of the universal belief of one Supreme Ru­
<lb/>ler of the Universe, who rewards the good, and
<lb/>punishes evil doers, without respect of persons. 
	  <lb/>The inhabitants of <placeName>Canaan</placeName>, among whom the
	  <lb/><name>Israelites</name> sojourned, all appealed to the same
<lb/>Almighty power to witness their engagements,
<lb/>to whom also they offered sacrifices and obla­
<pb n="53"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="E3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">53</mw>
<lb/>tions, and addressed their fervent prayers; and 
<lb/>we should rejoice to find the virtues of gener­
<lb/>osity, hospitality and good faith, held in the high­
<lb/>est estimation, however blended with vice, or
<lb/>deformed by sensuality.</p>
        <p>I trust, my dear children, you will not be
<lb/>wearied with this long digression, as it appears
<lb/>to me to be altogether essential to give you just,
<lb/>and comprehensive views of the never failing
<lb/>goodness, and essential perfections of that Al­
<lb/>mighty Being, who we are assured <quote>hath never
<lb/>left himself without a witness—for the invisible 
<lb/>things of Him from the creation of the world are
<lb/>clearly seen, being understood by the things
<lb/>that are made, even his eternal power and God­
<lb/>head.</quote> These assurances will prevent you from
<lb/>indulging those supercilious feelings, which lead
<lb/>many to imagine themselves to be the only peo­
<lb/>ple who are truly enlightened, and favoured by
<lb/>the most High. Our blessed master, came not
<lb/>to destroy the law, but to fulfil. He came to
<lb/>illustrate, improve and confirm, all those impres­
<lb/>sions which are written in divine characters on
<lb/>the heart, and to exemplify in the most perfect
<lb/>form the doctrines he taught. These views will
<lb/>silence those, who affirm that if these doctrines
<lb/>had been essential for our salvation and happi­
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">E2</mw>
<pb n="54"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="E3v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">54</mw>
<lb/>ness, God would not so long have delayed to 
<lb/>communicate them to the creatures whom He
<lb/>formed. You will also be assured that such as
<lb/>love not their brethren, but destroy and perse­
<lb/>cute them, and bind on them heavy burdens, are
	  <lb/>unworthy the name of <name>Christians</name>.</p>
        <p>I will now close what I have further to relate
	  <lb/>of the <name>Creeks</name>, with a description of the  charac­
	  <lb/>ter, customs and persons of the <name>Cherokees</name>, 
	  <lb/><name>Muscogulges</name>, <name>Siminoles</name>, <name>Chickasaws</name>, <name>Chack­
	    <lb/>taws</name>, and confederate tribes of the <name>Creeks</name>; from 
	  <lb/>Travels through <placeName>North</placeName> and <placeName>South Carolina</placeName>,
	  <lb/><placeName>Georgia</placeName>, <placeName>East</placeName> and <placeName>West Florida</placeName>, the <placeName>Cherokee
	    <lb/>Country</placeName>, the extensive <placeName>Territories of the Mus­
	    <lb/>cogulges</placeName>, or <placeName>Creek Confederacy</placeName>, and the <placeName>Coun­
	    <lb/>try of the Chactaws</placeName>; by <persName>William Bartram</persName>, in
	  <lb/><date when="1773">1773</date>. <persName>Mr. Bartram</persName> was a botanist, and a great
<lb/>admirer of natural scenery, which led him to be
<lb/>somewhat enthusiastic in his descriptions, yet his
<lb/>integrity is undoubted. The fervour of his reli­
<lb/>gious feelings led him to express without reserve
<lb/>his admiration of the works of God, in His gifts
<lb/>to man, and to all created intelligences, without
<lb/>any desire to limit His benevolence. <quote>This
<lb/>world,</quote> he says, <quote>as a glorious apartment of the
<lb/>boundless palace of the sovereign Creator, is
<lb/>furnished with an infinite variety of animated
<pb n="55"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="E4r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">55</mw>
<lb/>scenes, inexpressibly beautiful and pleasing,
<lb/>equally free to the inspection and enjoyment of
<lb/>all his creatures.</quote></p>
        <quote rend="bestow((pre(“))(p))">
          <p>
The males of the <name>Muscogulges</name>, <name>Cherokees</name>,
	    <lb/>and confederate tribes of the <name>Creeks</name>, are tall,
<lb/>erect and moderately robust; their limbs well
<lb/>shaped, so as generally to form a perfect human
<lb/>figure; their features regular, and countenance
<lb/>open, dignified and placid; yet the forehead and
<lb/>brow so formed, as to strike you instantly with
<lb/>heroism and bravery; the eye, though rather
<lb/>small, yet active and full of fire, the iris always
<lb/>black; and the nose inclining to the aquiline.
<lb/>Their countenance and actions exhibit an air of 
<lb/>magnanimity, superiority, and independence.
<lb/>Their complexion of a reddish brown or copper
<lb/>colour, their hair long, lank, coarse, and black
<lb/>as a raven, and reflecting the like lustre at dif­
<lb/>ferent exposures to the light.</p>
          <p>The women of the <name>Cherokees</name> are tall, slen­
<lb/>der, erect and of a delicate frame; their features
<lb/>formed with perfect symmetry; their counte­
<lb/>nances cheerful, and friendly; and they move
<lb/>with a becoming grace. This description of the
<lb/>Cherokee women, will with some variations, ap­
<lb/>ply equally well to the females of the other tribes.
	    <lb/>The <name>Cherokees</name> are taller and more robust than
<pb n="56"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="E4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum">56</mw>
	    <lb/>the <name>Muscogulges</name>, and by far the largest race of
<lb/>men I have seen, with some few exceptions;
<lb/>their complexions brighter, and somewhat of the
<lb/>olive cast, especially the adults; and some of 
<lb/>their young women are nearly as fair, and bloom­
<lb/>ing, as European women.</p>
        </quote>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> I recollect in the account given of
	  <lb/><persName>Catharine Brown</persName>, the Cherokee convert, it was
<lb/>said, that she was distinguished from the ladies
<lb/>belonging to the missionary family, only by her
<lb/>superior beauty and modest deportment, and that
<lb/>some gentlemen who accidentally saw her,
<lb/>doubted not her being white.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> I remember that she was represent­
<lb/>ed to be a most amiable and interesting young
<lb/>woman; her patience, fortitude, (and the ex­
<lb/>treme anxiety for the sorrow and privations of
<lb/>her people, whose ruin she foresaw,) during a
<lb/>long and severe illness, which terminated her
<lb/>life, made a deep impression on all who knew
<lb/>her.</p>
        <quote rend="bestow((pre(“))(p))">
          <p>The <name>Cherokees</name>, in their dispositions and
<lb/>manners are grave and steady; dignified and
<lb/>circumspect in their deportment, yet frank,
<lb/>cheerful, and humane; tenacious of the liberties
<lb/>and natural rights of men; secret, deliberate
<lb/>and determined in their councils; honest, just
<pb n="57"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="E5r"/>
<mw type="pageNum">57</mw>
<lb/>and liberal, and ready always to sacrifice every
<lb/>pleasure and gratification, even life itself, to de­
<lb/>fend their territories, and maintain their rights.</p>
          <p>The national character of the <name>Muscogulges</name>,
<lb/>when considered in a political view, exhibits a
<lb/>portraiture of a great and illustrious hero. A
<lb/>proud, haughty, arrogant race of men, they are
<lb/>valiant in war, ambitious of conquest, restless
<lb/>and perpetually exercising their arms, yet mag­
<lb/>nanimous and merciful to a vanquished enemy,
<lb/>when he submits and seeks their friendship and 
<lb/>protection: always uniting the vanquished tribes
<lb/>in confederacy with them; when they immedi­
<lb/>ately enjoy, unexceptionably, every right of free
<lb/>citizens, and are from that moment united in
<lb/>one common band of brotherhood. They were
<lb/>never known to exterminate a tribe, except the
	    <lb/><name>Yamasees</name>, who would never submit, but fought
<lb/>it out to the last, only about forty or fifty of them
<lb/>escaping at the last decisive battle. If we con­
<lb/>sider them with respect to their private charac­
<lb/>ter, or in a moral view, they must I think claim 
<lb/>our approbation, if we divest ourselves of preju­
<lb/>dice and think freely. As moral men, they cer­
<lb/>tainly stand in no need of European civiliza­
<lb/>tion. They are just, honest, liberal and hospita­
<lb/>ble to strangers; considerate, loving and affec­
<pb n="58"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="E5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">58</mw>
<lb/>tionate to their wives and relations; fond of their
<lb/>children, industrious, frugal, temperate and for­
<lb/>bearing. I have been weeks and months 
<lb/>amongst them and in their towns, and never ob­
<lb/>served the least sign of contention: never saw
	    <lb/>an instance of an <name>Indian</name> beating his wife, or
<lb/>even reproving her in anger. In this case, they
<lb/>stand as examples of reproof to the most civilized
<lb/>nations, as not being defective in justice, grati­
<lb/>tude, and good understanding; for indeed their
<lb/>wives merit their esteem, and the most gentle 
<lb/>treatment, they being industrious, frugal, loving
	    <lb/>and affectionate. The <name>Muscogulges</name> are more
<lb/>volatile, and talkative, than their Northern neigh­
	    <lb/>bours, the <name>Cherokees</name>; and though far more dis­
<lb/>tant from the white settlement than any nation 
	    <lb/>East of the <placeName>Mississippi</placeName> or <placeName>Ohio</placeName>, appear evidently
<lb/>to have made greater advances towards the re­
<lb/>finements of true civilization, which cannot in 
<lb/>the least degree be attributed to the good exam­
<lb/>ple of the white people.</p>
          <p>Their internal police and family economy,
<lb/>at once engage the notice of European travel­
<lb/>lers, and incontrovertibly place these people in
<lb/>an illustrious point of view: their liberality, inti­
<lb/>macy, and friendly intercourse one with another,
<lb/>without any restraint of ceremonious formality,
<pb n="59"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="E6r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">59</mw>
<lb/>as if they were even insensible of the use or neces­
<lb/>sity of associating the passions or affections of
<lb/>avarice or ambition. A man goes forth on his
<lb/>business or avocations, he calls in at another 
<lb/>town if he wants food, rest or social conversa­
<lb/>tion; he confidently approaches the door of the
<lb/>first house he chooses, saying, I am come;
<lb/>the good man or woman replies, you are, it is
<lb/>well. Immediately victuals and drink are ready;
<lb/>he eats and drinks a little, then smokes, and
<lb/>converses either of private matters, or news of
<lb/>the town. He rises and says I go, the other an­
<lb/>swers, you do. He then proceeds again, and 
<lb/>stops in at the next habitation he likes, or repairs
<lb/>to the public square, where are people always 
<lb/>conversing by day, or dancing at night, or to
<lb/>some more private assembly, as he likes; he
<lb/>needs no one to introduce him, any more than
<lb/>the black-bird or thrush, when he repairs to the
<lb/>fruitful groves to regale on their luxuries.</p>
          <p>It is astonishing, though a fact, as well as a 
<lb/>sharp reproof to the white people, if they will
<lb/>allow themselves to reflect and form a just esti­
<lb/>mate, and I must own elevates those people to the
<lb/>first rank amongst mankind, that they have been 
<lb/>able to resist the continual efforts of the compli­
<lb/>cated host of vices, that have for ages over-run
<pb n="60"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="E6v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">60</mw>
<lb/>the nations of the old world, and so contaminated
<lb/>their morals, yet more so, since such vast armies
<lb/>of these evil spirits have invaded this continent,
<lb/>and invested them on all sides. Astonishing
<lb/>indeed! when we behold the immoral con­
<lb/>duct of too many white people, who reside
<lb/>amongst them; notwithstanding which, it seems
<lb/>natural, eligible, and even easy, for these simple,
<lb/>illiterate people to put in practice those beautiful
<lb/>lectures delivered to us by the ancient sages and
<lb/>philosophers, and recorded for our instruction.
	    <lb/>I saw a young <name>Indian</name> in the nation, who when
<lb/>present and beholding the scenes of mad intem­
<lb/>perance and folly, acted by the whites in the
<lb/>town, pressed his hand to his breast, and with
<lb/>a smile looked aloft as if struck with astonish­
<lb/>ment, and wrapt in love and adoration to the
<lb/>Diety; as who should say, <said>Oh thou Great and
<lb/>Good Spirit! we are indeed sensible of thy be­
<lb/>nignity and favour to us red men, in denying us
<lb/>the knowledge of white men,—We did not know 
<lb/>before they came amongst us that mankind
<lb/>could become so base, and fall so below the
<lb/>dignity of their nature.—Defend us from their 
	      <lb/>manners, laws and power.</said> The <name>Muscogulges</name>
<lb/>with their confederates, eminently deserve the
<lb/>encomium of all nations, for their wisdom
<pb n="61"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="F1r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">61</mw>
<lb/>and virtue, in resisting, and even repelling the
<lb/>greatest and common enemy of mankind, at least,
<lb/>of most of the European nations; I mean spiritu­
<lb/>ous liquors. The first and most cogent article 
<lb/>in all their treaties with the white people, is, that
<lb/>there shall not be any kind of spirituous liquors
<lb/>sold or brought into their towns; and the traders
<lb/>are allowed but five gallons each, wich is sup­
<lb/>posed to be sufficient for a company, to serve
<lb/>them on the road, and if any of this remains on
<lb/>their approaching the town, they must spill it on
<lb/>the ground, or secrete it on the road, for it must
<lb/>not come into the town.</p>
          <p>How are we to account for their excellent
<lb/>policy in civil government; it cannot derive its
<lb/>influence from coercive laws, for they have no
<lb/>such artificial system. Divine wisdom dictates
<lb/>and they obey. We see and know full well the
<lb/>direful effects of this torrent of evil, which has
<lb/>its source in hell, and we know surely, as well as
<lb/>these savages, how to divert its course and sup­
<lb/>press its inundations. Do we want wisdom and
<lb/>virtue? let our youth then repair to the venera­
	    <lb/>ble councils of the <name>Muscogulges</name>.</p>
          <p>The <name>Indians</name> are by no means idolators, un­
<lb/>less their puffing the tobacco smoke towards the
<lb/>sun, and rejoicing at the appearance of the new
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">F</mw>
<pb n="62"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="F1v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">62</mw>
<lb/>moon, may be termed so. So far from idolatry
<lb/>are they, that they have no images among them,
<lb/>nor any religious rite or ceremony that I could 
<lb/>perceive; but adore the Great Spirit, the giver
<lb/>and taker away of the breath of life, with the
<lb/>most profound and respectful homage. They
<lb/>believe in a future state where the spirit exists,
<lb/>which they call the world of spirits, where they
<lb/>enjoy different degrees of tranquility or comfort,
<lb/>agreeably to their life spent here: a person who
<lb/>in his life has been an industrious hunter, provid­
<lb/>ed well for his family; an intrepid active war­
<lb/>rior, just, upright, and done all the good he
<lb/>could, will, they say, in the world of spirits, live
<lb/>in a warm, pleasant country, where are expan­
<lb/>sive, green, flowery savannas, and high forests,
<lb/>watered with rivers of pure waters, replenished
<lb/>with every species of game, a serene, unclouded
<lb/>sky; in short, where there is a fulness of pleasure.</p>
          <p>These people, like all other nations, are fond 
<lb/>of music and dancing: their music is both vocal
<lb/>and instrumental; but of the latter they have
<lb/>scarcely any thing worth the name; the tambour,
<lb/>rattle-gourd, and a kind of flute, made of the
<lb/>joint of reed; on this instrument they perform
<lb/>badly, it is only young fellows who amuse them­
<lb/>selves on this howling instrument; but the tam­
<pb n="63"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="F2r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">63</mw>
<lb/>bour and rattle, accompanied with their sweet
<lb/>low voices, produce a pathetic harmony, keeping 
<lb/>exact time together, and the countenance of the
<lb/>musician at proper times seems to express the
<lb/>solemn elevated state of the mind; at that time 
<lb/>there appears not only a harmony between him
<lb/>and his instrument, but it instantly touches the
<lb/>feelings of the attentive audience, as the influ­
<lb/>ence of an active and powerful spirit; there is 
<lb/>then an united, universal sensation, and peace­
<lb/>ful union of souls throughout the assembly.
<lb/>Their music, vocal and instrumental, keeps ex­
<lb/>act time with the performers or dancers.</p>
        </quote>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> What can be the reason that the
	  <lb/><name>Indians</name> feel the force of music more powerfully 
<lb/>than we do?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> They have fewer objects to divert
<lb/>their attention, and being much abroad in the
<lb/>open air, have many opportunities of becoming
<lb/>acquainted with the wonders of nature, and are
<lb/>thus strongly impressed with the all pervading
<lb/>presence, and goodness of God—hence their
<lb/>sensibility is deeply excited. In the early ages,
<lb/>music was held in the highest estimation, and
<lb/>exerted great power over the human mind. You
<lb/>know that Bards, at public festivals, sang the
<lb/>deeds of their heroes and great men, and it is
<pb n="64"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="F2v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">64</mw>
<lb/>thus that in many instances historical facts have
<lb/>been transmitted from one generation to another.
	  <lb/>But I will proceed with <persName>Mr. Bartram's</persName> descrip­
<lb/>tion of their dancing.</p>
        <quote rend="bestow((pre(“))(p))post()">
          <p>They have an endless variety of steps, but
<lb/>the most common and most admired and prac­
<lb/>tised amongst themselves, is a slow shuffling al­
<lb/>ternate step, both feet move forward, one after
<lb/>the other, first the right foot foremost, and next
<lb/>the left, moving one after the other in opposite
<lb/>circles, first a circle of young men, and within
<lb/>a circle of young women, moving together oppo­
<lb/>site ways, the men with the course of the sun,
<lb/>and the females contrary to it; the men strike
<lb/>their arm with their open hand, and the girls
<lb/>clap hands and raise their shrill sweet voices,
<lb/>answering an elevated shout of the men, at stated
<lb/>times of termination of the stanzas, and the girls
<lb/>perform an interlude or chorus separately. To
<lb/>accompany their dances, they have songs of dif­
<lb/>ferent classes, some are of a moral character,
<lb/>and seem to be the most esteemed and practised,
<lb/>and answer to the purpose of religious lectures.
<lb/>Some of their most favourite songs and dances,
	    <lb/>they have from the <name>Chactaws</name>, for it appears that
<lb/>these people are very eminent for poetry and
<lb/>music; every town amongst them strive to excel
<pb n="65"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="F3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">65</mw>
<lb/>each other in composing new songs for dances,
<lb/>and by a custom amongst them they must at
<lb/>least have one new song, for exhibition, at every
<lb/>annual busk. Their doleful moral songs or ele­
<lb/>gies, have a quick and sensible effect on their
<lb/>passions; their countenances now dejected, again
<lb/>by an easy transition, become gently elevated,
<lb/>as if in solemn address or supplication, accom­
<lb/>panied with a tremulous, sweet lamentable voice.
<lb/>A stranger is for a moment lost to himself as it
<lb/>were, or his mind associated with the person im­
<lb/>mediately affected, is in danger of revealing his 
<lb/>own distress unawares.</p>
          <p>They have a variety of games for exercise
<lb/>and pastimes: some particular to the male, some
<lb/>to the female sex; and others wherein both sexes
<lb/>are engaged. The ball play is esteemed the
<lb/>most noble and manly exercise. This game is
<lb/>exhibited in an extensive level plain, usually con­
<lb/>tiguous to the town: the inhabitants of one town
<lb/>play against another, in consequence of a chal­
<lb/>lenge, when the youth of both sexes are often
<lb/>engaged, and sometimes stake their whole sub­
<lb/>stance. Here they perform amazing feats of 
<lb/>strength and agility. The game principally con­
<lb/>sists in taking and carrying off the ball from the
<lb/>opposite party, after being hurled into the air,
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">F2</mw>
<pb n="66"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="F3v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">66</mw>
<lb/>midway between two high pillars, which are the
<lb/>goals, and the party who bears off the ball to their
<lb/>pillar, wins the game; each person has a racquet
<lb/>or hurl, which is an instrument of a very curious
<lb/>construction, somewhat resembling a ladle or
<lb/>little hoop-net. The foot ball is likewise a fa­
<lb/>vourite, manly diversion with them. Feasting
<lb/>and dancing in the square at evening, ends all
<lb/>their games. They have, besides, feasts or festi­
<lb/>vals, almost for every month in the year, which 
<lb/>are chiefly dedicated to hunting and agriculture.</p>
          <p>The busk, or feast of first fruits, is their
<lb/>principal festival; this seems to end the last, and
	    <lb/>begin the new year. It commences in <name>August</name>,
<lb/>when their new crops of corn are arrived at ma­
<lb/>turity; and every town celebrates the busk se­
<lb/>parately, when their own harvest is ready. If
<lb/>they have any religious rite or ceremony, this
<lb/>festival is its most solemn celebration. When a
<lb/>town celebrates the busk, having previously pro­
<lb/>vided themselves with new clothes, house­
<lb/>hold utensils, and furniture, they collect all their
<lb/>worn-out clothes, and other despicable things,
<lb/>sweep and cleanse their houses, squares, and the 
<lb/>whole town, and all the remaining grain, and 
<lb/>other old provisions, they cast into one common
<lb/>heap, and consume it with fire. After having
<pb n="67"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="F4r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">67</mw>
<lb/>taken medicine, and fasted for three days, all 
<lb/>the fire in the town is extinguished. During
<lb/>this fast they abstain from the gratification of
<lb/>every appetite and passion whatever. A general
<lb/>amnesty is proclaimed; all malefactors may re­
<lb/>turn to their town, and are absolved from their
<lb/>crimes, which are now forgotten. On the fourth
<lb/>morning the high priest, by rubbing dry wood
<lb/>together, produces new fire in the public square,
<lb/>from whence every habitation in the town is
<lb/>supplied with the new and pure flame. Then
<lb/>the women go forth to the harvest field and bring
<lb/>from thence new corn and fruits, which being
<lb/>prepared in the best manner, in various dishes,
<lb/>and drink withal, is brought with solemnity to
<lb/>the square, where the people are assembled, ap­
<lb/>pareled in their new clothes and decorations.
<lb/>The men having regaled themselves, the remain­
<lb/>der is carried off and distributed among the fam­
<lb/>ilies of the town. The women and children
<lb/>solace themselves in their families, and in the
<lb/>evening repair to the public square, where they
<lb/>dance, sing and rejoice, during the whole night,
<lb/>observing a proper and exemplary decorum.
<lb/>This continues three days, and the four follow­
<lb/>ing days they receive visits and rejoice with their
<pb n="68"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="F4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">68</mw>
<lb/>friends from the neighbouring towns, who have 
<lb/>purified and prepared themselves.</p>
        </quote>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> This manner of celebrating their
<lb/>thanksgiving appears to me very delightful; but
<lb/>their fasts have more solemnity and devotedness
	  <lb/>than ours—why should <persName>Mr. Bartram</persName> be in doubt
<lb/>of this annual festival, being a religious rite? I
<lb/>can perceive no other motive which could induce 
	  <lb/>the <name>Indians</name> to observe a fast, which requires so 
<lb/>many sacrifices and privations.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> There can be no doubt of their fast
<lb/>being commemorated with a view to make atone­
<lb/>ment for sin, and in the hope of propitiating the
<lb/>Deity, and they thus attest their humility and
<lb/>sorrow for past offences. They after, testify
<lb/>their gratitude to the great Creator, by enjoying
<lb/>His bounties with gladness and rejoicing, and in
<lb/>mutual reciprocations of kindness.</p>
        <p>Other writers have noticed these ancient cus­
	  <lb/>toms of the <name>Aborigines</name>. The <persName>Rev. Dr. Morse</persName>, who
<lb/>performed a tour in the summer of <date when="1820">1820</date>, under a
	  <lb/>commission from the President of the <placeName>U. States</placeName>,
<lb/>for the purpose of ascertaining for the government,
<lb/>the actual state of the Indian tribes in our coun­
	  <lb/>try, says,—<quote>The <name>Indians</name> have two sacrifices in
<lb/>each year. The principal festival is celebrated
	    <lb/>in the month of <name>August</name>. The precise time is
<pb n="69"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="F5r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">69</mw>
<lb/>fixed by the head chief counsellors of the
<lb/>town, and takes place, sooner or later, as the
<lb/>state of the affairs of the town, or forwardness of 
<lb/>the corn will admit. It is called the green corn
<lb/>dance, or more properly speaking, the <mentioned rend="pre(‘)post(’)">ceremony
<lb/>of thanksgiving for the first fruits of the earth.</mentioned> 
<lb/>It lasts from four to twelve days, and in some
<lb/>places resembles a large camp meeting. The 
	    <lb/><name>Indians</name> attend from all quarters, with their fami­
<lb/>lies, their tents and provisions, encamping around
<lb/>the council house, or house of worship. The ani­
<lb/>mals killed for the sacrifice are cleansed, the
<lb/>heads, horns, &amp;c. are suspended on a large white
<lb/>pole, with a forked top, which extends over the 
<lb/>roof of the house. The women having prepared 
<lb/>the new corn and provisions for the feast, the
<lb/>men take some of the new corn and rub it be­
<lb/>tween their hands, then on their faces and
<lb/>breasts: They then feast, the great chief having
<lb/>first addressed the crowd, thanking the Great
<lb/>Spirit, for the return of the season, and giving
<lb/>such moral instruction to the people, as he thinks
	    <lb/>proper. On these occasions the <name>Indians</name> are
<lb/>dressed in their best manner, and the whole na­
<lb/>tion attend from the greatest to the smallest.—
<lb/>The quality of provisions is immense, every 
<lb/>one bringing, in proportion to his ability. The
<pb n="70"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="F5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">70</mw>
<lb/>whole is cast into one pile, and distributed dur­
<lb/>ing the continuance of the feast, among the mul­
<lb/>titude, by leaders appointed for the purpose.—In
<lb/>former times this festival was held in the highest
<lb/>veneration, and was a general amnesty, which
	    <lb/>not only absolved the <name>Indians</name> from all punish­
<lb/>ments for crimes, (murder only excepted,) but 
<lb/>seemed to bury guilt itself in oblivion. There
<lb/>are no people more frequent or fervent in their 
<lb/>acknolegments of gratitude to God. Their
<lb/>belief in Him is universal, and their confidence
<lb/>astonishingly strong.</quote></p>
        <p>Religious festivals, such as are here described,
<lb/>were common among all nations; a considerable
<lb/>resemblance has been remarked between ma­
	  <lb/>ny customs of the <name>Jews</name> and the <name>Aborigines</name> of
<lb/>this country, which has induced some, to imag­
	  <lb/>ine our <name>Indians</name> to be the descendants of the lost
	  <lb/>tribes of <name>Israel</name>.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> The description you have last men­
<lb/>tioned, differs somewhat from that given by 
	  <lb/><persName>Bartram</persName>.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> Though these sacrifices and feasts,
<lb/>were celebrated amongs most of the various tribes
	  <lb/>of <name>Indians</name>, we find some variation in the forms
<lb/>observed; yet they are all allowed to bear the
<lb/>same sacred character.—I will now give you
<pb n="71"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="F6r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">71</mw>
	  <lb/><persName>Bartram's</persName> account of the <name>Creeks</name>, or <name>Muscogul­
<lb/>ges</name>, who are under a more strict government, or
	  <lb/>regular civilization, than the <name>Indians</name> in general.</p>
        <quote rend="bestow((pre(“))(p))">
          <p>Their country having a vast frontier, natur­
<lb/>ally accesible and open to the incursions of
<lb/>their enemies, they find themselves under the
<lb/>necessity of associating in large populous towns,
<lb/>as near together as convenient, that they may be
<lb/>enabled to succour and defend one another in
<lb/>case of sudden invasion. This, consequently,
<lb/>occasions deer and bear to be scarce, and diffi­
<lb/>cult to procure, which obliges them to be vigi­
<lb/>lant and industrious; this naturally begets care
<lb/>and serious attention, which we may suppose in
<lb/>some degree forms their natural disposition and
<lb/>manners; and gives them that air of dignified 
<lb/>gravity, so strikingly characteristic in their aged
<lb/>people; and that steadiness, just and cheerful
<lb/>reverence, in the middle-aged and youth, which
<lb/>sits so easy upon them, and appears so natural.
<lb/>For however strange it may appear to us, the
<lb/>same moral duties, which with us form the amia­
<lb/>ble, virtuous character, so difficult to maintain,
<lb/>there, without compulsion or visible restraint,
<lb/>operate like instinct, with a surprising harmony
<lb/>and natural ease, insomuch that it seems impossi­
<pb n="72"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="F6v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">72</mw>
<lb/>ble for them to act out of the common high road
<lb/>to virtue.</p>
          <p>We will now take a view of the lower
	    <lb/><name>Creeks</name> or <name>Seminoles</name>, and the natural disposition
<lb/>which characterizes this people; whom, from
<lb/>the striking contrast, the philosopher may ap­
<lb/>prove or disapprove, as he thinks proper, from
<lb/>the judgment and opinion given by different men.
	    <lb/>The <name>Seminoles</name> are but a weak people with re­
<lb/>spect to numbers, yet they enjoy a superabun­
<lb/>dance of the necessaries of life, with the security
<lb/>of person and property. The hides of deer,
<lb/>bears, &amp;c. together with honey, wax, and other
<lb/>productions of the country, purchase their cloth­
<lb/>ing, equipage and domestic utensils, from the
<lb/>whites. They seem to be free from want or de­
<lb/>sires. No cruel enemy to dread; nothing to
<lb/>give them disquietude, but the gradual encroach­
<lb/>ments of the white people. Thus contented and 
<lb/>undisturbed, they appear as blythe and free 
<lb/>as the birds of the air, and like them as volatile
<lb/>and active, tuneful and vociferous. The visage,
	    <lb/>action and deportment of the <name>Seminoles</name>, form
	    <lb/>the most striking picture of happiness in this
<lb/>life; joy, contentment, love and friendship, seem
<lb/>inherent in them, or predominant in their vital
<lb/>principle, for it leaves them but with the last
<pb n="73"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="G1r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">73</mw>
<lb/>breath. It even seems imposing a constraint
<lb/>upon their ancient chiefs and senators, to main­
<lb/>tain a necessary decorum and solemnity, in their
<lb/>public councils; not even the debility of ex­
<lb/>treme old age, is sufficient to erase from their
<lb/>visages, this joyous simplicity; but, like the gray
<lb/>eve of a serene and calm day, a gladdening
<lb/>cheering blush remains on the western horizon
<lb/>after the sun is set. I doubt not but some of my
<lb/>countrymen, who may read these accounts of the
	    <lb/><name>Indians</name>, which I have endeavoured to relate ac­
<lb/>cording to truth, at least as they appeared to me,
<lb/>will charge me with partiality or prejudice in
<lb/>their favour.</p>
        </quote>
        <p><quote rend="post()">I will now,</quote> (proceeds <persName>Bartram</persName>,) <quote rend="pre()">endeavour
<lb/>to exhibit their vices and immoralities, from my
<lb/>own observations, and knowledge, as well as ac­
<lb/>counts from the white traders who reside amongst 
<lb/>them.</quote></p>
        <p>
          <quote>The <name>Indians</name> make war against, kill and de­
<lb/>stroy their species, and their motives spring from
<lb/>the same erroneous source as they do in all other
<lb/>nations of mankind; that is, the ambition of ex­
<lb/>hibiting to their fellows a superior character of
<lb/>national and personal valour; and thereby im­
<lb/>mortalizing themselves, by transmitting their
<lb/>names with honour and lustre to posterity; or
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">G</mw>
<pb n="74"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="G1v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">74</mw>
<lb/>revenge of their enemy, for public or personal in­
<lb/>sults; or lastly to extend the boundaries of their
<lb/>territories. But I cannot find, upon the strictest
<lb/>enquiry, that their bloody contests at this day
<lb/>are marked with deeper stains of inhumanity or
<lb/>savage cruelty, than may be observed amongst
<lb/>the most civilized nations: they do indeed scalp
<lb/>their slain enemy, but they do not kill the females
<lb/>or children of either sex: the most ancient
	    <lb/>traders, both in the upper and lower <name>Creeks</name>, as­
<lb/>sured me they never saw an instance of either
<lb/>burning or tormenting their captives; though it is
<lb/>said they used to do it formerly. I saw in every 
	    <lb/>town in the nation of <name>Seminoles</name>, that I visited,
<lb/>more or less male captives, some extremely aged,
<lb/>who were free and in as good circumstances, as
<lb/>their masters; and all slaves have their freedom
<lb/>when they marry, which is permitted and en­
<lb/>couraged; when, they and their offspring are
<lb/>every way upon an equality with their conquer­
<lb/>ors. They punish adulterers with great severity,
<lb/>male and female equally alike, by taking off their
<lb/>ears. Infamy and disgrace is supposed to be
<lb/>a sufficient punishment for crimes of less magni­
<lb/>tude. They are fond of games and gambling,
<lb/>and amuse themselves like children, in relating
<lb/>extravagant stories, to cause surprise and mirth.</quote>
        </p>
        <pb n="75"/>
        <milestone unit="sig" n="G2r"/>
        <mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">75</mw>
        <p>In giving a summary view of the character of
<lb/>a people, the result of the writer's conclusions
<lb/>are frequently at variance with what he has him­
<lb/>self previously stated; hence in estimating the
<lb/>qualities of the people described, the only crite­
<lb/>rion by which we are enabled to form a just
<lb/>judgment, is by attending to transactions which
<lb/>came within the scope of the writer's own ob­
<lb/>servation. The opinion given by our author in
<lb/>reference to the habits and dispositions of the
	  <lb/><name>Indians</name>, is abundantly confirmed in the details
<lb/>he has made relative to his reception and enter­
<lb/>tainment by these natives. The situation of
<lb/>their towns, manner of building, with their agri­
<lb/>cultural products, afford a most pleasing picture
<lb/>of rural happiness and independence. The
<lb/>country is beautiful and fertile in a high degree.
<lb/>Oranges, peaches, grapes, with almost every va­
<lb/>riety of fruits, are spontaneously produced; and
<lb/>vegetables of the finest flavour, particularly me­
<lb/>lons; and lastly, they have horses, and every 
<lb/>species of game, in great abundance. Orange
<lb/>groves, intermixed with the most beautiful flow­
<lb/>ering trees and shrubs, in many instances, nearly
<lb/>surround their towns and villages, forming a cool 
<lb/>and fragrant shade.</p>
        <p>I will give you, in the words of <persName>Mr. Bartram</persName>,
<pb n="76"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="G2v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">76</mw>
	  <lb/>a description of the town of <placeName>Cuscowilla</placeName>, and its
<lb/>environs, which may give you an idea of many
<lb/>others, visited by him during this tour.</p>
        <quote rend="bestow( (pre(“)post(”)) (p) )">
          <p>After crossing over the point or branch of
<lb/>the marshes, we entered a noble forest, the land
<lb/>level and the soil fertile; the forest consisted of
<lb/>orange groves, overtopped by grand magnolias,
<lb/>palms, &amp;c., with various kinds of shrubs and 
<lb/>herbaceous plants. We were cheerfully received
<lb/>in this hospitable shade by various tribes of
<lb/>birds, their sprightly songs seemed a prelude to
<lb/>the vicinity of human habitations. This magni­
<lb/>ficent grove was a wing of the vast forests lying 
<lb/>upon the coast of the great and beautiful lake of
	    <lb/><placeName>Cuscowilla</placeName>, at no great distance from us. Con­
<lb/>tinuing eight or nine miles through this sublime
<lb/>forest, we entered an open forest of lofty
<lb/>pines and oaks, on gently swelling sand hills,
<lb/>and presently saw the lake, its waters  sparkling
<lb/>through the open groves. Near the path was a 
<lb/>large artifical mound of earth, on a charming
<lb/>high situation, supposed to be the work of the
	    <lb/>ancient <name>Floridians</name> or <name>Yamazees</name>, with other tra­
<lb/>ces of an Indian town. Here were three or
<lb/>four Indian habitations; the women and chil­
<lb/>dren saluted us with cheerfulness and complai­
<lb/>sance. After riding near a mile farther we ar­
<pb n="77"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="G3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">77</mw>
	    <lb/>rived at <placeName>Cuscowilla</placeName>, near the banks; a pretty
<lb/>brook of water ran through the town, and enter­
<lb/>ed the lake just by.</p>
          <p>We were welcomed to the town, and con­
<lb/>ducted by the young men and maidens to the
<lb/>chief's house, which stood on an eminence, and 
<lb/>was distinguished from the rest by its superior
<lb/>magnitude, and a large flag being hoisted on a
<lb/>high staff at one corner. We immediately
<lb/>alighted; the chief, attended by several ancient
<lb/>men, came to us, and in a very free and socia­
<lb/>ble manner shook our hands, saying at the same 
<lb/>time, <said>you are come.</said> We followed him to an
<lb/>apartment prepared for the reception of their
<lb/>guests. The pipe being filled, was handed 
<lb/>around; after which a large bowl, with what
<lb/>they call their drink, was brought in and set
<lb/>down on a small low table. In this bowl is a 
<lb/>great wooden ladle: each person takes up as
<lb/>much as he pleases, and after drinking, returns 
<lb/>it again into the bowl, with the handle towards
<lb/>the next person in the circle, and so it goes
<lb/>round. After the usual compliments and inqui­
<lb/>ries, the chief trader informed the chief, in the
<lb/>presence of his council or attendants, the purport
<lb/>of our business, with which he expressed his sat­
<lb/>isfaction. He was then informed what the na­
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">G2</mw>
<pb n="78"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="G3v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">78</mw>
<lb/>ture of my errand was, and he received me with
<lb/>complaisance, giving me unlimited permission to
<lb/>travel over the country for the purpose of collect­
<lb/>ing flowers, medicinal plants, &amp;c. saluting me
	    <lb/>by the name of <persName>Pue Puggy</persName>, or the flower hunter,
<lb/>recommending me to the friendship and protec­
<lb/>tion of his people. The next day was agreed on
<lb/>to hold a council and transact the business of our
<lb/>embassy; soon after a considerable number of
	    <lb/><name>Indians</name> assembled around their chief, when the
<lb/>conversation turned to common and familiar
<lb/>topics. The chief is a tall well made man, very
<lb/>affable and cheerful, about sixty years of age,
<lb/>his eyes lively and full of fire, his countenance
<lb/>manly and placid, yet ferocious, or what we call
<lb/>savage, his nose aquiline, his dress extremely
<lb/>simple, but his head trimmed and ornamented in
<lb/>the true Creek mode. The repast was now
<lb/>brought in, consisting of venison stewed with
<lb/>bear's oil, fresh corn cakes, milk and homeny; 
<lb/>and our drink, honey and water, very cool and
<lb/>agreeable. After partaking of this banquet, we
<lb/>took leave and departed for the great savanna.</p>
        </quote>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> How beautiful must be this country
	  <lb/>inhabited by the <name>Creeks</name>, I do not wonder to find
<lb/>they are so unwilling to leave it; neither can I 
<lb/>perceive any thing barbarous in their manners,
<pb n="79"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="G4r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">79</mw>
<lb/>or customs, but on the contrary there is much
<lb/>urbanity, and politeness in their behaviour; this
<lb/>doubtless induced the Chief to grant permission
	  <lb/>to <persName>Mr. Bartram</persName>, in a manner so pleasing, to travel
<lb/>over the country, as they were so much in fear
<lb/>of the encroachments of the white people.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> Their willingness to shew courtesy 
<lb/>to strangers, was unquestionably the reason of
	  <lb/>their allowing <persName>Bartram</persName> to explore the country, as
<lb/>the accounts given by travellers of the Indian 
<lb/>territory, has uniformly incited the desire of our
	  <lb/>people to possess their lands. <persName>Bartram's</persName> descrip­
<lb/>tions are of a nature to create this desire, in the
<lb/>breasts of unprincipled men; he gives here a 
	  <lb/>most magnificent view of the extensive <placeName>Alachua
<lb/>savanna</placeName>, which he says, <quote>is a level green plain,
<lb/>above fifty miles in circumference, and scarcely a
<lb/>tree or bush to be seen on it. It is encircled with
<lb/>high, sloping hills, covered with waving forests
<lb/>and fragrant Orange groves, rising from an ex­
<lb/>huberantly fertile soil. The towering magnolia,
<lb/>grandiflora and transcendent Palm, stand con­
<lb/>spicuous amonst them. At the same time are
<lb/>seen innumerable droves of cattle, herds of deer,
<lb/>squadrons of the beautiful fleet Seminole horse,
<lb/>flocks of turkeys, civilized communities of the
<pb n="80"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="G4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">80</mw>
<lb/>sonorous watchful crane, mixing together, happy
<lb/>in the enjoyment of nature's bounties.</quote></p>
        <p>
          <quote>Soon after sun-rise a party of <name>Indians</name> ap­
<lb/>peared upon the savanna to collect together 
<lb/>several herds of cattle, which they drove along
<lb/>near our camp towards the town. One of the
<lb/>party came up, and informed us that the cattle
	    <lb/>belonged to the chief of <placeName>Cuscowilla</placeName>, that he had
<lb/>ordered some of the best steers to be slaughtered
<lb/>for a general feast for the whole town, in com­
<lb/>pliment of our arrival, and pacific negotiations.
<lb/>We soon followed them to town, in order to be
<lb/>at the council at the hour appointed. Upon our
<lb/>arrival we repaired to the public square or coun­
<lb/>cil-house, where the chiefs and senators were
<lb/>already convened; the warriors and young men
<lb/>assembled soon after, the business being trans­
<lb/>acted in public, which was soon terminated to
<lb/>the satisfaction of both parties. The banquet
<lb/>succeeded; the ribs and choisest fat pieces of
<lb/>the bullocks, excellently well barbecued, were 
<lb/>brought into the apartment of the public square, 
<lb/>constructed and appointed for feasting; bowls 
<lb/>and kettles of stewed flesh and broth were
<lb/>brought in for the next course.</quote>
        </p>
        <p rend="post(”)"><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> Why mother I had no idea that 
	  <lb/>entertainments were given by the <name>Indians</name> in this
<pb n="81"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="G5r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">81</mw>
<lb/>style; they must have had spacious apartments,
<lb/>to accommodate so large a party.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> In this place <persName>Bartram</persName> does not men­
<lb/>tion the size  of the council house, or mode of
<lb/>its construction; yet shortly after he describes
	  <lb/>one in the town of <placeName>Cowe</placeName>, belonging to the <name>Chero­
<lb/>kees</name>, which would furnish ample accommodation
<lb/>for a numerous assembly, to which this undoubt­
<lb/>edly bore a strong resemblance.</p>
        <quote rend="bestow( (pre(“)post(”)) (p) )">
          <p>But I will now proceed to furnish the des­
	    <lb/>cription of the town of <placeName>Cuscowilla</placeName>, which is the
	    <lb/>capital of the <name>Alachua tribe</name>, and contains about
<lb/>thirty habitations, each of which consists of two
<lb/>houses of nearly the same size, about thirty feet in
<lb/>length, twelve feet wide, and about the same in
<lb/>height. The door is placed midway on one side
<lb/>or in the front. This house is divided into two
<lb/>apartments, one of which is the cook room and
<lb/>common hall, and the other the lodging room.
<lb/>The other house is nearly of the same dimen­
<lb/>sions, standing about twenty yards from the
<lb/>dwelling house, its end fronting the door. The
<lb/>building is two stories high, and constructed in
<lb/>a different manner. It is divided transversely, as
<lb/>the other, but the end next the dwelling house
<lb/>is open on three sides, supported by posts or pil­
<lb/>lars. It has an open loft or platform, the ascent
<pb n="82"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="G5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">82</mw>
<lb/>to which, is by a portable stair or ladder; this is
<lb/>a pleasant, airy, cool situation, and here the
<lb/>master or chief of a family retires to repose in
<lb/>the hot seasons, or receives his guests or visitors.
<lb/>The other half of this building is closed on all
<lb/>sides, the lowest or ground part is a potatoe
<lb/>house, and the upper story over it a granary for
<lb/>corn and other provisions. Their houses are 
<lb/>constructed of a kind of frame. In the first
<lb/>place strong corner pillars are fixed in the ground,
<lb/>with others somewhat less, ranging on a line be­
<lb/>tween; these are strengthened by cross pieces 
<lb/>of timber, and the whole with the roof is covered
<lb/>close with the bark of the Cypress tree. The
<lb/>dwelling stands near the middle of a square yard,
<lb/>encompassed by a low bank, which is always
<lb/>carefully swept. Their towns are clean, the
<lb/>inhabitants being particular in laying all their
<lb/>filth at a proper distance from their dwellings,
<lb/>which undoubtedly contributes to the healthiness
<lb/>of their habitations.</p>
          <p>The town stands on the most pleasant situa­
<lb/>tion that could be well imagined, in an inland
<lb/>country; upon a high swelling ridge of sand
<lb/>hills, within three or four hundred yards of a 
<lb/>large and beautiful lake, the circular shore of
<lb/>which continually washes a sandy beach, under
<pb n="83"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="G6r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">83</mw>
<lb/>a moderately high sloping bank, terminated on
<lb/>one side by extensive forests, consisting of orange
<lb/>groves, overtopped with grand Magnolias, palms,
<lb/>poplar, and others already noticed, and the op­
<lb/>posite point of the crescent, gradually retires
<lb/>with hommochy projecting points indenting the
<lb/>grassy marshes, and lastly terminates in infinite
<lb/>green plains and meadows, united with the skies
<lb/>and waters of the lake; at present the ground
<lb/>betwixt the town and the lake is adorned by an
<lb/>open grove of tall pine trees, which, standing at
<lb/>a considerable distance from each other, admit a
<lb/>delightful prospect of the sparkling waters. The
<lb/>lake abounds with various excellent fish, and wild
<lb/>fowl: there are incredible numbers of the latter,
<lb/>especially in the winter season.</p>
        </quote>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> It appears very strange that the 
	  <lb/><name>Indians</name> should be represented by some, as hav­
<lb/>ing no permanent dwelling places, but perpetual­
<lb/>ly roaming in search of a precarious subsistence; 
<lb/>occupying miserable huts, scarcely capable of 
<lb/>affording shelter, or convenience of any sort;
	  <lb/>when <persName>Mr. Bartram</persName>, and many others, so deserv­
<lb/>ing of confidence, describe their situation so
<lb/>pleasant, and desirable.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> This is easily explained; people of
<lb/>contracted and sordid minds, from having been
<pb n="84"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="G6v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">84</mw>
<lb/>early instructed to limit the goodness of God to
<lb/>a small portion of the human race, embracing 
<lb/>those only who belong to their sect or party,
<lb/>imagine that all who are removed from their own
<lb/>narrow circle must be ignorant and vile. Influ­
<lb/>enced by these impressions, they perversely mis­
<lb/>represent and distort the gifts and high endow­
<lb/>ments which the beneficent Father of the Uni­
<lb/>verse hath so abundantly bestowed on His
<lb/>children, without partiality, and thus by these
<lb/>delusive expedients they persuade themselves
<lb/>that it is not criminal to wrest from those, whom
<lb/>they call heathen, their possessions and all they
	  <lb/>hold most dear; hence, having forced the <name>In­
<lb/>dians</name> to become vagrants, by depriving them of
<lb/>the means of subsistence, and reducing them to
<lb/>a state of desperation; they are stimulated to
<lb/>conceal their guilty deeds by representing the
	  <lb/><name>Indians</name> as unworthy, and incapable of enjoying
<lb/>or improving the bounties of nature. Poli­
<lb/>cy, also influences many to acquiesce in these
<lb/>misrepresentations, who are desirous of enjoying
<lb/>spoil thus acquired without disturbance, or feel­
<lb/>ing their responsibility to vindicate or relieve the
	  <lb/>oppressed <name>Indians</name>. It is generally maintained
	  <lb/>that the male <name>Indians</name> are too indolent to bestow
<lb/>any attention on agriculture, and that a small
<pb n="85"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="H1r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">85</mw>
<lb/>quantity of corn is produced by the labour of the
<lb/>women only, as the men feel it to be derogatory
<lb/>to lend them any assistance; little attention
<lb/>therefore is bestowed on the rising plants, and of
<lb/>course they frequently are in great want of this
<lb/>necessary article of food. It is however only
<lb/>necessary to refer to the first settlement of the
<lb/>country, to be assured that corn was raised in
<lb/>abundance by the natives, who frequently re­
<lb/>lieved the settlers from much suffering by their
<lb/>liberal supplies.</p>
        <p><persName>Bartram</persName> gives a distinct account of their hus­
	  <lb/>bandry, in closing his description of <placeName>Cuscowilla</placeName>.
<lb/><quote rend="post()">They plant</quote> (says this writer,) <quote rend="pre()">but little here
<lb/>about the town; only a small garden at each
<lb/>habitation, consisting of corn, beans, citruls, &amp;c.
<lb/>Their plantation, which supplies them with the
<lb/>chief of their vegetable provisions, lies on the rich,
	    <lb/>prolific lands bordering on the great <placeName>Alachua
<lb/>savanna</placeName>, about two miles distance. This plan­
<lb/>tation is one common enclosure, and is worked
<lb/>and tended by the whole community; yet every
<lb/>family has its particular part, according to its
<lb/>own appointment, marked off when planted; and
<lb/>this portion receives the common labour until
<lb/>ripe, when each family gathers and deposits in
<lb/>its granary its own proper share, setting apart a
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">H</mw>
<pb n="86"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="H1v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">86</mw>
<lb/>small gift or contribution for the public granary,
<lb/>which stands in the centre of the plantation.
<lb/>The youth, under the supervisal of some of their
<lb/>ancient people are, daily stationed in the fields,
<lb/>and are continually whooping and halooing to
<lb/>chase away crows, black-birds, and such preda­
<lb/>tory animals; and the lads are armed with bows
<lb/>and arrows, and being trained up to it from their
<lb/>early youth, are sure at a mark, and in the
<lb/>course of the day load themselves with squirrels,
<lb/>birds, &amp;c. The men in their turn parole the 
<lb/>cornfields at night to protect them from the 
<lb/>depredations of bears, raccoons,</quote> &amp;c.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> Do you suppose, mother, that all
<lb/>the natives of this country were as attentive to 
<lb/>the cultivation of their lands, as were those of 
	  <lb/><placeName>Cuscowilla</placeName>?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> Unquestionably those were whom
	  <lb/><persName>Mr. Bartram</persName> visited, as he constantly speaks of
<lb/>the abundance which prevailed, and the fine plan­
<lb/>tations which every where met his view, in, or 
<lb/>near, their settlements<unclear reason="flawed-reproduction">;</unclear> nor can we doubt of the
<lb/>attention paid to agriculture at the period when
	  <lb/>this country was first discovered. <persName>Mr. Bartram</persName>
<lb/>says, <quote>that in the old Spanish highway across
	    <lb/>the isthmus of <placeName>Florida</placeName> to <placeName>Saint Marks</placeName>, in the bay
	    <lb/>of <placeName>Apalache</placeName>, they passed through a great extent
<pb n="87"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="H2r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">87</mw>
<lb/>of ancient Indian fields, now grown over with
<lb/>forests of stately trees, orange groves, and luxuri­
<lb/>ant herbage, the old trader, his associate, inform­
	    <lb/>ed him it was the ancient <placeName>Alachua</placeName>, the capital
<lb/>of that famous and powerful tribe, who peopled
<lb/>the hills surrounding the savanna, when in days
<lb/>of old, they could assemble by thousands at ball
<lb/>play, and other juvenile diversions and athletic
<lb/>exercises, over those then happy fields and
<lb/>green plains. And there is no reason to doubt
<lb/>of his account being true, as almost every step
<lb/>we take over those fertile heights, discovers re­
<lb/>mains and traces of human habitations and cul­
<lb/>tivation.</quote></p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> By what people were those <name>Indians</name>
<lb/>destroyed who were so numerous and happy?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> I believe both the <name>French</name> and
	  <lb/><name>Spaniards</name> made settlements in this part of the
<lb/>country, who, like all other nominal christian
<lb/>settlers, disregarded the ties of gratitude, and hu­
<lb/>manity, and sacrificed with merciless barbarity,
<lb/>the natives by whose kindness, and generous
<lb/>hospitality, they had been preserved from famine
<lb/>and disease.</p>
        <p>Some years past, in a work entitled <title rend="pre(‘)post(’)">Sketches
	    <lb/>historical and descriptive of <placeName>Louisiana</placeName>, by <persName>Major 
	      <lb/>Stoddard</persName>, member of the <orgName>New York Historical
<pb n="88"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="H2v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">88</mw>
<lb/>Society</orgName></title>, &amp;c. who was appointed to take posses­
	  <lb/>sion of <placeName>Upper Lousiana</placeName> under the treaty of ses­
<lb/>sion, the writer says, <quote>the records and other
<lb/>public documents were open to my inspection,
<lb/>and as it was my fortune to be stationed about
	    <lb/>five years on various parts of the lower <placeName>Mississip­
	      <lb/>pi</placeName>, and nearly six months on <placeName>Red River</placeName>, my
	    <lb/>enquiries gradually extended to <placeName>Louisiana</placeName> in
<lb/>general.</quote></p>
        <p>The author bestows ample praises on the
	  <lb/><name>Natches</name>, as a comparatively polished and civi­
<lb/>ized tribe. <quote rend="post()">They had an established religion
<lb/>among them, in many particulars rational and
<lb/>consistent, as likewise regular orders of priest­
<lb/>hood. They had a temple to the Great Spirit,
<lb/>in which they preserved the eternal fire.</quote></p>
        <p><quote>The civil policy of the <name>Natches</name> partook of
<lb/>the refinements of a people, in some degree
<lb/>learned and scientific; it exhibited penetration
<lb/>and wisdom, and was calculated to make them 
<lb/>happy. They had kings or chiefs, invested with
<lb/>absolute power, as likewise a kind of subordinate 
<lb/>nobility, among them.</quote> It is added, <quote rend="post()">they
<lb/>were just, generous and humane, and never fail­
<lb/>ed to extend relief to objects of distress. They
<lb/>were well acquainted with the properties of medi­
<lb/>cinal plants, and the cures they performed, par­
<pb n="89"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="H3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">89</mw>
	    <lb/>ticularly among the <name>French</name>, appear almost in­
<lb/>credible. What is much more to their praise,
<lb/>they never deemed it glorious to destroy the hu­
<lb/>man species, and for this reason seldom waged
<lb/>any other than defensive war.</quote></p>
        <p>
          <quote>The <name>Natches</name> had received favourably the
<lb/>French adventurers; had supplied them with
<lb/>provisions, assisted them in their tillage, and
<lb/>in building their houses; had saved them
<lb/>from famine and death; and continued to pos­
<lb/>sess the strongest disposition to oblige; and
<lb/>would still have been eminently useful to them,
<lb/>had they not been treated with indignity and in­
<lb/>justice, by the commandant of a French fort.
<lb/>They began to take as might be expected a se­
<lb/>vere revenge, but were induced to stop short of 
<lb/>its complete execution, and a treaty of peace
<lb/>restored confidence, apparently on both sides,
	    <lb/>and in reality on the side of the <name>Natches</name>. But
	    <lb/>the civilized party, the <emph><name>Christians</name></emph>, were meditat­
<lb/>ing a plan of extermination. A very strong mili­
<lb/>tary body, concealed its movements so well as to
<lb/>be enabled to fall suddenly on the habitations of 
	    <lb/>the <name>Indians</name>, of whom a large proportion perished
<lb/>in a slaughter prolonged for several days, and
<lb/>not terminated till the surrender, at the requisi­
	    <lb/>tion of the <name>French</name>, of the head of a peculiarly
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">H2</mw>
<pb n="90"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="H3v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">90</mw>
<lb/>obnoxious chief. The remainder of the nation,
<lb/>still considerable, continued to be treated with
<lb/>the most galling injustice, and about six years
<lb/>afterwards were suddenly ordered to clear away
<lb/>their huts, for the establishing a French settle­
<lb/>ment. Stimulated to madness by this outrage,
<lb/>they endeavoured to destroy the settlements.
<lb/>This was revenged by measures which compelled
	    <lb/>the <name>Indians</name> to retire precipitately into a distant
<lb/>part of the wilderness. Thither they were fol­
<lb/>lowed, and their most desperate efforts could not
<lb/>avert their fate. A few escaped and incorpor­
<lb/>ated themselves with other tribes; while the re­
<lb/>mainder of those that survived the carnage were
	    <lb/>taken, enslaved, and at last transported to <placeName>St. 
<lb/>Domingo</placeName>.</quote>
        </p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> Did the <name>Natches</name> resemble the
	  <lb/><name>Creek Indians</name>?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> It is probable there was not any
<lb/>great dissimilarity between them, as they were
<lb/>continguous to each other, and the natives of our
<lb/>Southern clime bear a strong resemblance in
<lb/>their habits and dispositions, with the difference
<lb/>only, which is found between those who dwell
<lb/>in populous towns, where a degree of refinement
<lb/>prevails, and the people of the country; yet we
<lb/>find that all of them had a common object of
<lb/>worship, and that adoration was paid to the
<pb n="91"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="H4r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">91</mw>
<lb/>Great Spirit, in singleness of beast.—Fire also
<lb/>appears to have been held in veneration as a sa­
<lb/>cred element, and an emblem of purity, as we
	  <lb/>find it to have been both by the <name>Persians</name> and
	  <lb/><name>Hindoos</name>, and other Pagan nations.</p>
        <p>From the writings of <persName>Stoddard</persName>, we learn, that
	  <lb/>both the <name>Spaniards</name> and <name>French</name> strove to exceed
<lb/>each other in acts of barbarity, <quote>which no or­
<lb/>dinary improvement in depravity could rival.</quote>
<lb/>The wretched policy and want of principle, in
<lb/>the European adventurers, in destroying the na­
<lb/>tives, was soon followed by that retributive jus­
<lb/>tice, which is not long delayed. Their cupidity
<lb/>incited them so powerfully to possess lands in
<lb/>the new world, that they were impelled to prac­ 
<lb/>tice on each other, enormities too disgusting to 
<lb/>bear repetition; and thus they alternately were
<lb/>driven out or exterminated. A just and liberal
<lb/>policy, in the first settlers, would doubtless have
<lb/>secured the confidence and affection with their new
<lb/>friends, and secured to them a peaceful and
<lb/>happy country. What I have related to you of 
	  <lb/>the <name>Natches</name>, is taken from the <title>Analectic Maga­
	    <lb/>zine</title>, where <persName>Major Stoddard's</persName> work is hand­
<lb/>somely spoken of; and I promise myself much
<lb/>pleasure in perusing the volume at some future
<pb n="92"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="H4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">92</mw>
<lb/>period, as he had testified his aversion to acts of
<lb/>injustice and barbarity, in strong terms, and
	  <lb/>considers the <name>Indians</name> as a part of the human 
<lb/>race, not unworthy respect and commisseration.
<lb/>His morality is not of that acommodating kind,
<lb/>which some have the hardiness to maintain, who
<lb/>boldly assert that our obligations to act with jus­
<lb/>tice and honesty in our dealings, may be dispen­
	  <lb/>sed with in treaties with our defenceless <name>Indians</name>.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> Are we not bound to treat the unfor­
<lb/>tunate and helpless with more kindness and at­
<lb/>tention, than is due to the prosperous and happy?
<lb/>and does it not discover a base and sordid spirit,
<lb/>to take advantage of the weak and defenceless?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> You are right, my dear girl, and we
<lb/>certainly have reason to conclude that those who
<lb/>advance such sentiments, do right only when
<lb/>they fear to do wrong; but when measures are 
<lb/>adopted by a government, which accord with 
<lb/>these base and sordid views, and set at defiance
<lb/>the eternal laws of justice and mercy, the whole
<lb/>nation is implicated who do not raise their voices,
<lb/>in contemning this violation of the moral princi­
	  <lb/>ple. I have much yet to tell you of the <name>Creek
<lb/>Indians</name>, but must defer what I have further to
<lb/>say until another opportunity is afforded us.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> Pray, mother, allow me to ask, if
<pb n="93"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="H5r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">93</mw>
<lb/>it be not extraordinary that so little interest is
<lb/>shown for our suffering natives, when so much 
	  <lb/>excitement is manifested for the <name><choice><sic>G</sic><corr>C</corr></choice>reeks</name>?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> We can have small confidence in
<lb/>the benevolence of those who profess so much
	  <lb/>sensibility for the unfortunate <name>Greeks</name>, yet not­
<lb/>withstanding this display of sympathy, make no
	  <lb/>effort to save those <name>Indians</name> whom we have so 
<lb/>deeply injured. We appear desirous of having
<lb/>it believed, that we would willingly put a stop to 
<lb/>the abominable traffic in slaves, but cannot with­
<lb/>out the cooperation of other nations; yet the an­
<lb/>nual amount of the sums employed in foreign
<lb/>missions, which must at best be deemed a very
<lb/>uncertain good, would go far, it is believed, to
<lb/>liberate those whom we so unjustly hold in bon­
<lb/>dage; but no pretext can excuse our want of ex­
	  <lb/>ertion in favour of our unhappy <name>Indians</name>, who are
<lb/>altogether dependent on us for safety and pro­
<lb/>tection, as to us alone must be imputed the guilt
<lb/>of their cruel persecution. I must own that I
<lb/>am filled with mingled emotions of shame and
<lb/>regret, when I reflect on the appearance it must
<lb/>have, in the opinion of foreigners, that whilst we
<lb/>busy ourselves in futile attempts to remedy the
<lb/>evils which exist in distant lands, we should allow
<lb/>of such enormous abuses in our own country; and
<pb n="94"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="H5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">94</mw>
<lb/>that whilst we boast of our freedom, and our
<lb/>liberal institutions, and boldly assert, that the
<lb/>rights of men are better understood and acted on
<lb/>in this country, than in any other, we should
<lb/>evince our entire disregard of justice and mercy,
<lb/>in our treatment of our fellow men, whom we
<lb/>have so unworthily subjected.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> Shall you have leisure this afternoon,
	  <lb/>mother, to give us a further account of the <name>In­
<lb/>dians</name>?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> <persName>Mr. Bartram's</persName> description of the
	  <lb/>beautiful vale of <placeName>Keowe</placeName>, which he says <quote>is per­
<lb/>haps as celebrated for fertility, fruitfulness, and
	    <lb/>fine prospects, as the fields of <placeName>Pharsalia</placeName>, or the
	    <lb/>vale of <placeName>Tempe</placeName>,</quote> will give you a high idea of
<lb/>this enchanting spot.</p>
        <p>
          <quote>We now saw the town of <placeName>Cowe</placeName>, the elevated
	    <lb/>peaks of the <placeName>Jore mountains</placeName>, at a distance,
	    <lb/>the <placeName>Jore village</placeName> in a beautiful lawn, lifted up 
<lb/>many thousands feet higher than our present
<lb/>situation, besides many other villages and
<lb/>settlements, on the sides of the mountains, at
<lb/>various distances and elevations; the silver rivu­
<lb/>lets gliding by them, and snow-white cataracts
<lb/>glimmering on the sides of the lofty hills, and the
	    <lb/>bold promontories of the <placeName>Jore mountain</placeName> stepping
	    <lb/>in to the <placeName>Tanase river</placeName>, whilst his foaming waters
<pb n="95"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="H6r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">95</mw>
<lb/>rushed between them. Proceeding on our re­
	    <lb/>turn to <placeName>Cowe</placeName>, we continued through part of the
<lb/>high forests skirting on the meadows; and began
<lb/>to ascend the hills of a ridge, which we were un­
<lb/>der the necessity of crossing and having gained
<lb/>its summit, enjoyed a most enchanting view; a 
<lb/>vast expanse of green meadows and strawberry
<lb/>fields; a meadering river, flowing through
<lb/>swelling green knowls, embellished with flowers
<lb/>and fruitful strawberry beds; flocks of turkies
<lb/>strolling about them; herds of deer bounding
<lb/>over the hills; companies of young innocent
<lb/>Cherokee virgins, some busy gathering the rich
<lb/>fruit, others, having already filled their baskets,
<lb/>lay reclined under the shade of native bowers of
<lb/>magnolias, &amp;c. bathing in the cool streams;
<lb/>whilst others, more gay, were yet collecting 
<lb/>strawberries, or chasing their companions, and
<lb/>staining their lips and cheeks with the rich fruit.
<lb/>We cautiously made our approaches undiscover­
<lb/>ed, almost to the joyous scene of action, when
<lb/>some matrons espying us, gave the alarm, time
<lb/>enough for the nymphs to assemble together.
<lb/>We however pursued and gained ground on a
<lb/>group of them, who had incautiously strolled to
<lb/>a greater distance from their guardian, and find­
<lb/>ing their retreat now like to be cut off, took
<pb n="96"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="H6v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">96</mw>
<lb/>shelter under cover of a little grove; but on per­
<lb/>ceiving themselves to be discovered by us, con­
<lb/>fidently and decently advanced to meet us, half
<lb/>unveiling their faces, and with native innocence
<lb/>and cheerfulness, presented their little baskets,
<lb/>telling us their fruit was ripe and good. We
<lb/>accepted a basket, sat down and regaled our­
<lb/>selves on the delicious fruit, encircled by the
<lb/>whole assembly of these innocent, jocose, sylvan
<lb/>nymphs; by this time the several parties, under
<lb/>the conduct of the elder matrons, had disposed
<lb/>themselves in companies on the green banks.
<lb/>My young companion, the trader, by concessions
<lb/>and suitable apologies for the bold intrusion, en­
<lb/>gaged them to bring their collections to his
<lb/>house; we parted friendly.</quote>
        </p>
        <p>In relating the scenes described by <persName>Mr. Bar­
<lb/>tram</persName>, I omit much which is merely expressive of
<lb/>admiration, as my design is to give as plain a
<lb/>detail as I apprehend to be consistent with truth,
<lb/>and of course my narrative in many instances is 
<lb/>abruptly introduced. This writer appears en­
<lb/>chanted with the beauties of nature, and the
<lb/>simplicity of rural life, and describes in glowing
<lb/>language the appearance of the country previous
	  <lb/>to his arrival in <placeName>Cowe</placeName>.</p>
        <quote rend="bestow( (pre(“)post(”)) (p) )">
          <p>This town consists of about one hundred
<pb n="97"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="I1r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">97</mw>
	    <lb/>dwellings, near the banks of the <placeName>Tanase</placeName>, on
	    <lb/>both sides of the river. The <name>Cherokees</name> con­
<lb/>struct their habitations, on a different plan from
	    <lb/>the <name>Creeks</name>, that is one oblong square build­
<lb/>ing, of one story high; the materials consisting
<lb/>of logs or trunks of trees stripped of their bark,
<lb/>notched at their ends, fixed one upon another,
<lb/>and afterward plastered well, both inside and
<lb/>out, with clay well tempered with dry grass, and
<lb/>the whole covered or roofed with the bark of the 
<lb/>chesnut tree, or long broad shingles. This
<lb/>building is however, partitioned transversely,
<lb/>forming three apartments, which communicate
<lb/>with each other by inside doors; each house has
<lb/>besides a little conical house, covered with dirt,
<lb/>called the winter or hot house; this stands a
<lb/>few yards distant from the mansion house, oppo­
<lb/>site the front door.</p>
          <p>The council or town house is a large rotun­
<lb/>da, capable of accommodating several hundred
<lb/>people: it stands on the top of an ancient artifi­
<lb/>cial mount of earth, of about twenty feet perpen­
<lb/>dicular, and the rotunda on the top of it being
<lb/>above thirty feet more, gives the whole fabric an
<lb/>elevation of near sixty feet from the common 
<lb/>surface of the ground. But it may be proper to
<lb/>observe, that this mount on which the rotunda
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">I</mw>
<pb n="98"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="I1v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">98</mw>
<lb/>stands, is of a more ancient date than the build­
<lb/>ing, and perhaps was raised for another purpose.
	    <lb/>The <name>Cherokees</name> themselves are ignorant by what
<lb/>people, or for what purpose, these artificial hills
<lb/>were raised; they have various stories concern­
<lb/>ing them, which amount to no more than mere
<lb/>conjecture; but they have a tradition common
	    <lb/>with other nations of <name>Indians</name>, that they found
<lb/>them in much the same condition as they now
<lb/>appear, when their ancestors arrived from the
<lb/>West, and possessed themselves of the country,
<lb/>after vanquishing the nations of red men who
<lb/>then inhabited it, who themselves found these
<lb/>mounts, when they took possession of the coun­
<lb/>try; the former possessors delivering the same
<lb/>story concerning them; perhaps they were de­
<lb/>signed and appropriated by the people, who con­
<lb/>structed them, to some religious purpose, as
<lb/>great altars and temples, similar to the high pla­
<lb/>ces and sacred groves, anciently amongst the
	    <lb/><name>Canaanites</name>, and other nations of <name>Palestine</name> and
	    <lb/><name>Judea</name>.—The rotunda is constructed after the
<lb/>following manner: they first fix in the ground a
<lb/>circular range of posts or trunks of trees, about
<lb/>six feet high, at equal distance, which are notch­
<lb/>ed at top, to receive into them, from one to
<lb/>another, a range of beams or wall plates; within
<pb n="99"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="I2r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">99</mw>
<lb/>this is another circular order of very large and
<lb/>strong pillars, above twelve feet high, notched in
<lb/>like manner at top, to receive another range of
<lb/>wall plates; and within this is yet another or
<lb/>third range of stronger and higher pillars, but
<lb/>fewer in number, and standing at a greater dis­
<lb/>tance from each other; and lastly, in the centre
<lb/>stands a very strong pillar which forms the pin­
<lb/>nacle of the building, and to which the rafters
<lb/>centre at the top; these rafters are strengthened
<lb/>and bound together by cross beams or laths,
<lb/>which sustain the roof, which is a layer of bark
<lb/>neatly placed and tight enough to exclude the
<lb/>rain, and sometimes they cast a thin superficies
<lb/>of earth over all. There is but one large door,
<lb/>which serves at the same time to admit light
<lb/>from without, and for the smoke to escape when
<lb/>a fire is kindled; but as there is but a small fire
<lb/>kept sufficient to give light at night, and that
<lb/>fed with dry, small, round wood, divested of its
<lb/>bark, there is but little smoke. All around the
<lb/>inside of the building, betwixt the second range
<lb/>of pillars and the wall, is a range of cabins or 
<lb/>sofas, consisting of two or three steps, one
<lb/>above or behind the other, in theatrical order,
<lb/>where the assembly sit or lean down; these so­
<lb/>fas are covered with mats or carpets, very cu­
<pb n="100"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="I2v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">100</mw>
<lb/>riously made of thin splints of ash or oak, woven
<lb/>or platted together: near the great pillar in the
<lb/>centre the fire is kindled for light, near which
<lb/>the musicians seat themselves, and round about
<lb/>the performers exhibit their dances and other
<lb/>shows at public festivals, which happen almost
<lb/>every night throughout the year.</p>
          <p>About the close of the evening, I accomp­
	    <lb/>nied <persName>Mr. Galahan</persName> and other white traders to the
<lb/>rotunda, where was a great festival, music and 
<lb/>dancing. This assembly was held principally
<lb/>to rehearse the ball-play dance, this town being
<lb/>challenged to play against another the next day.
<lb/>The people being assembled and seated in order,
<lb/>and the musicians having taken their station,
<lb/>the ball opens, first with a long harangue or ora­
<lb/>tion, spoken by an aged chief, in commendation
<lb/>of the manly exercise of the ball-play, recounting 
<lb/>the many brilliant victories which the town of
	    <lb/><placeName>Cowe</placeName> had gained over the other towns in the
<lb/>nation, not neglecting to recite his own exploits,
<lb/>together with other aged men now present, coad­
<lb/>jutors in the performance of these athletic games
<lb/>in their youthful days. The oration was deliv­
<lb/>ered with great spirit and eloquence, and was
<lb/>designed to influence the passions of the young
<lb/>men present, excite them to emulation, and in­
<pb n="101"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="I3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">101</mw>
<lb/>spire them with ambition. This prologue being 
<lb/>ended, the musicians began, both vocal and in­
<lb/>strumental; when presently a company of girls,
<lb/>hand in hand, dressed in clean white robes, and
<lb/>ornamented with beads, bracelets, and a profu­
<lb/>sion of gay ribbons, entering the door, immedi­
<lb/>ately began to sing their responses in a gentle
<lb/>low and sweet voice, and formed themselves in a 
<lb/>semicircular file or line, in two ranks, back to
<lb/>back, facing the spectators and musicians, mov­
<lb/>ing round and round. This continued about a 
<lb/>quarter of an hour, when we were surprised by a
<lb/>sudden loud and shrill whoop, uttered at once by
<lb/>a company of young fellows, who came in briskly 
<lb/>after one another, with rackets or hurls in one
<lb/>hand. These champions were well dressed,
<lb/>painted, and ornamented with moccasins, silver
<lb/>bracelets, gorgets, and wampum, with high wav­
<lb/>ing plumes in their diadems; they immediately 
<lb/>formed themselves in a semicircular rank also,
<lb/>in front of the girls, when these changed their
<lb/>order, and formed a single rank, parallel to the 
<lb/>men, raising their voices in responses to the
<lb/>tunes of the young champions, the semicircles
<lb/>continually moving round. There was some­
<lb/>thing singular and diverting in their step and
<lb/>motions, and I imagine not to be learned to ex­
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">I2</mw>
<pb n="102"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="I3v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">102</mw>
<lb/>actness, but with great attention and perse­
<lb/>verance; they at the same time, and in the same
<lb/>motion, moved on obliquely, or sideways; so that
<lb/>the circle performed a double complex motion in
<lb/>its progression, and at stated times exhibited a
<lb/>grand or universal movement, instantly and un­
<lb/>expectedly to the spectators, by each rank turn­
<lb/>ing to right and left, and taking each others
<lb/>places: the movements were managed with in­
<lb/>conceivable alertness and address, and accom­
<lb/>panied with an instantaneous and universal ele­
<lb/>vation of the voice.</p>
          <p>The <name>Cherokees</name>, besides the ball-play dance,
<lb/>have a variety of others equally entertaining.
<lb/>The men especially exercise themselves with a
<lb/>variety of gesticulations, and capers; some of
<lb/>them are ludicrous and diverting enough; and
<lb/>they have others, which are of a martial order,
<lb/>and others of the chase; these seem to be some­
<lb/>what of a tragical nature, wherein they exhibit
<lb/>astonishing feats of military prowess, masculine
<lb/>strength and activity. Indeed all their dances
<lb/>and musical entertainments seem to be theatrical 
<lb/>exhibitions or plays, varied with comic interludes.
<lb/>The women however conduct themselves with
<lb/>becoming grace and dignity.</p>
        </quote>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> Is it not wonderful that the <name>In­
<pb n="103"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="I4r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">103</mw>
<lb/>dians</name> should have such a variety of amusements,
<lb/>and that they should observe so much order, and 
<lb/>propriety in their entertainments?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> The beneficent Creator of the Uni­
<lb/>verse hath implanted in the human breast a love
<lb/>of order and a strong desire for happiness; and
<lb/>when this desire of enjoyment interferes not with
<lb/>the serious duties of life, these social meetings
<lb/>for entertainment harmonize the spirits, and are 
<lb/>productive of friendship and cordiality towards
<lb/>each other, and we thus testify our gratitude by
<lb/>enjoying with innocence and simplicity the gifts
<lb/>of heaven. No people in the state of nature are
<lb/>without harmless amusements; the natives of the
<lb/>new discovered Islands, in their public exhibi­
<lb/>tions, display great prowess and skill, accompa­
<lb/>nied with much order and regularity; the fa­
	  <lb/>mous navigator, <persName>Cook</persName>, says, their movements
<lb/>and dexterity, are much superior to what is
	  <lb/>found among <name>Europeans</name>. Dancing is common
<lb/>to all nations, and is by some consecrated, by
<lb/>devotional exercises, expressive of gratitude; it
	  <lb/>was so considered by the <name>Israelites</name> when they
<lb/>rejoiced before the Lord for their deliverance
	  <lb/>from the <name>Egyptians</name>, <quote>and <persName>Miriam</persName>, the prophet­
	    <lb/>ess, the sister of <persName>Aaron</persName>, took a timbrel in her
<lb/>hand, and all the women went out after her with
<pb n="104"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="I4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">104</mw>
	    <lb/>timbrels and with dances. And <persName>Miriam</persName> answered
<lb/>them, sing ye to the Lord, for he hath triumphed
<lb/>gloriously.</quote></p>
        <p>Our puritan ancestors denounced all amuse­
<lb/>ments, however innocent; their extreme scrupu­
<lb/>losity, in this respect, made them view with a 
<lb/>jealous and suspicious eye the joyous disposition
	  <lb/>of the <name>Indians</name>; and they were much disturbed
<lb/>and alarmed on being told, that some whom they
<lb/>had put in confinement, (from the apprehension
<lb/>that they might be induced to join their coun­
<lb/>trymen in defence of their rights,) had endea­
<lb/>voured to beguile the tedious days of their cap­
<lb/>tivity, by resorting to some of their wonted
<lb/>sports. A military guard was sent to silence
<lb/>and prevent them from dancing, or pleasing
<lb/>themselves with music, as such amusements
<lb/>were deemed to indicate a hostile intention,
<lb/>though these natives had ever manifested the
<lb/>most friendly feelings toward the settlers. The
<lb/>great attention given to things, wholly unimpor­
<lb/>tant in themselves, and having no connection
<lb/>with the doctrines or precepts of Christ, which
<lb/>they professed to follow, led our ancestors most
<lb/>frequently to neglect the weightier matters of
<lb/>the law. Some allowance should however be
<lb/>made for the austerity of the settlers, when we
<pb n="105"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="I5r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">105</mw>
<lb/>call to mind the disgust they had justly enter­
<lb/>tained for the revelry, and criminal indulgence,
<lb/>of the courtiers in the mother country, whose
<lb/>revenues were exhausted in furnishing entertain­
<lb/>ment for the sovereign and his parasites, which
<lb/>should have been employed in defence of the 
<lb/>kingdom, and in promoting the happiness of the 
<lb/>people.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> I hope, mother, you have more to
	  <lb/>tell us from <persName>Mr. Bartram</persName>; I should think that 
	  <lb/>those who read his accounts of the <name>Indians</name>,
<lb/>would be convinced how much we have wronged 
<lb/>them?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> It is difficult to convince those who
<lb/>have an interest in being deceived, and the pride
<lb/>of opinion operates very powerfully on common
	  <lb/>minds. <persName>Mr. Bartram</persName> describes very many towns,
<lb/>similar to those I have already related; one vil­
<lb/>lage in which they were received and entertain­
<lb/>ed, in somewhat different style is worth noticing.</p>
        <p><quote rend="post()">The chief of the village</quote> (says <persName>Bartram</persName>,)
<lb/><quote rend="pre()">conducted us to a grand airy pavilion in the
<lb/>centre. It was a square: a range of pillars
<lb/>or posts on each side supporting a canopy com­
<lb/>posed of palmetto leaves, woven or thatched to­
<lb/>gether, which shaded a level platform in the
<lb/>centre, that was ascended to from each side by
<pb n="106"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="I5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">106</mw>
<lb/>two steps or flights, each about twelve inches
<lb/>high, and seven or eight feet in breadth, all cov­
<lb/>ered with carpets or mats, curiously woven, of
<lb/>split canes dyed of various colours. Here being
<lb/>seated or reclining ourselves, after smoking to­
<lb/>bacco, baskets of the choisest fruits were brought
<lb/>and set before us.—The fields, surrounding the
<lb/>towns and groves, were plentifully stored with 
<lb/>corn, citrals, pumpkins, squashes, beans, peas,
<lb/>potatoes, peaches, figs, oranges, &amp;c.</quote></p>
        <p>
          <quote>The <name>Muscogulges</name> are said to be ingenious,
<lb/>sensible and virtuous men, bold and intrepid, yet
<lb/>quiet and peaceaable. They are supposed to be
<lb/>most ingenious and industrious husbandmen,
<lb/>having large plantations, or country farms, where
<lb/>they employ much of their time in agricultural
<lb/>improvements, after the manner of the white
<lb/>people; by which means their territories are
<lb/>more generally cultivated, and better inhabited,
<lb/>than any other Indian republic that we know of.
<lb/>It appeared to me, from observation, and what
	    <lb/>information I could get, that the <name>Indians</name> have 
<lb/>rational notions of the soul's immortality, and of
<lb/>a future state of social existence; and in order
<lb/>to inculcate morality, and promote human hap­
<lb/>piness, they applaud and praise worthy actions
<lb/>as commendable, and necessary for the support
<pb n="107"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="I6r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">107</mw>
<lb/>of civil society, and maintaining the dignity and 
<lb/>strength of their nation or tribe, as well as se­
<lb/>curing an excellent and tranquil state and de­
<lb/>gree in the world of spirits, after their decease.
<lb/>And they say the Great Spirit favours all good
<lb/>and brave men.</quote>
        </p>
        <p>Our brave author enumerates fifty-five towns, be­
<lb/>sides many villages, which constitute the power­
	  <lb/>ful confederacy of the <name>Creeks</name> or <name>Muscogulges</name>,
<lb/>surrounded by fertility and beauty.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> Are these the <name>Indians</name> who were 
	  <lb/>so inhumanly destroyed by <persName>Gen. Jackson</persName>?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> Multitudes of the <name>Seminoles</name> were
<lb/>slain by this general, on the pretext of their hav­
<lb/>ing committed some depredations, (though as in
<lb/>most instances we are not informed what pro­
	  <lb/>voked the aggression,) whilst these <name>Indians</name> were
	  <lb/>under the government of <placeName>Spain</placeName>, and included in
<lb/>their territory; and those who escaped slaughter
<lb/>were driven from their fertile fields and pleasant 
<lb/>homes, by an act of our government, to a sterile 
<lb/>part of the country, where numbers have misera­
<lb/>bly perished by famine, and the insalubrity of
<lb/>the climate, arising from the swampy, boggy
<lb/>land they have been compelled to occupy. Their 
<lb/>sufferings have been so great, that our govern­
<lb/>ment have been induced to furnish them with
<pb n="108"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="I6v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">108</mw>
<lb/>some present support to prevent them from per­
	  <lb/>ishing. Many of the <name>Creeks</name>, alarmed by the 
	  <lb/>fate of the <name>Seminoles</name>, endeavoured to prevent
<lb/>the ruin which threatened to overwhelm them,
	  <lb/>(as it was confidently affirmed, that <persName>Gen. Jack­
<lb/>son</persName> had avowed his intention to exterminate
<lb/>their whole nation,) and assembled in some of
<lb/>their towns, in a hostile attitude, when they
<lb/>were attacked and all destroyed, by this sangui­
<lb/>nary chieftan, as I have before related.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> Is this the <persName>Gen. Jackson</persName> who is pro­
<lb/>posed for our President?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> I cannot, without mingled feeliings
<lb/>of shame and indignation, confess even to you,
<lb/>that many among us desire to have this man to 
<lb/>rule over them.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> What reason can be given, mo­
<lb/>ther, for their preference of such a man?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> In most, it unquestionably springs
<lb/>from a desire to participate in the arbitrary and
<lb/>unjust rule, which they believe he will exercise
<lb/>over the better part of the community. These
<lb/>people are blinded (by avarice and ambition,) to
<lb/>their own interest, as well as to the honour and
<lb/>prosperity of their country. They have not im­
<lb/>bibed lessons of wisdom, from the appalling suf­
	  <lb/>ferings of the <name>French</name>, under their military des­
<pb n="109"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="K1r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">109</mw>
<lb/>pots and assassins; nor do they perceive the fa­
<lb/>cility afforded, under such sanguinary and un­
<lb/>principled rulers, for different parties to sup­
<lb/>plant and destroy each other.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> Was it not inconsistent with the jus­
<lb/>tice and honour of our government, to force
	  <lb/>these <name>Indians</name> to quit their native country, where
<lb/>they might have remained contented and happy,
<lb/>and drive them to a land sterile and unhealthful?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> It appears indeed wonderful that it
<lb/>should not have been deemed important, by our
<lb/>government, to protect the people whom we have
<lb/>so greatly injured, when so fair an opportunity
	  <lb/>was presented. Had the <name>Indians</name> been suffered
<lb/>to retain this portion of their territory, under the
	  <lb/>protection of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, they would have
<lb/>felt bound to defend it against an invading foe,
<lb/>and would have relieved them from the burthen
<lb/>of defending a part of the country so much ex­
<lb/>posed. Moreover, as it is acknowledged, that
<lb/>as no people are more susceptible of gratitude 
<lb/>than our natives, they would have become our
<lb/>firm friends and allies, had they received just
	  <lb/>and generous treatment from the <placeName>United States</placeName>,
<lb/>and would thus have greatly diminished the ex­
<lb/>penditures, which in war would be found essen­
	  <lb/>tial for its preservation. Could the <name>Indians</name> have
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">K</mw>
<pb n="110"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="K1v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">110</mw>
<lb/>relied with confidence on our government, it
<lb/>would have afforded an assylum for others, who
<lb/>have been obliged to quit their homes, and thus
<lb/>have relieved our country from the odium which
<lb/>is accumulating on us, by our treatment of this
<lb/>people. We might have expected this justice
	  <lb/>toward our <name>Indians</name>, as at the time when <placeName>Florida</placeName>
	  <lb/>was ceded to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, no claim to any
<lb/>part of it could be urged by any of the states;
<lb/>and had the natives of our country been allowed
<lb/>to retain the lands they occupied under the go­
	  <lb/>vernment of <placeName>Spain</placeName>, the difficulties which have
<lb/>arisen, in attempts to settle the country, would
<lb/>not have existed. We learn that <quote xml:id="a03" rend="pre(*)" corresp="#n03">the board of
	    <lb/>commissioners, in <placeName>East-Florida</placeName>, after a session
<lb/>of three years and a half, have transacted very
<lb/>little business; and what they have gone through,
<lb/>is said to be very imperfectly done. They have
	    <lb/>cost the <placeName>United States</placeName> about 70,000 dollars, be­
<lb/>ing far more than the lands are worth to the
<lb/>nation.</quote></p>
        <p>In addition to this, immense number of gross
<lb/>frauds are said to have been practised. This
<lb/>might have been expected from agents who are
<lb/>employed to perpetrate acts of violence and in­
<lb/>justice. I recollect to have read in a newspaper,
	  <lb/>published in <placeName>Tallahassee</placeName>, which is now the me­
<pb n="111"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="K2r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">111</mw>
	  <lb/>tropolis of <placeName>West-Florida</placeName>, the following article on
<lb/>the growth of American cities.</p>
        <p>
          <quote>It was in the month of <date when="1824-04"><name>April</name>, 1824</date>, that the
<lb/>first wagon was seen wending its devious way
	    <lb/>through that part of the wilds of <placeName>Florida</placeName>, which
<lb/>now constitutes the middle Judicial District;
<lb/>the sons of the forest were often arrested in pur­
<lb/>suit of their game, to gaze with wonder at the
<lb/>strange phenomenon; for there was not a being
<lb/>among them, within whose knowledge so strange
<lb/>a vehicle was ever seen to disturb the repose of
<lb/>their retirement; nor were they sensible that
<lb/>this was the day star which warned them to
<lb/>leave the land of their fathers, whose bones for
<lb/>centuries had mingled with the very soil from 
<lb/>which they raised their bread. The weary party
<lb/>at length arrived by the way of a gentle rise,
<lb/>upon the summit of a bold commanding emin­
<lb/>ence, at whose eastern and southern base, a
<lb/>beautiful rivulet meandered its course through a
<lb/>rich hammock. Our party was not long in se­
<lb/>lecting a camping ground, and pitching their
<lb/>tents about midway of the southern slope, which
<lb/>might well be taken for the land of the fairies:
<lb/>to the southward and westward, the country
<lb/>opened to their view like a magnificent park,
<lb/>gently undulated and studded with beautiful ba­
<pb n="112"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="K2v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">112</mw>
<lb/>sons of limpid water; at their feet a crystal
<lb/>fountain, gushing from the declivity of the hill;
<lb/>to the eastward, the view was more confined by
<lb/>the thick foliage of the undergrowth, which ser­
<lb/>ved to screen the view, though not the sound of
<lb/>a beautiful cascade, which was formed by the
<lb/>rivulet above described, falling over a ledge of
<lb/>rocks into a deep glen, which forms almost a 
<lb/>circle of about seventy yards in diameter, and
<lb/>didsappears at the bottom of the same ledge of
<lb/>rocks, very near the cascade. In the afternoon,
<lb/>our silvan party commenced building, and in two
<lb/>days were enabled to secure themselves from the
	    <lb/>weather, in the first house ever built in <placeName>Talla­
<lb/>hassee</placeName>. Many obstacles occured to prevent
<lb/>improvement for some time; among others, the
	    <lb/>great difficulty of removing the <name>Indians</name> from
<lb/>their country; so firmly were they attached to
<lb/>their native soil, that they would make the most
<lb/>frivolous excuses for procrastinating their depar­
<lb/>ture, and nothing but the peculiarly firm and re­
<lb/>solute, yet mild and persuasive measures, adopted 
<lb/>by the Executive, could have removed them
<lb/>without resorting to military force.</quote>
        </p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> Oh, mother, it makes me feel very
<lb/>sorrowful to hear of the sad reverses which the
	  <lb/><name>Indians</name> are forced to endure, obliged to leave a
<pb n="113"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="K3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">113</mw>
<lb/>land so delightful, and to which they were so
<lb/>strongly attached, and driven to one so sterile
<lb/>and unpleasant.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> No one, whose feelings have not 
<lb/>been paralyzed by selfish and sordid considera­
<lb/>tions, would have the affrontery to advocate a
<lb/>system so repugnant to mercy and justice. Yet
<lb/>a writer in the <title>American Quarterly Review</title>, to
<lb/>which I have before referred, censures the go­
	  <lb/>vernment for issuing rations to those <name>Indians</name>,
<lb/>who were so cruelly deprived of their territory,
<lb/>as, he affirms, they would sooner have been dri­
<lb/>ven into their reserve, where, he says, they might
<lb/>have found great numbers of small hummocks,
<lb/>good enough for their purposes, though it was of
	  <lb/>comparatively small value to the <placeName>United States</placeName>,
<lb/>as it would not be suitable for planters. In
	  <lb/>what way the <name>Indians</name> were to have subsisted,
<lb/>till they could have raised corn from these hum­
<lb/>mocks, he has not troubled himself to specify.
<lb/>This writer, in reviewing the works of those
	  <lb/>who have written on <placeName>Florida</placeName>, though he allows
<lb/>that some of them have given correct views of
	  <lb/>the country, and <quote>that the travels of <persName>William
<lb/>Bartram</persName> are especially deserving of attention, as
<lb/>they contain a great number of most interesting 
<lb/>facts and observations, and will always be refer­
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">K2</mw>
<pb n="114"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="K3v"/>
<lb/>red to as conveying a good general idea of the
<lb/>countries through which he passed,</quote> yet he
<lb/>boldly affirms, that the notice which some of
	  <lb/>them have taken of the <name>Indians</name> <quote>is mere ro­
<lb/>mance, than whom, he says, a more miserable
<lb/>and pitiable race can scarcely be imagined.</quote></p>
        <p>It appears somewhat unaccountable that so
<lb/>many good and intelligent men, who could have
<lb/>no interest in giving false impressions in regard
	  <lb/>to the <name>Indians</name>, should have so well agreed in
<lb/>their representations of these people, from the
<lb/>first settlement of the country to the present day,
<lb/>and it requires stronger evidence than mere as­
<lb/>sertion, to disprove the favourable accounts, so
<lb/>repeatedly given. We are then authorized to
<lb/>conclude that the author of this article, like
<lb/>many of the same class, has founded his opinion
	  <lb/>of the <name>Indians</name>, from the miserable vagrants who
<lb/>loiter about our settlements, having no abiding
<lb/>place, and who, wearied with contumely and op­
<lb/>pression, and unprovided with food or shelter,
<lb/>seek to drown their sorrows, and steep their
<lb/>senses in forgetfulness by intoxicating draughts.
<lb/>The false impressions which it appears the wri­
<lb/>ter of this article endeavours to produce, respect­
	  <lb/>ing the <name>Indians</name>, was doubtless meant to suppress
<lb/>all sympathy for this unfortunate race of men;
<pb n="115"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="K4r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">115</mw>
<lb/>but we must be convinced that little confidence
<lb/>can be had in one, who openly advocates the
<lb/>most oppressive and iniquitous measures. I
<lb/>quote the following sentence, with a view to con­
<lb/>firm the remarks I have made.</p>
        <p>
          <quote>It certainly appears preposterous to ask the
	    <lb/>consent of the <name>Indians</name>, after it is determined to
<lb/>force them into measures, how much soever they
<lb/>may object. As to the justice and honesty of
<lb/>the policy, that is a very different question. Un­
	    <lb/>der ordinary circumstanc<choice><sic>s</sic><corr>e</corr></choice>s, it would be consid­
<lb/>ered ridiculous to enquire whether a company
<lb/>or an individual might not be forced to dispose
<lb/>of goods, provided a stonger party chose to pur­
<lb/>chase, or desired to possess them. But history
<lb/>and experience teach us that in relation to the
	    <lb/><name>Indians</name>, <quote rend="pre(‘)post(’)">we have changed all that.</quote></quote>
        </p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> Then in conformity with these senti­
<lb/>ments, we may dispense with what is just and
<lb/>honest, in our dealings with those who are una­
<lb/>ble to resist us.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> This is the only construction which
<lb/>can be made consistently with the general cur­
<lb/>rent of his arguments, we are bound to do jus­
<lb/>tice toward those only whom we fear to offend,
<lb/>least they should make reprisals and punish us
<lb/>for our guilty deeds; sentiments like these, level
<pb n="116"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="K4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">116</mw>
<lb/>man with the brute creation, for such as advo­
<lb/>cate them can have no rational belief in a just
<lb/>and perfect Being, who has commanded us, <quote>to
<lb/>do justice and love mercy.</quote> I extremely regret
<lb/>that a review of transactions so base, accompa­
<lb/>nied with arguments so devoid of integrity and
<lb/>benevolence, qualities essential to the dignity of
<lb/>human nature, and which can alone exalt man
<lb/>in the scale of being, should have been permitted
<lb/>to stain the pages of a Journal, by which its
<lb/>general merit must be worthy the attention, not
<lb/>only of our own citizens, but of foreign nations:
<lb/>who will thus be incited to scoff at our boasted
<lb/>institutions, and declarations of the liberty and
<lb/>protection, afforded by our government to all
<lb/>men, whom we have solemnly pronounced to be
<lb/>by nature free and equal.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> I trust that no other person has 
<lb/>written in this style, mother?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> Not exactly in the same spirit, 
<lb/>though many have attempted to excuse or ex­
	  <lb/>tenuate our treatment of the <name>Indians</name>. A writer
<lb/>in the <title>North American</title>, in reviewing the histo­
	  <lb/>ries and notices of the <name>North American Indians</name>,
<lb/>whose main design is to exonerate his country­
<lb/>men from the odium which rests upon them for 
	  <lb/>their exterminating warfare against the <name>Abori­
<pb n="117"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="K5r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">117</mw>
<lb/>gines</name>, has endeavoured to discredit those writers,
<lb/>who have given the most favourable accounts of
<lb/>them, and is moreover anxious to prove that they
<lb/>have overrated the amount of the Aboriginal
<lb/>population at the era of the discovery of this
<lb/>country. With this view he disregards the ac­
<lb/>counts, given by worthy and intelligent men,
<lb/>who by early and familiar intercourse with the
<lb/>natives, were well qualified to give correct state­
<lb/>ments of their habits and situation, and contends,
	  <lb/><quote>that their own ceaseless hostilities, more than
<lb/>any other cause, has led to their melancholy de­
<lb/>population.</quote> Had this writer given any atten­
<lb/>tion to the well authenticated histories of our
<lb/>early warfare with the natives, he would not 
<lb/>have asserted, that the statements made upon
<lb/>this subject were made in a spirit of exaggera­
<lb/>tion. Had he learnt, that multitudes of hap­
<lb/>less victims were perpetually sacrificed to in­
<lb/>terest and ambition, during a protracted and
<lb/>merciless war, and that in the space of forty
<lb/>years, three important kingdoms were subverted,
<lb/>and the inhabitants were all destroyed, or trans­
<lb/>ported and sold for slaves in a foreign clime, in
<lb/>addition to some smaller tribes, all in this vicini­
<lb/>ty; or had he <choice><sic>h</sic><corr>m</corr></choice>ade any estimate of the numbers
	  <lb/>who dwelt on the shores of the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName>, within our
<pb n="118"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="K5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">118</mw>
<lb/>present domain, who, within a short time, were
<lb/>forcibly swept from the face of the earth, he would
<lb/>not have ventured to impose on his readers con­
<lb/>clusions, hastily made from present appearances
<lb/>and casual observations. To corroborate the
<lb/>facts here given, no place is selected, either for
<lb/>the establishment of cities, towns or villages,
	  <lb/>but what was previously occupied by the <name>Indians</name>, 
<lb/>who have left numerous memorials of themselves
<lb/>in every part of the country. In the same spirit,
<lb/>the reviewer endeavours to destroy our confi­
<lb/>dence in those, who influenced by humane and
	  <lb/>generous sympathy for the sufferings of our <name>Abo­
<lb/>rigines</name>, have endeavoured to mollify the preju­
<lb/>dices, unjustly fostered against them, by dis­
<lb/>playing their noble and good qualities, and re­
<lb/>presenting the injurious treatment to which they
<lb/>are subjected; though truth compels him to con­
<lb/>fess, that many fine traits of character have ar­
<lb/>rested his attention, and engaged his admiration;
<lb/>and notwithstanding the sarcasm he has levelled
	  <lb/>against the admirers of the <name>Indian language</name>, his
<lb/>own convictions appear to have the same results,
	  <lb/>as he owns that, <quote>what has been called the
<lb/>richness of their grammatical forms,</quote> cannot be
<lb/>accounted for, but by supposing them to be
	  <lb/><quote>the wrecks of more polished tongues, acquired
<pb n="119"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="K6r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">119</mw>
<lb/>in far different circumstances, and almost lost in
<lb/>the lapse of ages.</quote> Nevertheless, though this re­
<lb/>viewer has sacrificed much in support of his
<lb/>theory, he has not been insensible to the feelings
<lb/>of compassion, nor deaf to the voice of con­
<lb/>science, and I quote with pleasure some of the
<lb/>sentiments with which he has closed his discus­
<lb/>sion.</p>
        <quote rend="bestow((pre(“))(p))">
          <p>But after all, neither the government nor
	    <lb/>the people of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, have any wish
<lb/>to conceal from themselves, nor from the world,
<lb/>that there is upon their frontiers a wretched and
<lb/>forlorn people, looking to them for support and
<lb/>protection, and possessing strong claims upon
<lb/>their justice and humanity. These people re­
<lb/>ceived our forefathers in a spirit of friendship,
<lb/>aided them to endure privations and sufferings,
<lb/>and taught them how to provide for many of the
<lb/>wants with which they were surrounded. The
	    <lb/><name>Indians</name> were then strong, and we were weak;
<lb/>and without looking at the change which has
<lb/>occurred in any spirit of morbid affectation, but
<lb/>with the feelings of an age accustomed to ob­
<lb/>serve great mutations in the fortunes of nations
<lb/>and of individuals, we may express our regret,
<lb/>that they have lost so much of what we have 
<lb/>gained. The prominent points of their history
<pb n="120"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="K6v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">120</mw>
<lb/>are before the world, and will go down unchan­
<lb/>ged to posterity. In the revolution of a few ages,
<lb/>this fair portion of the continent, which was
<lb/>theirs, has passed into our possession. The fo­
<lb/>rests, which afforded them food and security,
<lb/>where were their cradles, their homes, and their
<lb/>graves, have disappeared or are disappearing, be­
<lb/>fore the progress of civilization.</p>
          <p>We have extinguished their council fires,
<lb/>and ploughed up the bones of their fathers.
<lb/>Their population has diminished with lamenta­
<lb/>ble rapidity. Those tribes that remain, like the
<lb/>lone column of a fallen temple, exhibit but the
<lb/>sad relics of their former strength; and many
<lb/>others live only in the names which have reach­
<lb/>ed us through the earlier accounts of travellers
<lb/>and historians. The causes which have produc­
<lb/>ed this moral desolation, are yet in constant and
<lb/>active operation, and threaten to leave us, at no
<lb/>distant day, without a living proof of Indian suf­
	    <lb/>fering, from the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName> to the immense desert, 
	    <lb/>which sweeps along the base of the <placeName>Rocky Moun­
<lb/>tains</placeName>. Nor can we console ourselves with the
<lb/>reflection, that their physical declension has been
<lb/>counter-ballanced, by any melioration in their
<lb/>moral condition. We have taught them neither
<lb/>how to live, nor how to die.</p>
        </quote>
        <pb n="121"/>
        <milestone unit="sig" n="L1r"/>
        <mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">121</mw>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> I am pleased to find the reviewer ex­
<lb/>presses so much sensibility for the sufferings of
	  <lb/>the <name>Indians</name>, and that he acknowledges the strong
<lb/>claims they possess upon our justice and huma­
<lb/>nity; but it is strange, I think, that he should
<lb/>insist, that their own hostilities, more than any
<lb/>other cause, has led to their depopulation, when
<lb/>he tells us, that we have deprived them of their
<lb/>lands and their forests, so essential to their ex­
<lb/>istence, and have introduced so much evil and
<lb/>disorder among them.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> We all know that the <name>Indians</name> are
<lb/>frequently engaged in bloody conflicts with each
<lb/>other, though it would, in my apprehension, be
<lb/>difficult to prove that they are more disposed to
<lb/>war than other nations. I cannot recollect a
<lb/>period of any duration, when hostilities have
	  <lb/>ceased among the potentates of <placeName>Europe</placeName>, and dur­
	  <lb/>ing the revolution in <placeName>France</placeName>, torrents of blood
<lb/>were shed, both in the field and on the scaffold
<lb/>and whilst that unfortunate country was under 
	  <lb/>the dominion of <persName>Bonaparte</persName>, millions were sacri­
<lb/>ficed to gratify the insatiable ambition of this
	  <lb/>usurper. <placeName>France</placeName> at this period exhibited a
<lb/>scene of desolation truly appalling, and it seemed
<lb/>to distant observers that ages would be required
<lb/>to restore its population; nevertheless, we are as­
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">L</mw>
<pb n="122"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="L1v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">122</mw>
<lb/>sured that her numbers have since greatly in­
<lb/>creased.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> You recollect, <persName>Elizabeth</persName>, that Mr.
	  <lb/>―― told us, the other day, that the <name>Creeks</name> de­
<lb/>served to loose their land, because they had ob­
<lb/>tained it by conquest.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> However the <name>Creeks</name> may merit pun­
<lb/>ishment, it does not become us to be their aven­
<lb/>gers, unless we be prepared to submit in our
<lb/>turn to retributive justice; you would not, my
<lb/>dear girls, deem one guiltless who took and con­
<lb/>verted to his own use what had been unjustly
<lb/>obtained by another; I do not however admit
<lb/>that any excuse can be given for a people, who
<lb/>forcibly wrest from its native possessors the ter­
<lb/>ritory bestowed upon them by the beneficent 
<lb/>Parent of the Universe, unless indeed we may
<lb/>believe they had themselves been compelled to
<lb/>yield their country to a nation more powerful
<lb/>and could obtain otherwise no abiding place;
	  <lb/>yet as these <name>Indians</name>, after their conquest, incor­
<lb/>porated the people whom they had subdued with
<lb/>themselves, it is assuredly no small extenuation
<lb/>of their guilt.</p>
        <p><persName>Mr. Bartram</persName> describes many wonderful re­
<lb/>mains, which attest the ingenuity and improve­
<lb/>ment of the native or former possessors. Not
<pb n="123"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="L2r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">123</mw>
	  <lb/>far from <placeName>Little River</placeName>, a branch of the <placeName>Savanna</placeName>,
<lb/>in a beautiful situation, from an eminence over­
<lb/>looking the low grounds of the river, we disco­
<lb/>vered, says he—</p>
        <p>
          <quote>Many very magnificent monuments of the 
<lb/>power and industry of the ancient inhabitants of
<lb/>these lands. I observed a stupendous conical
<lb/>pyramid, or artificial mound of earth, vast tetra­
<lb/>gon terraces, and a large sunken area, of a cu­
<lb/>bical form, encompassed with banks of earth;
<lb/>and certain traces of a larger Indian town, the
<lb/>work of a powerful nation, whose period of gran­
<lb/>deur perhaps long preceded the discovery of the
<lb/>continent.</quote>
        </p>
        <p>
          <quote rend="post()">I made a little excursion up the <placeName>Savanna
	      <lb/>river</placeName>, four or five miles above <name>fort James</name>, with
<lb/>the surgeon of the garrison, who was so polite
<lb/>as to attend me to show me some remarkable
<lb/>Indian monuments, which are worthy of every
<lb/>traveller's notice. These wonderful labors of 
<lb/>the ancients stand in a level plain, very near the
<lb/>banks of the river. They consist of conical
<lb/>mounts of earth, and four square terraces, &amp;c.
<lb/>The great mount is in the form of a cone, about
<lb/>forty or fifty feet high, and the circumference of
<lb/>its base two or three hundred yards, entirely
<lb/>composed of the loamy rich earth of the low
<pb n="124"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="L2v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">124</mw>
<lb/>grounds; the top or apex is flat; a spiral path
<lb/>or track leading from the low grounds to the top
<lb/>is still visible, where now grows a large and 
<lb/>beautiful spreading red cedar: there appears
<lb/>four niches excavated out of the sides of this
<lb/>mount, at different heights from the base, front­
<lb/>ing the four cardinal points; these niches are
<lb/>entered into town from the winding path, and seem to 
<lb/>have been meant for the resting places or look outs.
<lb/>The circumjacent level grounds are now cleared
<lb/>and planted with Indian corn; and I think the
<lb/>proprietor of these lands, who accompanied us
<lb/>to this place, said, that the mount itself yielded 
<lb/>above one hundred bushels in one season: the
<lb/>land hereabouts is indeed exceeding fertile and 
<lb/>productive. Some imagine these tumuli were
<lb/>constructed for look-out towers. It is reasona­
<lb/>ble to suppose, however, that they were to serve
<lb/>some important purpose, as they were public
<lb/>works, and would have required the united la­
<lb/>bour and attention of a whole nation, circum­
<lb/>stanced as they were, to have constructed one of
<lb/>them almost in an age. There are several small­
<lb/>er ones, round about the great one, with some
<lb/>very large tetragon terraces, on each side, near
<lb/>one hundred yards in length, and their surface,
<pb n="125"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="L3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">125</mw>
<lb/>four, six, eight and ten feet above the ground on
<lb/>which they stand.</quote>
        </p>
        <p>In another place the author speaks of having 
<lb/><quote>enjoyed a most enchanting prospect of the
	    <lb/>great <placeName>Lake George</placeName>. At about fifty yards dis­
<lb/>tance from the landing place stands a magnifi­
<lb/>cent Indian mount. About fifteen years ago I
<lb/>visited this place, at which time there were no
<lb/>settlements of white people, but all appeared wild 
<lb/>and savage; yet in that uncultivated state it
<lb/>possessed an almost inexpressible air of gran­
<lb/>deur, which was now entirely changed. At that
<lb/>time there was a very considerable extent of old
<lb/>fields round about the mount; there was also a
<lb/>large orange grove, together with palms and live
<lb/>oaks, extending from near the mount, along the
<lb/>banks downwards; all of which has been since 
<lb/>cleared away to make room for planting ground.
<lb/>But what greatly contributed towards complet­
<lb/>ing the magnificence of the scene, was a noble
<lb/>Indian highway, which led from the great mount
<lb/>on a straight line, three quarters of a mile, first
<lb/>through a point or wing of the orange grove, and
<lb/>continuing through a stately forest of live oaks,
<lb/>it was terminated by palms and laurel magnolias,
<lb/>on the verge of an oblong artificial lake, which
<lb/>was on the edge of an extensive green level sa­
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">L2</mw>
<pb n="126"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="L3v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">126</mw>
<lb/>vanna. This grand highway was about fifty
<lb/>yards wide, sunk a little below the common
<lb/>level, and the earth thrown up on each side,
<lb/>making  a bank of about two feet high. Neither
<lb/>nature nor art could any where present a more
<lb/>striking contrast, as you approached this savanna.
<lb/>The glittering water pond played on the sight
<lb/>through the dark grove like a brilliant diamond,
<lb/>on the bosom of the illuminated savanna, bordered
<lb/>with various flowery shrubs and plants; and as
<lb/>we advanced into the plain the sight was agreea­
<lb/>bly relieved by a distant view of the forest, which
<lb/>partly environed the green expanse on the left
<lb/>hand, whilst the imagination was still flattered and
<lb/>entertained by the distant misty points of the sur­
<lb/>rounding forests, which projected into the plain,
<lb/>alternately appearing and disappearing, making
<lb/>a grand sweep round on the right, to the distant
<lb/>banks of the great lake. All has been cleared 
<lb/>away and planted with indigo, corn and cotton,
<lb/>but since deserted; there was now scarcely five
<lb/>acres of ground under fence. It appeared like
<lb/>a desert to a great extent, and terminated on the
<lb/>land side, by frightful thickets, and open pine
<lb/>forests. It appears, however, that the late pro­
<lb/>prietor had some taste, as he has preserved the
<pb n="127"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="L4r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">127</mw>
<lb/>mount, and the little adjoining grove inviolate.
<lb/>The prospect from this station comprises at one
<lb/>view the whole of the sublime and pleasing.</quote></p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> How much taste and power these
<lb/>people must have possessed, and the little atten­
<lb/>tion which has been given to the preservation
<lb/>of these ancient structures, reminds one of the
	  <lb/>destruction of the noble edifices of <placeName>Rome</placeName> by the
	  <lb/><name>Goths</name> and <name>Vandals</name>.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> These northern invaders were in­
<lb/>fluenced by their contempt of the Roman people,
<lb/>who at the period of their final conquest were in
<lb/>the lowest state of national degeneracy. We
	  <lb/>learn from the history of modern <placeName>Europe</placeName>, that</p>
        <p>
          <quote>Many of the northern leaders were men of
<lb/>great abilities, and several of them were ac­
<lb/>quainted both with the policy and literature of 
	    <lb/>the <name>Romans</name>; but they were justly afraid of the
<lb/>contagious influence of Roman example; and
<lb/>therefore avoided every thing allied to that name,
<lb/>whether hurtful or otherwise. They erected a
<lb/>cottage in the neighbourhood of a palace, break­
<lb/>ing down the stately building, and burying in its
<lb/>ruins the finest works of human invention; they
<lb/>ate out of vessels of wood, and made the van­
<lb/>quished to be served in vessels of silver; they
<lb/>hunted the boar on the voluptuous parterre, the
<pb n="128"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="L4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">128</mw>
<lb/>trim garden, and expensive pleasure-ground,
<lb/>where effeminacy was wont to saunter, or indo­
<lb/>lence to loll; and they pastured their herds
<lb/>where they might have raised a luxurious har­
<lb/>vest.</quote>
        </p>
        <p>Now I cannot admit that the vices of our <name>In­
<lb/>dians</name> was the cause of their being treated with 
<lb/>injustice or contempt, as history has faithfully
<lb/>recorded their noble qualities; avarice has been
<lb/>the fatal source of our criminal disregard of their
<lb/>rights, and has also induced us to destroy those
<lb/>monuments which attest the power and ingenu­
	  <lb/>ity of the people who erected them. Our <name>Abo­
<lb/>rigines</name> resembled in many respects the barba­
<lb/>rians, as they were called, who subverted the 
	  <lb/>empire of the <name>Romans</name>, they were, like them,
	  <lb/><quote>simple in their manners, and unacquainted
<lb/>with the word luxury—though free and inde­
<lb/>pendent, they were firmly attached to their lead­
<lb/>ers, because they followed them from choice, not
<lb/>from constraint, the most gallant being always
<lb/>dignified with the command—Nor were these
<lb/>their only virtues—They were remarkable for
<lb/>their generous hospitality; for their detestation
<lb/>of treachery, and falsehood: they possessed
<lb/>many maxims of civil wisdom, and wanted only
<pb n="129"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="L5r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">129</mw>
<lb/>the culture of reason to conduct them to the true
<lb/>principles of social life.</quote></p>
        <p>These primitive virtues are found to prevail
<lb/>among every nation, who have not departed much
<lb/>from the original state in which they were placed
	  <lb/>by nature; yet we have stigmatised our <name>Indians</name>,
<lb/>as ignorant and barbarous, and incapable of civi­
<lb/>lizaton, because they refused to substitute for
<lb/>their own pure and rational religion, the dis­
<lb/>cordant and profane dogmas of their conquerors,
<lb/>or be willing to submit to their tyranny and
<lb/>usurpation.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> But must not those who raised
<lb/>these interesting monuments, have possessed
<lb/>more skill and better implements, than the pre­
	  <lb/>sent <name>Aborigines</name>?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> <persName>Bartram</persName> gives it as his opinion, that
<lb/>none of them he has seen, discover the least
<lb/>sign of the arts, sciences, or architecture of the
	  <lb/><name>Europeans</name>, or other inhabitants of the old world,
<lb/>yet evidently betray every sign or mark of the
<lb/>most distant antiquity. Nevertheless, we are 
<lb/>told that—</p>
        <p>
          <quote>When the <name>Spaniards</name> entered the city of 
	    <lb/><placeName>Mexico</placeName>, the natives were refined in their man­
<lb/>ners, intelligent, and in some degree learned.
	    <lb/>Like the ancient <name>Egyptians</name>, they knew with pre­
<pb n="130"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="L5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">130</mw>
<lb/>cision the annual revolution of the sun; they
<lb/>fixed the year at three hundred and sixty-five
<lb/>days, nearly, and divided it into eighteen parts.
<lb/>Their constitution was founded on the broad
<lb/>basis of religion and law. Their cities display­
<lb/>ed magnificence in architecture, and opulence
	    <lb/>in their decorations. The palace of <persName>Montezu­
<lb/>ma</persName> had thirty gates, which communicated with
<lb/>as many streets. The front was composed of
<lb/>red, black and white stone, beautifully polished;
<lb/>and in a large shield over the gate were repre­
	    <lb/>sented the arms of <persName>Montezuma</persName>—a Griffin with
<lb/>expanded wings, holding a Tyger in its talons.</quote>
        </p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> These mounts appear to resemble
	  <lb/>the pyramids of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> in their exterior form,
<lb/>perhaps they were erected with the same design.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> All nations have testified a desire
<lb/>to honour the Supreme Ruler of the Universe,
<lb/>by raising stately edifices consecrated to His
<lb/>service. The Egyptian pyramids were doubt­
<lb/>less intended for places of worship, where men
<lb/>would be perpetually reminded of the power,
<lb/>wisdom, and goodness of the most High, by a
<lb/>nearer view of the starry heavens, which were 
<lb/>seen in all their grandeur and beauty through a
	  <lb/>serene and pure atmosphere; hence the <name>Egyp­
<lb/>tians</name> obtained a knowledge of the periods and
<pb n="131"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="L6r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">131</mw>
<lb/>revolutions of the heavenly bodies, which made
<lb/>them to be renowned for their wisdom. Here
<lb/>too they doubtless deposited the remains of their
<lb/>illustrious dead, and they were thus associated
<lb/>with all that was most dear and sacred. The
	  <lb/><name>Indians</name> who constructed works of such magni­
<lb/>tude and regularity, must unquestionably have
<lb/>possessed no inconsiderable knowledge of mathe­
<lb/>matical science; mounts, such as have been des­
<lb/>cribed, afforded them facilities for observing the
<lb/>rising and setting of the planets, by which they 
<lb/>measured time; and the beauty and sublimity of 
<lb/>these objects, would naturally raise and elevate
<lb/>their ideas of that Being, whom they venerated
<lb/>and adored. These impressions would lead
<lb/>them to deposit the ashes of their departed
<lb/>friends, in places rendered so sacred and vener­
<lb/>able. That these mounts were designed in part
<lb/>for mausoleums cannot be doubted, as we learn 
<lb/>that human bones, and skeletons entire, have 
<lb/>been discovered in some of them, accompanied
<lb/>with emblems of respect and affection.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> As the <name>Mexicans</name> were so ingenious,
<lb/>and so polished and improved, why may not the
<lb/>people who constructed these works have come
	  <lb/>from the vicinity of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, and brought with
<lb/>them some knowledge of their arts?</p>
        <pb n="132"/>
        <milestone unit="sig" n="L6v"/>
        <mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">132</mw>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> This is I think the most natural
<lb/>supposition, especially as we learn they are found
<lb/>in certain districts, and do not appear to have
<lb/>been common with all the inhabitants. Our au­
<lb/>thor says,</p>
        <p><quote>About seventy or eighty miles above the
	    <lb/>confluence of the <placeName>Oakmulge</placeName> and <placeName>Ocone rivers</placeName>,
	    <lb/>the trading path, from <placeName>Augusta</placeName> to the <name>Creek na­
<lb/>tion</name>, crosses these fine rivers which are there
<lb/>forty miles apart. On the east banks of the
	    <lb/><placeName>Oakmulge</placeName> this trading road runs nearly two
<lb/>miles through ancient Indian fields, which are
	    <lb/>called the <placeName>Oakmulge fields</placeName>: they are the rich
<lb/>low lands of the river. On the heights of these
<lb/>low grounds are yet visible monuments, or traces
<lb/>of an ancient town, such as artificial mounts or
<lb/>terraces, squares and banks, encircling consid­
<lb/>erable areas. Their old fields and planting land 
<lb/>extend up and down the river, fifteen or twenty
<lb/>miles from this site.</quote>—In concluding this sub­
	  <lb/>ject, <persName>Bartram</persName> says,</p>
        <quote rend="bestow( (pre(“)post(”)) (p) )">
          <p>The pyramidal or artificial mounts, and
<lb/>highways, or avenues, leading from them to arti­
<lb/>ficial lakes, or ponds, vast tetragon terraces,
<lb/>church yards, (a term given by the white traders,
<lb/>to the oblong square yards, adjoining the 
	    <lb/>high mounts, and rotundas of the modern <name>In­
<pb n="133"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="M1r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">133</mw>
<lb/>dians</name> and obelisks or pillars of wood, are the
<lb/>only monuments of labour, ingenuity and mag­
<lb/>nificence, that I have seen worthy of notice.</p>
          <p>The region lying between <placeName>Savanna river</placeName>,
	    <lb/>and <placeName>Oakmulge</placeName>, East and West, and from the
	    <lb/>sea coast to the <placeName>Cherokee</placeName> or <placeName>Apalachean moun­
<lb/>tain</placeName>, North and South, is the most remarkable
<lb/>for these high conical hills, tetragon terraces,
<lb/>and church yards. This region was possessed
	    <lb/>by the <name>Cherokees</name> since the arrival of <name>Europeans</name>,
<lb/>but they were afterwards dispossessed by the 
	    <lb/><name>Muscogulges</name>, and all that country was, probably
<lb/>many ages preceding the Cherokee invasion, in­
<lb/>habited by one nation or confederacy, who were
<lb/>ruled by one system of laws, but so ancient that
	    <lb/>the <name>Cherokees</name>, <name>Creeks</name>, or the nations they con­
<lb/>quered, could render no account for what pur­
<lb/>pose these monuments were raised. The mounts 
<lb/>or cubical yards adjoining them, seem to have 
<lb/>been raised in part for ornament and recreation,
<lb/>and likewise to serve some other public purpose
<lb/>since they were always so situated as to com­
<lb/>mand the most extensive prospects over the
<lb/>town and country adjacent. The tetragon ter­
<lb/>races seem to be the foundation of a fortress;
<lb/>and perhaps the great pyramidal mounts, served
<lb/>for the purpose of lookout towers, and high places
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">M</mw>
<pb n="134"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="M1v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">134</mw>
<lb/>for sacrifices. The sunken areas adjoining the
<lb/>mounts are surrounded by a bank, and some­
<lb/>times two of them, one behind and above another
<lb/>and served as seats.</p>
          <p>From the river <placeName>St. Juan's</placeName>, southerly, to the
	    <lb/>point of the peninsula of <placeName>Florida</placeName>, are to be seen
<lb/>high pyramidal mounts, with spacious and exten­
<lb/>sive avenues, leading from them out of the town,
<lb/>to an artificial lake or pond of water; these were
<lb/>evidently designed in part for ornament or mon­
<lb/>uments of magnificence, to perpetuate the power
<lb/>and grandeur of the nation, and not inconsidera­
<lb/>ble neither, for they exhibit scenes of power and 
<lb/>grandeur, and must have been public edifices.</p>
        </quote>
        <p>Many other mounts, highways, and artificial 
	  <lb/>lakes up <placeName>St. Juan's</placeName> on the east shore, are men­
<lb/>tioned by our author; but as they all have a
<lb/>strong resemblance to those already noticed, a
<lb/>farther description is unnecessary; but there is
<lb/>every indication that they were all designed for
<lb/>the purposes I have before suggested. It was
<lb/>common with the people of old to choose the 
<lb/>high places of the earth, to offer up their praise
<lb/>and adoration to that exalted Being, to whom
<lb/>they owed their life, and health, and every other
<lb/>blessing; and by being thus elevated above
<lb/>earthly objects, they doubtless facied them­
<pb n="135"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="M2r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">135</mw>
<lb/>selves more immediately in His presence. When
	  <lb/><persName>Moses</persName> ascended <placeName>mount Sinai</placeName>, to hold communion
<lb/>with God, he gave strict command to the people
<lb/>to remain below, and set bounds about the
<lb/>mount lest they should break through; in this,
	  <lb/><persName>Moses</persName> unquestionably followed the example of
	  <lb/>the priests of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, whose mystical rites were
<lb/>veiled from all but the initiated. We learn that
	  <lb/><persName>Moses</persName> was skilled in all the wisdom of the <name>Egyp­
<lb/>tians</name>, and he was of course aware, that the na­
<lb/>tural phenomena exhibited in these elevated re­
<lb/>gions, were calculated to inspire the multitude
	  <lb/>with awe and veneration. The <persName>Rev. Mr. Heck­
	    <lb/>ewelder</persName> says, <quote>An old <name>Indian</name> told me, about fifty
<lb/>years ago, that when he was young he still follow­
<lb/>ed the custom of his fathers and ancestors, of
<lb/>climbing upon a high mountain to thank the
<lb/>Great Spirit, for His benefits bestowed, and to
<lb/>entreat a continuance of His favour; and that
<lb/>they were sure that their prayers were heard,
<lb/>and acceptable to the Great Spirit, though he
<lb/>did not himself appear to them.</quote> In plains
<lb/>where no high hills were found, artificial mounts,
<lb/>such as have been described, were designed 
	  <lb/>principally, as were the pyramids of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, for
<lb/>places of worship, and the sunken areas contigu­
<lb/>ous to the mounts, were unquestionably intended
<pb n="136"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="M2v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">136</mw>
<lb/>for the worshippers below. Judging from the 
<lb/>natural propensities of the human race, this is
<lb/>in my opinion the most rational conclusion, and 
<lb/>as these mounts are always continguous to rivers
<lb/>and lakes, it is a strong confirmation of their
<lb/>having been consecrated to the worship of the
<lb/>most High; the pecul<choice><sic/><corr>i</corr></choice>ar efficacy of water, has
<lb/>ever engaged the veneration and gratitude of 
<lb/>mankind.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> I do not wonder that mountains
<lb/>should have been chosen and consecrated to the
<lb/>worship of God, as the delightful serenity and
<lb/>purity of the air would inspire devotional feelings,
<lb/>but I did not imagine that this practise was com­
	  <lb/>mon to our <name>Aborigines</name>?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> It cannot I think be doubted, that
	  <lb/>the religion of our <name>Aborigines</name> was less contami­
<lb/>nated by superstition, and they had deviated less
<lb/>from those innate impressions, which are written
<lb/>in divine characters on the heart, than any other
<lb/>people. Their disposition to war, and cruel
<lb/>treatment of those captives who are doomed to
<lb/>die, appears to be the only criminal deviations
<lb/>from the great law of kindness, which constitutes
<lb/>the basis of true religion; yet it is no small ex­
<lb/>tenuation of their guilt, that no inspired teacher
<lb/>has been sent to them with messages of grace, to
<pb n="137"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="M3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">137</mw>
<lb/>renew and improve those innate convictions, so
<lb/>graciously bestowed by the beneficent Parent of
<lb/>the Universe, to guide us in the way of truth,
<lb/>that by this divine light we might be able to per­
<lb/>ceive and embrace all that is right, and good,
<lb/>and congenial to these impressions.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> Have the <name>Indians</name> never been in­
	  <lb/>structed in the divine precepts of <name>Christianity</name>?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> The orthodox have sent many Mis­
	  <lb/>sionaries among the <name>Indians</name> of our country, and
	  <lb/>much praise is due to the <persName>Rev. Cyrus Kingsbury</persName>, 
<lb/>who has devoted himself with the most disinter­
<lb/>ested zeal to convert and improve our western
	  <lb/><name>Aborigines</name>, and his labours have been crowned
<lb/>with more than common success, notwithstand­
<lb/>ing the disgust and aversion manifested by our
	  <lb/><name>Indians</name> in general, for the discordant and irrev­
	  <lb/>erent dogmas of <name>Calvinism</name>, which are made
<lb/>still more offensive by the bigotry and intoler­
<lb/>ance of common missionaries. The main in­
<lb/>ducement of most of those who are employed in
<lb/>this service, is to receive a competent support,
<lb/>unincumbered by labour or anxiety, and of course
<lb/>they have little interest in the welfare of the peop­
<lb/>ple to whom they are sent. Missionaries of this
<lb/>class are incapable of liberal and comprehensive
<lb/>views on subjects of religion and morals, as they
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">M2</mw>
<pb n="138"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="M3v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">138</mw>
<lb/>have enjoyed few advantages in early life, being
<lb/>in most instances taken from laborious occupa­
<lb/>tions, for the express purpose of propagating
<lb/>among the Heathen, incomprehensible doctrines
<lb/>and formulas, which though they do not under­
<lb/>stand, they are pledged to support and defend.
<lb/>These have confirmed the bad impressions which
	  <lb/>the <name>Indians</name> have received of <name>Christianity</name>, by the
<lb/>unjust and cruel treatment they have experi­
<lb/>enced, from a people who bear this sacred name.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> But why do not <name>Unitarians</name> send Mis­
	  <lb/>sionaries to our <name>Indians</name>, mother?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> I have before remarked to you
<lb/>the coldness and indifference which prevails in
<lb/>regard to this people; yet it appears to me to be
<lb/>an imperative and indispensible duty, that the
<lb/>ministers of Christ should exert the most strenu­
<lb/>ous endeavours to create an interest in the peop­
<lb/>ple, to rescue, and save from utter ruin, the rem­
<lb/>nant of this persecuted race. But how can pure
	  <lb/><name>Christianity</name> be inculcated, and its benign influ­
<lb/>ence pervade the heart, where no interest is felt
<lb/>in freeing the oppressed people, from whom we
<lb/>have wrested this goodly land. Nevertheless, I
<lb/>rejoice to find that all are not thus indifferent;
<lb/>but that many intelligent men have just and
<lb/>comprehensive views on this subject, in all its
<pb n="139"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="M4r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">139</mw>
<lb/>bearings. Uninfluenced by the contracted and
<lb/>selfish policy of narrow minded, unprincipled
	  <lb/>men, they earnestly insist that the <name>Indians</name> should
<lb/>be secured and protected, and allowed to possess
<lb/>in peace their lands, and that those who have
<lb/>been deprived of their possessions should have
<lb/>lands assigned them, where they will be freed
<lb/>from injury and intrusion, and that this should
<lb/>be done, not only as an act of justice due to the 
	  <lb/><name>Indians</name>, but as essential to the honour and dig­
	  <lb/>nity of the <placeName>United States</placeName>. I fear, however, that
	  <lb/>the <name>Indians</name> will not be relieved from persecution
<lb/>unless they be received into the Union, and be­
<lb/>come citizens of our country; and they have been
<lb/>encouraged to expect this, (after being duly pre­
<lb/>pared,) and some of them have declared that
<lb/>nothing shall be wanting on their part.</p>
        <p>No great or good man would, I presume, ob­
<lb/>ject to meet an Indian representative on the floor
	  <lb/>of <orgName>Congress</orgName>, but would rather esteem his coun­
<lb/>try honoured by this act of justice and liberality;
<lb/>though to soothe the pride of little men, a propo­
<lb/>sal has been made to substitute a white repre­
<lb/>sentative of their election, who shall reside
<lb/>among them.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> I should imagine the <name>Indians</name>, 
	  <lb/>whom <persName>Bartram</persName> visited, were as far advanced in 
<pb n="140"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="M4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">140</mw>
<lb/>civilization as are our farmers; they cultivate
<lb/>almost every species of vegetables, raise cattle,
<lb/>and poultry, have peach and apple orchards, and
<lb/>many other fruits in abundance?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> True, <persName>Elizabeth</persName>, <persName>Bartram</persName> says, a
<lb/>canoe ladened with melons and oranges came to
<lb/>the trading house to be disposed of to the traders,
	  <lb/>the day preceding his arrival in <placeName>Florida</placeName>, which
<lb/>proves they grew more than was wanted for their
<lb/>own use, and the courtesy and urbanity of their
<lb/>manners, are superior to what is commonly found
<lb/>in civilized society. I will give you an extract
	  <lb/>of a letter from <persName>Mr. David Brown</persName>, an interesting
	  <lb/>young <name>Cherokee Indian</name>, who some years since
<lb/>gave us much pleasure by delivering a very ap­
<lb/>propriate address in this town. This letter is 
	  <lb/>dated <placeName>Willstown</placeName>, <placeName>Cherokee Nation</placeName>, <date when="1825-09"><name>Sept.</name>, 
1825</date>.</p>
        <quote rend="bestow((pre(“))(p))">
          <p>I have made a hasty translation of the four
	    <lb/><name>Gospels</name>, which will require a close criticism.
	    <lb/>On my arrival at <placeName>Dwight</placeName>, I shall pursue the de­
<lb/>lightful work, and hope that the day is not very
	    <lb/>distant when the <name>Cherokees</name>, my brethren and
<lb/>kindred, according to the flesh, shall read the
<lb/>words of eternal life in their own tongue. I will
	    <lb/>here give you a faint picture of the <placeName>Cherokee
<lb/>Nation</placeName>, and its inhabitants. In the mean time,
<lb/>however, it must be borne in mind, that it is the
<pb n="141"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="M5r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">141</mw>
<lb/>mass and common people that form the character
<lb/>of a Nation, and not officers of government, nor
<lb/>the lowest grade of peasantry.</p>
          <p>The <placeName>Cherokee nation</placeName>, you know, is in about
<lb/>35 degrees north latitude. The precise quantity 
	    <lb/>of land over which the <name>Cherokees</name> claim sov­
<lb/>reignty is not yet ascertained, and consequently I
<lb/>cannot say; but this I can readily say, they
<lb/>have no more to spare. This country is well
<lb/>watered; abundant springs of pure water are
<lb/>found in every part. A range of majestic and
<lb/>lofty mountains stretch themselves across the
<lb/>nation. The northern part is hilly and moun­
<lb/>tainous. In the southern and western parts
<lb/>there are extensive fertile plains, covered partly 
<lb/>with tall trees, through which beautiful streams
<lb/>of water glide. These plains furnish immense
<lb/>pasturage, and numberless herds of cattle are 
<lb/>dispersed over them. Horses are plenty, and are
<lb/>used for servile purposes. Numerous flocks of
<lb/>sheep, goats and swine, cover the valleys and 
	    <lb/>hills. On <placeName>Tennessee</placeName>, <placeName>Ustanala</placeName>, and <placeName>Ganasagi
<lb/>rivers</placeName>, Cherokee commerce floats. The climate 
<lb/>is delicious and healthy; the winters are mild.
<lb/>The spring clothes the ground with its richest
<lb/>scenery. Cherokee flowers, of exquisite beauty
<lb/>and variegated hues, meet and fascinate the eye
<pb n="142"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="M5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">142</mw>
<lb/>in every direction. In the plains and valleys,
<lb/>the soil is generally rich, producing Indian corn,
<lb/>sweet and Irish potatoes, cotton, tobacco, wheat,
<lb/>oats, indigo. The natives carry on considerable
<lb/>trade with the adjoining states; and some of
	    <lb/>them export cotton in boats down the <placeName>Tennessee</placeName>
	    <lb/>to the <placeName>Mississippi</placeName>, and down that river to <placeName>New-
<lb/>Orleans</placeName>. Apple and peach orchards are quite
<lb/>common; and gardens are cultivated with much
<lb/>attention. Butter and cheese are seen on Chero­
<lb/>kee tables. There are many public roads in the
<lb/>Nation, and houses of entertainment kept by na­
<lb/>tives. Numerous and flourishing villages are
<lb/>seen in every section of the country. Cot­
<lb/>ton and woolen cloths are manufactured here.
<lb/>Blankets of various dimensions, manufactured by
<lb/>Cherokee hands, are very common. Almost
<lb/>every family in the nation grows cotton for its
<lb/>own consumption. Industry and commercial
<lb/>enterprise are extendng themselves in every part.
<lb/>Nearly all the merchants in the nation are native
	    <lb/><name>Cherokees</name>. Agricultural pursuits, the most so­
<lb/>lid foundation of our national prosperity, engage
<lb/>the chief attention of the people. Different
<lb/>branches of mechanics are pursued. The popu­
<lb/>lation is rapidly increasing. How vain then to
<lb/>talk of Cherokee deterioration.</p>
          <pb n="143"/>
          <milestone unit="sig" n="M6r"/>
          <mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">143</mw>
          <p>White 
men in the nation enjoy all the im­
<lb/>munities and privileges of the Cherokee people;
<lb/>except that they are not eligible to public offices.
<lb/>National pride, patriotism, and a spirit of inde­
<lb/>pendence, mark the Cherokee character.</p>
          <p>The Christian religion is the religion of the
	    <lb/>nation. <name>Presbyterians</name>, <name>Methodists</name>, <name>Baptists</name>, and
	    <lb/><name>Moravians</name>, are the most numerous sects. Some
<lb/>of the most influential are members of the
<lb/>church, and live consistently with their profes­
<lb/>sion. The whole nation is penetrated with gra­
	    <lb/>titude for the aid it has received from the <placeName>United 
<lb/>States</placeName> government, and from different religious 
<lb/>societies. Schools are increasing every year;
<lb/>learning is encouraged and rewarded. The
	    <lb/>younger class acquire the <name>English</name>, and those of
<lb/>mature age the Cherokee system of learning.
<lb/>The female character is elevated and duly re­
<lb/>spected. Indolence is discountenanced. Our
<lb/>native language, in its philosohpy, genius and
<lb/>symphony, is inferior to few, if any in the world.
<lb/>Our relations with all nations, savage or civiliz­
<lb/>ed, are of the most friendly character. We are
<lb/>out of debt, and our public revenue is in a flour­
<lb/>ishing condition. Beside the amount arising 
<lb/>from imports, a perpetual annuity is due from the 
	    <lb/><placeName>United States</placeName>, in consideration of lands ceded
<pb n="144"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="M6v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">144</mw>
<lb/>in former periods. Our system of government,
<lb/>founded on republican principles, by which jus­
<lb/>tice is equally distributed, secures the respect 
	    <lb/>of the people. <placeName>Newtown</placeName>, pleasantly situated in
<lb/>the centre of the nation, and at the junction of
	    <lb/><placeName>Ganasagi</placeName> and <placeName>Gusuwati</placeName>, two beautiful streams,
<lb/>is the seat of government. The legislative power
<lb/>is vested in what is denominated, in the native
	    <lb/>dialect, <orgName>Tsalagi</orgName> and <orgName>Tinilawiga</orgName>, consisting of a
<lb/>national committee and council. Members of
<lb/>both branches are chosen by and from the peo­
	    <lb/>ple for a limited period. In <placeName>Newtown</placeName>, a print­
<lb/>ing press is soon to be established; also a na­
<lb/>tional library, and a museum. Immense con­
<lb/>course of people frequent the seat of government,
	    <lb/>when <orgName>Tsalagi</orgName> and <orgName>Timilawiga</orgName> is in session,
<lb/>which takes place once a year. Nothing has
<lb/>excited so much interest for many years past, as
<lb/>the unhappy fate of our friends and allies the
	    <lb/><name>Creeks</name>; and the whole nation deeply sympathi­
	    <lb/>zes with them. The news of <persName>McIntosh's</persName> death
<lb/>gave universal satisfaction to the nation. I say
<lb/>satisfaction, the same that is felt when a danger­
	    <lb/>ous rattlesnake is killed. <persName>McIntosh</persName> was a noto­
<lb/>rious traitor, and made great efforts to overthrow
<lb/>our happy domains. His character was well
<lb/>known here; treacherous deeds marked his
<pb n="145"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="N1r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">145</mw>
<lb/>steps. His intrigues and efforts, to blast our
<lb/>dearest hopes and interests, in a disgraceful
<lb/>manner, will not soon be forgotten. His name
<lb/>will long live in the annals of Cherokee history,
<lb/>not as an honourable and patriotic statesman, but
<lb/>as a traitor to his country, the most despicable
	    <lb/><name>Creek</name> that ever lived. This is the language of
	    <lb/>every <name>Cherokee</name>, and I am persuaded of every 
	    <lb/>honourable man in the <placeName>United States</placeName>. Indeed
<lb/>none can forbear to eye his character with con­
	    <lb/>tempt, and who is there in the whole <name>Cherokee
	    <lb/>nation</name> to mourn his tragical end! Not one. But I
<lb/>have done, and have only room to promise you a 
	    <lb/>letter from the banks of the <placeName>Arkansas</placeName>, and re­
<lb/>spectfully bid you farewell.</p>
        </quote>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> How extremely wicked and bar­
<lb/>barous it would be, to force a people, like the
	  <lb/><name>Cherokees</name>, to quit a beloved and delightful coun­
<lb/>try, endeared to them by every fond recollection,
<lb/>and consign them to a dreary wilderness, where
<lb/>every valuable improvement will be lost.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Eliza</persName>.</label> It will not assuredly be contended
	  <lb/>that the <name>Cherokees</name> are not sufficiently improved
<lb/>in the arts of civilization, to entitle them to be
<lb/>admitted into the Union; yet it was asserted,
	  <lb/>that the <name>Georgians</name>, not satisfied with receiving
	  <lb/>the valuable territories of the <name>Creeks</name>, had now
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">N</mw>
<pb n="146"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="N1v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">146</mw>
	  <lb/>brought forward a claim to the lands of the <name>Che­
<lb/>rokees</name>.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> This might have been forseen; when
<lb/>a government for a temporary expedient, or to
<lb/>gratify the clamorous rapacity of any portion of
<lb/>the community, violates what justice and honour
<lb/>demands, and good faith requires, its integrity
<lb/>and dignity is prostrated, and new concessions will
<lb/>perpetually be required, and yielded to, as the
<lb/>ability to resist is enfeebled by every concession.
	  <lb/>Like the debased and degenerate <name>Romans</name>, who
<lb/>by their want of unity and patriotism, became
<lb/>unable to defend their country's rights, and were
<lb/>compelled to substitute bribes as an expedient to
	  <lb/>relieve themselves from the invasion of the <name>Goths</name>
	  <lb/>and <name>Vandals</name>, whom they dared not resist, and
<lb/>who thus emboldened perpetually returned with
	  <lb/>new demands, till <placeName>Rome</placeName> was drained of her trea­
<lb/>sure, and was completely subjugated, and eventu­
<lb/>ally destroyed.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> But the <name>Goths</name> and <name>Vandals</name>, moth­
<lb/>er, were not subjects of the Empire?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> True they were not, but when a
<lb/>government meanly stoops to concessions which
<lb/>are incompatible with justice and honour, and
<lb/>through imbecility or wickedness, sacrifices the
<lb/>rights of its country, or suffers the weak to be­
<pb n="147"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="N2r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">147</mw>
<lb/>come the prey of unprincipled usurpers, whoever
<lb/>they be, nothing but the most disastrous results 
<lb/>can be anticipated. The system of bribery and
<lb/>corruption had long existed among the degener­
	  <lb/>ate <name>Romans</name>, hence good and patriotic men, who
<lb/>disdained to connive at aught that was servile
<lb/>and base to promote the designs of a party, were
<lb/>excluded from all places of honour or profit, and
<lb/>those only admitted to participate in the govern­
<lb/>ment who were ready to sacrifice the public
<lb/>good by promoting to the highest offices the un­
<lb/>worthy and the profligate.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> It would, I think, be vain to ex­
<lb/>pect justice from a government so sordid, unless
<lb/>indeed fear should induce them to do right. It
<lb/>is however evident, let what will be said, that the
	  <lb/><name>Cherokees</name> have made great improvement of late,
<lb/>and I should like to know if they still adhere
<lb/>to the law of not allowing any spirituous liquors
<lb/>to be carried into the nation.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> I doubt not that this law is still in
	  <lb/>force, as it was asserted in proof of the <name>Georgi­
<lb/>ans</name> having designed to gain by bribery the title
	  <lb/>to the land of the <name>Creeks</name>, that a quantity of spirit
<lb/>and specie had been secretly conveyed into their 
	  <lb/>territory, by the emissaries of the <name>Georgians</name>.
	  <lb/>Happy would it be if all our <name>Aborigines</name>, as well
<pb n="147"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="N2v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">148</mw>
	  <lb/>as the people of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, had the virtue
<lb/>and firmness to prohibit the use of ardent spirits,
<lb/>so truly pernicious and destructive to human hap­
<lb/>piness. Here however we can claim no superi­
	  <lb/>ority over those miserable degraded <name>Indians</name>, who
<lb/>are located in the vicinity of our settlements and
<lb/>fortresses, and have thus become the victims of
<lb/>intemperance and misery; nor can we boast of
<lb/>any legislative interference to save from ruin and
<lb/>degradation those wretched families, whose par­
<lb/>ents daily exhibit the most disgusting and riotous
<lb/>conduct in the presence of their young offspring,
<lb/>and deliberately consign them to ruin and infa­
<lb/>my. There can be no suffering more extreme
<lb/>than that which a wife and mother is doomed to
<lb/>bear, who is daily compelled to endure the in­
<lb/>sults of a husband abandoned to intemperance,
<lb/>in which every vice is included, and sees the
<lb/>property which should support her children con­
<lb/>sumed, without any means of redress, or hope of
<lb/>relief, till death closes the scene, and her family
<lb/>are reduced to want and infamy. In this in­
<lb/>stance we might profit by the wisdom of our red
<lb/>brethren on our southern borders, and confess,
<lb/>notwithstanding our boasted advantages, their
<lb/>laws greatly superior to our own.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> We should, I think, refrain from
<pb n="149"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="N3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">149</mw>
<lb/>censuring so severely those who have copied 
<lb/>from us this odious vice, if we cannot be induced
<lb/>to institute laws similar to those of the southern
	  <lb/><name>Indians</name>, to restrain its baleful influence.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> I will close what I have to say of  
	  <lb/>the <name>Creek Indians</name>, by giving you an extract from
	  <lb/><persName>Mr. Le Vasseur's</persName> <title>Journal of <persName>Lafayette's</persName> Tour
	  <lb/>among the <name>Creek Indians</name></title>, copied from a new
	  <lb/>periodical work, recently established in <placeName>Paris</placeName>,
<lb/>devoted to intelligence relating to this country.</p>
        <quote rend="bestow((pre(“))(p))post()">
          <p><placeName>Macon</placeName>, a pretty little town, which is now
<lb/>tolerably well peopled, was not in existence 
<lb/>eighteen months ago; it seems to have arisen
<lb/>from the forests as by enchantment. It is a
<lb/>civilized spot, lost amid the still immense do­
	    <lb/>mains of the first children of <placeName>America</placeName>. About
<lb/>a league thence we are in the bosom of virgin 
<lb/>forests, and the tops of trees, which seem as old
<lb/>as the world, hang over our heads. The winds
<lb/>sounded through them by turns, grave and shrill,
	    <lb/>which <persName>M. de Chauteaubriand</persName> calls the voice of the
<lb/>desert. Our road was a sort of trench, at the
<lb/>bottom of which the carriage of the general rolled
<lb/>with difficulty, and was often in danger of break­
<lb/>ing. We followed on horseback, and thus arriv­
	    <lb/>ed at the <orgName>Indian Agency</orgName>. This is situated in
<lb/>the midst of the forests, constructed for the con­
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">N2</mw>
<pb n="150"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="N3v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">150</mw>
<lb/>venience of the Indian Chiefs, and Agents of the 
	    <lb/><placeName>United States</placeName>, who hold their conferences here.
<lb/>It was here that the treaty was formed, after
<lb/>which the Indian tribes, still inhabitants of  <seg xml:id="a04" corresp="#n04" rend="post(*)">the
	    <lb/>left branch of the <placeName>Missouri</placeName>,</seg> consented for a con­
<lb/>siderable sum, to retire to the right. The year
<lb/><date when="1827">1827</date> was assigned for their evacuation, and it is
	    <lb/>not without pain the <name>Indians</name> see this conclusion
<lb/>of their ancient possessions approach. They
<lb/>quit with regret the neighbourhood of civilized
<lb/>men, notwithstanding they dislike them. They
<lb/>accuse their Chiefs of having betrayed them in
<lb/>making this cession, and we are assured that it
	    <lb/>has already cost the life of <persName>M‘Intosh</persName>, one of the
<lb/>signers of the treaty.</p>
          <p>We passed the night at the <orgName>Indian agency</orgName>;
	    <lb/>for fifty years the name of <persName>Gen. Lafayette</persName> had
<lb/>lived among them by tradition, and an hundred
	    <lb/><name>Indians</name> had waited to receive us, but the delays
<lb/>we experienced during our journey, having tired
<lb/>their patience, they had gone elsewhere to pre­
<lb/>pare a reception. We had to travel thirty-two
<lb/>miles the next day, by a route still less practa­
<lb/>ble. Such a storm as we have never seen in
	    <lb/><placeName>England</placeName>, assailed and dispersed us during some
<pb n="151"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="N4r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">151</mw>
<lb/>hours. The end of the storm permitted us to
<lb/>meet again, and to begin our route. We arrived
<lb/>at a habitation little bigger than that of the
<lb/>watch. It was a group of cabins, constructed
<lb/>with the bodies of trees placed over each other
<lb/>and stripped of their bark. At our arrival we
	    <lb/>found two <name>Indians</name> seated before the door, one
<lb/>young, the other a grown up man, and both of
<lb/>them of remarkable form and beauty. They
<lb/>were clothed with a short tunic of light and
<lb/>finged stuff, fastened round their body with a
<lb/>girdle, embroidered with small beads of a thou­
<lb/>sand colours. A shawl of lively colour was rolled
<lb/>round their heads with much elegance. Their
<lb/>trowsers of sheep skin reached down to their
<lb/>knees. They arose at the approach of the Gen­
<lb/>eral, saluted him, and the youngest, to our great
<lb/>astonishment, complimented him in very good
	    <lb/><name>English</name>. We soon learned that he had passed
	    <lb/>his youth in college in the <placeName>United States</placeName>, but 
<lb/>that he had stolen away many years ago from a
<lb/>benefactor, to return to his brother's, whose life
<lb/>he preferred to that of civilized men. The Gen­
<lb/>eral put many questions to him upon the exist­
<lb/>ence of the Indian colony. He replied to them
<lb/>with much sense and precision.</p>
          <p>When he was questioned as to the last treaty
<pb n="152"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="N4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">152</mw>
	    <lb/>concluded with the <placeName>United States</placeName>, his counte­
<lb/>nance darkened, he struck his foot on the ground,
<lb/>and laying hold of the handle of his knife, he
	    <lb/>mentioned the name of <persName>M‘Intosh</persName>, in a manner
<lb/>that made us shudder at the danger of this chief.
	    <lb/>As we appeared astonished, <said><persName>M‘Intosh</persName>,</said> cried 
<lb/>he, <said>has sold the land of his fathers—he has
<lb/>sacrificed us all to his avarice—it is impossible to
<lb/>break the treaty which he has formed; but the
<lb/>scoundrel!</said> He stopped after this violent excla­
<lb/>mation, and a little while after took up quietly
<lb/>some other subject of conversation.</p>
          <p><persName>Hamly</persName>, (that was the name of the young <name>In­
<lb/>dian</name>,) when he saw us a little rested, engaged us
<lb/>to visit his habitation, which we perceived on the
<lb/>brow of a hill at a little distance. Two of the
<lb/>General's aid de camps, and myself, accepted the
	    <lb/>invitation, and we followed the <name>Indians</name>. Going
<lb/>along he showed us an enclosure surrounded by
<lb/>palisades, filled with stags, mastiffs, and grey­
<lb/>hounds, which they called their reserve, and
<lb/>which supplied them when the chase proved un­
	    <lb/>favourable. <persName>Hamly's</persName> cabin bordered upon this
<lb/>enclosure. We entered it. There was a great
<lb/>fire in the fire place, the day was declining, and
<lb/>the spacious habitation was lighted by the flame
<lb/>of a fir tree. The furniture was composed of a
<pb n="153"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="N5r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">153</mw>
<lb/>table, two beds, some large chairs, ozier baskets,
<lb/>fire-arms, bows and arrows, were hung upon the
<lb/>wall, and also a violin. The arrangement of all
<lb/>indicated the presence of a half civilized man.</p>
          <p>Two Indian women approached the habita­
	    <lb/>tion, whilst it resounded with the sports of <persName>Ham­
<lb/>ly</persName> and his applauses, but they did not enter; I
<lb/>alone perceived them. They had the beauty pe­
<lb/>culiar to their race; their vestment was compos­
<lb/>ed of a long white tunic; of a scarlet drapery
<lb/>thrown over their shoulders; their long hair
<lb/>floated at liberty; they wore upon their necks a
<lb/>collar of five rings of pearls, and in their ears
<lb/>large pendants of silver, which are the principal 
<lb/>ornaments of Indian women.</p>
          <p>I would willingly have made myself the
	    <lb/>b<gap extent="2 letters" reason="flawed-reproduction" desc="printed"/>ning companion and messmate of <persName>Hamly</persName> for
<lb/>some days; but it was necessary to continue our
<lb/>journey. We retired, and the next day recom­
<lb/>menced our route. In proportion as we advanc­
<lb/>ed into the woody country, the appearance of In­
<lb/>dian land, desrtroyed in our minds that prejudice
<lb/>which induces civilized nations to desire to intro­
<lb/>duce their state of society among people who
<lb/>have not changed their primitive mode of life;
<lb/>and to consider as a lawful conquest, the usurpa­
<lb/>tion of places in which this pretended barbarity
<pb n="154"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="N5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">154</mw>
<lb/>reigns; but no one can help taking interest in
	    <lb/>the fate of the <name>Indians</name>, meeting at every step the
<lb/>bark hut of a wandering hunter, who inhabits it
<lb/>in security, and in the simple virtues of igno­
<lb/>rance, we cannot think without sorrow that they
<lb/>will soon be overturned and replaced by an Ame­
<lb/>rican cultivated farm.</p>
          <p>It was near a rapid creek, the borders of
<lb/>which were steep, that we saw for the first time
	    <lb/>the <name>Indians</name> united in a body to receive the Gen­
<lb/>eral. A great number of women and young
<lb/>boys, broke through the trees on the opposite
<lb/>border of the river, and upon seeing us, they
<lb/>raised cries of joy. Some warriors descended
<lb/>the brow of a hill at a little distance, and ran to
<lb/>a spot on the river where the boat was, in
	    <lb/>which we were to land. The variety and singu­
<lb/>lar richness of their costumes offered a most
<lb/>picturesque view. <persName>M. George Lafayette</persName> sprang 
<lb/>first upon land, and in a moment was surrounded 
<lb/>by men, women and children, who moved round
<lb/>him, danced about him, touched his hands and
<lb/>his garments with an air of surprise and delight,
<lb/>which caused him almost as much embarrassment
<lb/>as emotion. Suddenly, as if they wished to give a
<lb/>more dignified and solemn expression to their joy,
<lb/>they retired behind the men ranged in front. He,
<pb n="155"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="N6r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">155</mw>
<lb/>who appeared to be the chief of the tribe, by a shrill
<lb/>and prolonged cry, gave the signal for a sort of 
<lb/>salute, which was repeated by the whole troop;
<lb/>then they again rushed toward the boat. Imme­
<lb/>diately upon the General's descending, some of
<lb/>the strongest brought a low chair, which we had
<lb/>with us, and obliged him to mount it, <said>not wish­
<lb/>ing,</said> they said, <said>that their father should put his
<lb/>foot on the damp earth.</said> The General was thus
<lb/>carried as in a palanquin to a certain distance
<lb/>from the river side, then he, whom I have al­
<lb/>ready distinguished as the chief of the tribe, ap­
	    <lb/>proached and told him in <name>English</name>, that all his
<lb/>brothers were happy at being visited by him,
	    <lb/>who in his affection for the inhabitants of <placeName>Ameri­
<lb/>ca</placeName>, had never distinguished blood or colour; who
<lb/>was the cherished father of men who inhabited
<lb/>the continent. After the Chief had spoken, the
	      <lb/>other <name>Indians</name> came to press the hand of the
<lb/>General, and to place it on their head. They
<lb/>would not abandon the carriage but dragging it
<lb/>themselves, mounted by short steps to the hill
<lb/>from which we had seen them descend, and on
<lb/>which was situated one of their largest hamlets.</p>
          <p>Whilst we walked we approached the In­
<lb/>dian chief; and thought that since he spoke
	    <lb/><name>English</name>, he had been brought up like <persName>Hamly</persName> in
<pb n="156"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="N6v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">156</mw>
	    <lb/>the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and so I was informed. He
<lb/>was about 28 years of age, of middle size, his
<lb/>limbs were perfectly formed, his physiognomy
<lb/>noble, and his air sorrowful. When he did not
<lb/>speak, he cast down his large black eyes, which
<lb/>were covered with thick eye lashes; when he told
	    <lb/>me he was the eldest son of <persName>M‘Intosh</persName>, I could
<lb/>not recal, without pain, the imprecations that I
<lb/>had heard from the watch, against the chief of
	    <lb/>the <name>Muscogulges</name>. It was this undoubtedly,
<lb/>which gave the young man the air of dejection
<lb/>and meditation.</p>
          <p>In the mean time, we arrived at the top of
<lb/>the hill—there we saw helmets, swords and
<lb/>horsemen, ranged along the road: they were not
	    <lb/><name>Indians</name>, but civilized men sent from the state of
	    <lb/><placeName>Alabama</placeName>, to meet the General. The singular
<lb/>triumphant march to which he had been obliged
	    <lb/>to submit, then ceased. The <name>Indians</name> could not
<lb/>see without jealousy the American escort place
<lb/>themselves around him; but we approached their
<lb/>village, and they hastened to reach it before us.
<lb/>There, at our arrival, we found them met together,
<lb/>having thrown aside their garments, and prepar­
<lb/>ed to exhibit before us their warlike games. We
<lb/>reached a vast plain, about which was scattered
<lb/>a hundred Indian habitations, improved by the
<pb n="157"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="O1r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">157</mw>
<lb/>verdure of the thick groves. We noticed a house
<lb/>larger than the others, it was that of the Ameri­
<lb/>can resident; he at the same time kept an inn,
<lb/>and his wife had the direction of a school, in
<lb/>which they attempted to instruct the children of
	    <lb/>the <name>Indians</name>. All the men were assembled in
<lb/>this place, having thrown aside part of their vest­
<lb/>ments; their faces painted with colours fantasti­
<lb/>cally mixed, and some wearing, by way of dis­
<lb/>tinction, plumes in their hair. They told us
<lb/>they were going to play in honour of their white
<lb/>father. And we really saw them separate into
<lb/>two armies, form two camps, in the two extremi­
<lb/>ties of the place, name two chiefs, and provoke
<lb/>each other to combat. The cry which was rais­
<lb/>ed by each of the two divisions, and which they
<lb/>told us was the war cry of the Indian tribes, is
<lb/>perhaps the strangest modulation of the human
<lb/>voice that it is possible to hear, and the effect it
<lb/>produced upon the warriors, young and old, is
<lb/>more extraordinary still. They commenced—
<lb/>they explained to us that the game was for two
<lb/>parties to throw a ball, something like that of
<lb/>our scholars, to a certain mark, and that he who
<lb/>struck this mark seven times, should be victori­
<lb/>ous. We in reality saw the combatants, each
<lb/>armed with two long and heavy <choice><sic>;</sic><corr/></choice> rackets precipi­
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">O</mw>
<pb n="158"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="O1v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">158</mw>
<lb/>tate themselves with a light movement, leap one
<lb/>over the other in order to seize it in the air, with
<lb/>unprecedented skill, and send it to the mark.
<lb/>When the ball was missed by a player it rolled
<lb/>on the ground. Then they all lowered their
<lb/>heads, struck each other, and it was often only
<lb/>after a long struggle that any of them raised it.
<lb/>In the midst of one of these long contests, whilst
<lb/>the players with their backs bent pressed in a 
	    <lb/>circle round the ball, an <name>Indian</name> separated from
<lb/>the group, went a little distance, came again
<lb/>running, rushed forward, after having turned
<lb/>himself round several times, fell upon the robust
<lb/>shoulders of the others without bending them; 
<lb/>leaped into the middle of the circle, seized the
<lb/>ball, and for seven times threw it at the mark.
	    <lb/>This was <persName>M‘Intosh</persName>. The camp of which he was
<lb/>chief was victorious—he came to receive our
<lb/>congratulations, in the midst of the acclamations
<lb/>of a party of Indian women, whilst the wives of
<lb/>the vanquished seemed to address them in words
<lb/>of consolation. The General, after this feat,
<lb/>which amused us very much, went to visit the
<lb/>interior of some of their habitations, and some of
<lb/>the Indian schools. When we were ready to
	    <lb/>begin our route, young <persName>M‘Intosh</persName> reappeared in a
<lb/>European habit. He asked the General's permis­
<pb n="159"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="O2r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">159</mw>
	    <lb/>sion to accompany him to <placeName>Montgomery</placeName>, where
<lb/>he was going to conduct his brother, a boy of ten
<lb/>years old, willing to trust his education to an
	    <lb/><name>American</name>. The General consented to it, and
	    <lb/>we all departed together for the <name>Uchee Creek</name>, an
<lb/>American Inn situated on the borders of a tor­
<lb/>rent which bears that name. We arrived early
<lb/>at this station, and were able to visit the envi­
<lb/>rons, which are delightful. Accompanied by
	    <lb/><persName>M‘Intosh</persName>, I soon made acquaintance with the
	    <lb/><name>Indians</name> of this country: we found some of them
<lb/>drawing the bow. I wished to try my strength
	    <lb/>like the rest. <persName>M‘Intosh</persName> also armed himself with
<lb/>a bow; he has the arm, and the eye sight of
	    <lb/><persName>William Tell</persName>. Some of the trials of skill which
<lb/>he exhibited, if told, would scarcely be believed.
<lb/>I particularly admired the dexterity with which,
<lb/>while lying on the green plat, he threw an ar­
<lb/>row, which striking the earth a little distance,
<lb/>rose with a light bound, and flew to a prodigious
	    <lb/>distance. It is a way which the <name>Indians</name> employ
<lb/>to throw far, without being seen by the enemy.
<lb/>I tried in vain this singular feat; each time my
<lb/>arrow instead of rebounding sank in the earth.</p>
          <p>We returned to <name>Uchee Creek</name>, where we had
<lb/>a meeting with an Indian chief who kept an Inn.
<lb/>Some steps from the house the chief alighted,
<pb n="160"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="O2v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">160</mw>
<lb/>went to salute the General, and made a few pur­
<lb/>chases. The women in the mean time took
<lb/>care of the horse, and led him back, and when
<lb/>he set out again put on the bridle and saddle,
<lb/>and sprang up behind him. I asked my travel­
<lb/>ling companions, if this was the condition of the 
<lb/>women of this nation. They answered that in
<lb/>general they lived with their husbands in this
<lb/>kind of servitude, that in the agricultural coun­
<lb/>tries, they cultivated the field, laboured, sowed
<lb/>and reaped. In the walks, which I afterwards
	    <lb/>took in the environs of <name>Uchee Creek</name>, their fate
<lb/>never appeared so bad, as these statements made
<lb/>them. I saw women ranged in a circle before
<lb/>almost all the habitations, occupied in weaving
<lb/>mats and panniers, and amusing themselves with
<lb/>games and exercises of the body, in which the
<lb/>young men joined before them; and I did not
<lb/>mark any trait of severity on the part of the men,
<lb/>or servile dependence on that of the women. I
<lb/>had been so well received in all these Indian
	    <lb/>habitations, near <name>Uchee Creek</name>, and all the coun­
<lb/>tries watered by the streams were so beautiful,
<lb/>that it still seems one of the most delightful
<lb/>places I have met with.</p>
          <p>From the <name>Uchee Creek</name> to the <name>hamlet of the
	    <lb/>Big Warrior</name>, the nearest halt is about a day's
<pb n="161"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="O3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">161</mw>
<lb/>journey. It led us through a country peopled
	    <lb/>by <name>Indians</name>. We often met them assembled on
<lb/>our route, and were assisted by them to cross the
<lb/>dangerous passages: for the storms had filled
<lb/>the roads, and swelled the torrents. In one of
<lb/>these situations the General received a very
<lb/>touching proof of the veneration which these sim­
<lb/>ple men have for him. One of the torrents
<lb/>which he had to cross ran over a wooden bridge
<lb/>without a railing, and over which the General
<lb/>must pass. What was our astonishment, on ar­
	    <lb/>riving at the river side, to find a hundred <name>In­
<lb/>dians</name>, who taking each other by the hand, and
<lb/>up to their breasts in water, formed a double
<lb/>guard, in the direction of the bridge! We were 
	    <lb/>very glad to have this assistance, and the <name>Indians</name>
<lb/>for their recompense, only wished the favour of
<lb/>kissing the hand of the General whom they called
<lb/>their white father, the ambassador of the Great 
<lb/>Spirit, the French warrior who formerly came to
	    <lb/>deliver them from the tyranny of the <name>English</name>.
	    <lb/><persName>M‘Intosh</persName>, who translated their discourse to us,
<lb/>explained to them the wishes of the General, and
	    <lb/>the rest of us. The <name>Hamlet of the Big Warrior</name>,
<lb/>was so called on account of the extraordinary
<lb/>courage and high stature of its Chief. We ar­
<lb/>rived there too late; the chief had been dead
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">O2</mw>
<pb n="162"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="O3v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">162</mw>
<lb/>for some time: the council of the old men had
<lb/>been assembled to give a successor, and had
<lb/>chosen one of his sons, as remarkable for strength
<lb/>of body as his father.</p>
          <p>We passed a night with the family of the
	    <lb/><name>Big Warrior</name>. The next day we arrived at <placeName>Line
<lb/>Creek</placeName>, on the frontiers of the Indian country.
	    <lb/>We were received there by an <name>American</name>, who
<lb/>had married the daughter of a Creek chief, and
	    <lb/>who lived the life of an <name>Indian</name>. He was a <persName>Cap­
<lb/>tain Lewis</persName>, an old officer in the army of the
	    <lb/><placeName>United States</placeName>. His house was commodious and
<lb/>elegant for an Indian hut. He was a man dis­
<lb/>tinguished for his knowledge and character, and
<lb/>appeared to us to exercise great influence over
	    <lb/>the <name>Indians</name>. He had brought together a num­
<lb/>ber of them on horseback and armed for war to
<lb/>form an escort for the General. His discourse,
<lb/>which appeared studied, was translated to us by
<lb/>the interpreter. He began by praising the skill
<lb/>and courage that the General had shown against
	    <lb/>the <name>English</name>. The most brilliant circumstances
<lb/>of this war were recalled and related in a lan­
<lb/>guage not unpoetical. The Indian chief con­
<lb/>cluded by nearly these words. <said>Father, they
<lb/>will tell for a long time among us, that you re­
<lb/>turned to visit our forests and huts; you whom
<pb n="163"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="O4r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">163</mw>
<lb/>the Great Spirit formerly sent from the other
<lb/>side of the great lake to drive away those ene­
	      <lb/>mies of men, the <name>English</name>, as usual stained with
<lb/>blood. The youngest among us will tell their
<lb/>grand children that they have touched your hand
<lb/>and seen your person.—They will see you again
<lb/>perhaps, for you are the favourite of the Great
<lb/>Spirit, and you cannot grow old; you will be able
<lb/>still to defend us, when we are threatened.</said> The
<lb/>General answered by the help of the interpreter
	    <lb/>the farewell of the <name>Indians</name>. He gave them
<lb/>counsels of wisdom and temperance, recommend­
<lb/>ed to them to live always on good terms with the
	    <lb/><name>Americans</name>, and to regard them always as friends
<lb/>and brothers. He told them he would think of
<lb/>them, and pray for the prosperity of their huts,
<lb/>and the glory of their warriors.</p>
        </quote>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> How well these observations agree
	  <lb/>with the accounts given by <persName>Mr. Bartram</persName>, and
	  <lb/>others, of the character and manners of the <name>In­
<lb/>dians</name>. What was told him of their treatment of 
<lb/>their women, is the same as we have often heard
<lb/>repeated whenever we speak favourably of the 
	  <lb/><name>Indians</name>.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> It is pleasant to find a writer, who
<lb/>cannot be suspected of prejudice, confirming
<lb/>statements which have so repeatedly been given. 
<pb n="164"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="O4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">164</mw>
<lb/>Such information as was given by the compan­
	  <lb/>ions of <persName>Le Vasseur</persName>, is generally received as true
<lb/>by superficial observers, who give themselves lit­
<lb/>tle trouble to compare the manners of strangers
<lb/>with those to which they have been accus­
	  <lb/>tomed. Were an <name>Indian</name> to witness the accumu­
<lb/>lated labours of women in the common classes of
<lb/>civilized society, especially could he be made
<lb/>acquainted with the condition of the wives and
<lb/>daughters of our common farmers, whose toil is
<lb/>incessant, and find that notwithstanding all they
<lb/>do and suffer, they are treated as mere depend­
<lb/>ents to whom no civility or courtesy is due, he
<lb/>would doubtless be shocked at their servile con­
<lb/>dition, and exult in the comparative leisure and
<lb/>importance of the women of his own nation.
<lb/>Were I inclined to extend my remarks on this
<lb/>subject, it would be easy to adduce other instan­
<lb/>ces of the servile dependence of women in the
<lb/>higher classes of society, and the arrogant as­
<lb/>sumption of all right to the disposal of property
<lb/>by the other sex, even of that which was exclu­
<lb/>sively possessed by women previous to mar­
<lb/>riage.</p>
        <p>To illustrate some of my observations, I will
	  <lb/>give you some remarks of <persName>Mirza Abu Taleb Khan</persName>,
	  <lb/>in his book of travels through <placeName>Asia</placeName>, <placeName>Africa</placeName> and
<pb n="165"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="O5r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">165</mw>
	  <lb/><placeName>Europe</placeName>, which we are told <quote rend="pre(‘)post(’)">possesses the strongest
<lb/>claim to attention, as the work was ushered into
<lb/>notice under circumstances which leave no doubt
<lb/>of its authenticity.</quote> The work is concluded by
<lb/>an appendix, containing a curious tract on the
	  <lb/>treatment of women in <placeName>Asia</placeName>; a subject which
	  <lb/>was suggested to <persName>Abu Taleb</persName>, by the notion pre­
	  <lb/>valent in <placeName>Europe</placeName>, that the fair sex in the East
<lb/>live in a state of thraldom. The observations
<lb/>are curious, chiefly as communicating the reasons
	  <lb/>which strike the imagination of an <name>Orientalist</name> as 
<lb/>productive of differences in national habits.</p>
        <p><quote>The Asiatic women appear to have the
<lb/>greater liberty of the two; possessing, he says,
<lb/>more authority over the property of their hus­
<lb/>bands, and over their servants, as well as over
<lb/>the education, the religion, and the marriages of
<lb/>their children. At the same time the Asiatic
<lb/>ladies have no trouble in entertaining the guests,
<lb/>or attending to the business of the husband. If
	    <lb/>a divorce happens to take place in <placeName>India</placeName>, a 
	    <lb/>mother does not, as in <placeName>Europe</placeName>, relinquish all her
<lb/>children to her husband, but carries away her
<lb/>daughters, and her property; a step, indeed,
<lb/>which she will have little hesitation in taking on
<lb/>the occurrence of a quarrel of less consequence
<lb/>than those which lead to a permanent separation.
<pb n="166"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="O5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">166</mw>
	    <lb/>Polygamy does not exist in <placeName>India</placeName>, in the manner
<lb/>commonly imagined; the first wife being the
<lb/>only one who is considered as on a footing of 
<lb/>equality with the husband. Women, submitting
<lb/>to become the wives of married men, are not ad­
<lb/>mitted into the society of ladies, but have either
<lb/>a separate dwelling, or occupy a subordinate sta­
<lb/>tion in the house of the equal wife.</quote> The truth 
<lb/>indeed is, that polygamy is very rare, and gener­
	  <lb/>ally carries its cure along with it; <quote>for from
	    <lb/>what I know</quote>, says <persName>Abu Taleb</persName>, <quote>it is easier to
<lb/>live with two tigresses than with two wives.</quote>
<lb/>This emphatic assertion he confirms by adduc­
<lb/>ing various points in which a lady makes no scru­
	  <lb/>ple of teasing her husband; such as <quote>keeping
<lb/>dinner waiting for her coming to the table; visiting
<lb/>her own friends frequently, and remaining day 
<lb/>after day under their roof, though repeatedly in­
<lb/>treated by her husband to return;</quote> all of which,
<lb/>it seems, are put in practice for the sake of keep­
<lb/>ing a hold on the husband's affection. Another
	  <lb/>assertion of <persName>Abu Taleb</persName>, and one which we con­
	  <lb/>fess, rather startled us, is, that the <name>Asiatics</name> ap­
<lb/>pear by their manners to place a greater reli­
	  <lb/>ance on a wife's discretion than the <name>Europeans</name>.
	  <lb/><quote>Here,</quote> he says, <quote>custom prevents a married
<lb/>lady from going abroad without the company of
<pb n="167"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="O6r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">167</mw>
<lb/>a friend, and to sleep from home would be at
<lb/>variance with all rule; whereas in the East a 
<lb/>wife will go unattended to the house of a lady
<lb/>of her acquaintance, though their husbands are
<lb/>strangers, and will remain there a week without
<lb/>its being thought unusual.</quote> Next as to the cus­
	  <lb/>tom in <placeName>Asia</placeName>, of ladies not entering into the society 
<lb/>of gentlemen, and not even seeing them, <quote>the 
	    <lb/>motive,</quote> says <persName>Abu Taleb</persName>, <quote>is choice, not com­
<lb/>pulsion; because in the East, the house-doors
<lb/>being kept open all the day, the females could
<lb/>not without such a precaution, be free from in­
<lb/>cessant interruption, or find leisure for domestic 
<lb/>employments.</quote></p>
        <p><seg xml:id="a05" corresp="#n05" rend="post(*)">This account, which I have taken from the
	  <lb/><title>Analectic Magazine</title>, for <date when="1814-01"><name>January</name>, 1814</date>,</seg> comes
<lb/>directly in point, and proves the truth of the po­
<lb/>sition I have advanced, respecting the erroneous
<lb/>opinions, and false views taken by superficial ob­
<lb/>servers, more especially such as are accustomed
<lb/>to think that nothing good can be found, but in
<lb/>the country or society to which they belong.
<lb/>Great advantage is taken of the ignorance and
<lb/>vanity, so prevalent among the common classes
<pb n="168"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="O6v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">168</mw>
<lb/>of society, by designing men, and the success in
<lb/>gaining subscriptions for missionary purposes,
<lb/>may be traced to the false impressions given of
<lb/>the slavery and superstition to which females are
<lb/>subjected in heathen countries, without the
<lb/>slightest allusion to the privileges they enjoy.
<lb/>Nothing is better calculated to suppress the
<lb/>puerile conceit of our own superiority, than the
<lb/>knowledge of the contempt and derision excited
	  <lb/>in the minds of the <name>Hindoos</name>, by the arrogant as­
<lb/>sumption of our missionaries, of being the only
<lb/>truly enlightened and favoured people in the 
<lb/>world, notwithstanding their profane and dis­
<lb/>cordant dogmas, prove how small is their title to
	  <lb/>respect or attention.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> You told us, mother, that the bur­
<lb/>thens which fell to the lot of the Indian women,
<lb/>were not so laborious or injurious as were the 
<lb/>hardships endured by the men in hunting, to 
	  <lb/>supply their families with food and clothing.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> We learn from 
<persName>Mr. Heckewelder</persName>,
<lb/>that women receive much attention from their
<lb/>husbands, who invariably give up to their dis­
<lb/>posal, when they return from their hunts, all the
<lb/>skins they have taken, that they may barter them
<lb/>with the traders for such articles as they choose,
<lb/>and that the women are sure to purchase some­
<pb n="169"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="P1r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">169</mw>
<lb/>thing which they know will please the husband 
<lb/>first. On the other hand, if the wife raise more
<lb/>corn and vegetables than will supply her family,
<lb/>the husband is at liberty to make presents of the
<lb/>surplus to his friends. This mutual confidence,
<lb/>and reciprocation of good offices, greatly tends
	  <lb/>to cement affection and 
respect.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> I rejoice that our excellent <persName>La­
	    <lb/>fayette</persName> gratified and cheered the <name>Creeks</name> by visit­
<lb/>ing them in their adversity; but it is what might
<lb/>have been expected from one so noble and dis­
	  <lb/>interested.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> This is indeed true;—<persName>Lafayette</persName> is 
<lb/>superior to all that is sordid or unworthy; his
<lb/>benevolence and patriotism would naturally in­
<lb/>spire him with feelings of deep sorrow and com­
<lb/>passion for a people who had suffered so greatly,
<lb/>and were bereft of those natural rights which he
<lb/>had devoted himself to maintain, undismayed by
	  <lb/>danger and suffering. <persName>Lafayette</persName> is the friend of
<lb/>the whole human race; in him we discover no
<lb/>inconsistency—he would not, whilst defending
<lb/>the rights of one set of men, doom to exile and
<lb/>misery any portion of his fellow beings, that he
<lb/>might riot on their spoils. To sum up all I have
<lb/>to say of this extraordrinary man, he approximates
<lb/>more, than any one of whom we have knowl­
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">P</mw>
<pb n="170"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="P1v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">170</mw>
<lb/>edge, to the character of our beloved and vener­
	  <lb/>ated <persName>Washington</persName>.</p>
        <p>I have thus, my dear girls, endeavoured to
<lb/>correct the erroneous opinions entertained of our
<lb/>superiority, and to vindicate the characters of
	  <lb/>our <name>Aborigines</name>, from the gross calumnies and 
<lb/>vulgar prejudices of their enemies. I trust you 
<lb/>will accustom yourselves to investigate and com­
<lb/>pare, without partiality, the laws and customs
<lb/>which influence the character of men, before
<lb/>you decide on their merits, and above all, you
<lb/>will defend and plead the cause of our much in­
	  <lb/>jured <name>Aborigines</name>, whose impending fate I ar­
<lb/>dently desire to avert.</p>
        <p>The courteous manner in which the natives of
<lb/>this country received and entertained the first
<lb/>English adventurers, who visited them, is well
	  <lb/>known; but I have lately met in <persName>Smith's</persName> <title><placeName>Vir­
<lb/>ginia</placeName></title>, a more particular account of their recep­
<lb/>tion in that part of the country, than is found
<lb/>elsewhere:—which I will now relate, though I
<lb/>intended not to have taxed your patience farther
<lb/>at present.</p>
        <p>Having arrived on the coast, which is describ­
<lb/>ed as very beautiful, abounding in a great variety
<lb/>of the goodliest trees and shrubs, with abundance
<lb/>of game—<quote rend="post()">Grapes</quote> (we are told) <quote rend="pre()">were found
<pb n="171"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="P2r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">171</mw>
<lb/>very plentiful in all places, both on the sand, the
<lb/>green soil and hills, and in the plains as well as
<lb/>on every little shrub, as also climbing towards
<lb/>the top of high cedars, that they did think in the
<lb/>world were not the like abundance.</quote> <quote>Till the
<lb/>third day,</quote> says the writer, <quote>we saw not any of
<lb/>the people; then in a little boat three of them
<lb/>appeared; one of them went on shore, to whom
<lb/>we rowed, and he attended us without any sign
<lb/>of fear, after he had spoken much, though we
<lb/>understood not a word, of his own accord he
<lb/>came boldly aboard us, we gave him a shirt, a 
<lb/>hat, wine and meat, which he liked very well
<lb/>and after he had well viewed us he went away
<lb/>in his own boat, and within a quarter of a mile 
<lb/>of us in half an hour he had loaden his boat with
<lb/>fish, with which he came again to the point of
<lb/>land, and there divided it in two parts, pointing 
<lb/>one part to the ship, the other to the pinnace,
<lb/>and so departed. The next day campe divers
<lb/>boats, and in one of them the king's brother,
<lb/>with forty or fifty men, proper people, and in
	    <lb/>their behaviour very civil; his name was <persName>Gran­
	      <lb/>ganameo</persName>, the king is called <persName>Winginia</persName>, the coun­
	    <lb/>try <placeName>Wingandocoa</placeName>; leaving his boats a little from
<lb/>our ships, he came with his train to the point;
<lb/>where spreading a mat he sat down; though we
<pb n="172"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="P2v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">172</mw>
<lb/>came to him well armed, he made signs to us to
<lb/>sit down without any show of fear, stroking his
<lb/>head and breast, and also ours, to express his
<lb/>love. After he had made a long speech to us,
<lb/>we presented him with divers toys, which he
<lb/>kindly accepted.</quote></p>
        <quote rend="bestow( (pre(“)post(”)) (p) )">
          <p>Not long after <persName>Granganameo</persName> brought his 
<lb/>wife and children, they were but of mean stature
<lb/>but well favoured, and very bashful; she had a
<lb/>long coat of leather, and about her forehead a
<lb/>band of white coral, and so had her husband; in
<lb/>her ears were bracelets of pearl of the bigness of
<lb/>peas; (the rest of the women had pendants of
<lb/>copper, and the noblemen five or six in an ear:)
<lb/>his apparel was like his wives, only the women
<lb/>wear their hair long on both sides, and the men 
<lb/>but one.</p>
          <p>After these women had been with us, there
<lb/>came down from all parts great store of people,
<lb/>with leather, coral and divers kinds of dyes, but 
	    <lb/>when <persName>Granganameo</persName> was present none durst trade
<lb/>but himself, and those who wore red copper on
<lb/>their heads, as he did. Whenever he came he
<lb/>would signify by so many fires, he came with so
<lb/>many boats, that we might know his strength.
<lb/>For an armour he would have engaged us a bag
<lb/>of pearl, but we refused, as not regarding it,
<pb n="173"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="P3r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">173</mw>
<lb/>that we might the better learn where it grew.
<lb/>He was very just in his promise, for oft we
<lb/>trusted him, and he would come within his day
<lb/>to keep his word. He sent us commonly every
<lb/>day a brace of bucks, conies, hares, and fish,
<lb/>sometimes melons, walnuts, cucumbers, peas,
<lb/>and divers roots.</p>
          <p>After this acquaintance, myself with seven
	    <lb/>more went twenty miles into the river <placeName>Oecum</placeName>,
	    <lb/>that runneth toward the city <placeName>Shiconck</placeName>, and the 
<lb/>evening following we came to an Isle called
	    <lb/><placeName>Roanoak</placeName>, from the harbour where we entered
<lb/>seven leagues; at the North end were nine
<lb/>houses, builded with cedar, fortified round with
<lb/>sharp trees, and the entrance like a turnpike.
	    <lb/>When we came towards it, the wife of <persName>Granga­
<lb/>nameo</persName> came running out to meet us, (her hus­
<lb/>band was absent) commanding her people to
<lb/>draw our boat ashore from beating on the bil­
<lb/>lows; others she appointed to carry us on their
<lb/>backs to land; others to bring our oars into the
<lb/>house, &amp;c. When we came into the other room,
<lb/>(for there were five in the house,) she caused us
<lb/>to sit down by a great fire, and after took off our
<lb/>clothes and washed them, and some of our stock­
<lb/>ings, and some of our feet in warm water, and
<mw type="sig" rend="indent(4)align(left)">P2</mw>
<pb n="174"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="P3v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">174</mw>
<lb/>she herself took much pains to see all things
<lb/>well ordered, and to provide us victuals.</p>
          <p>After we had dryed ourselves, she brought
<lb/>us into an inner room, where she set on the board
<lb/>standing along the house, somewhat like frumen­
<lb/>tie, sodden, venison and roasted fish; in like
<lb/>manner, mellons, boiled roots, and fruits of divers
<lb/>kinds. Their drink is commonly water boiled
<lb/>with ginger, or sassafras, and wholesome herbs,
<lb/>but whilst the grape lasteth they drink wine.
<lb/>More love she could not express to entertain us.
<lb/>When we were at meat, two or three of her men
<lb/>came amongst us with their bows and arrows,
<lb/>which caused us to take our arms in hand. She
<lb/>perceiving this our distrust, caused their bows
<lb/>and arrows to be broken, and they driven out of
<lb/>the gate: but evening approaching we returned
<lb/>to our boat, whereat she was much grieved, and
<lb/>brought us our supper half boiled, pots and all;
<lb/>but when she saw us put our boat a little off from
<lb/>the shore and lie at anchor, she sent divers men
<lb/>and women, to sit all night on the shore side
<lb/>against us, and sent us fine mats to cover us from 
<lb/>the rain, doing all she could to persuade us to
<lb/>her house. Though there was no cause of doubt,
<lb/>we would not adventure; for on our safety de­
<pb n="175"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="P4r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">175</mw>
<lb/>pended the voiage; but a more loving kind peo­
	    <lb/>ple cannot be.</p>
        </quote>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> How antiquated is the style,
<lb/>mother, in which this is written, but do you sup­
	  <lb/>pose that the wife of <persName>Granganameo</persName> herself wash­
	  <lb/>ed their clothes and feet?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> From the manner in which this is 
<lb/>related, and the circumstance of her having so
<lb/>many attendants, we must conclude that these
<lb/>things were done in obedience to her commands,
<lb/>as it is added that she herself took much pains
<lb/>to see all things well ordered. I have elsewhere
<lb/>stated to you that the wives of chiefs were, like
<lb/>ladies of high rank among us, exempted from
	  <lb/>servile occupations.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Caroline</persName>.</label> How delightful it is to find so
<lb/>much kindness shown to strangers; this account
	  <lb/>affords ample proof that the <name>Indians</name> improved
<lb/>the soil to great advantage, as they enjoyed such
<lb/>abundance and variety; notwithstanding so many
<lb/>have insisted that they cultivate nothing but
<lb/>corn, and even that so negligently as scarcely to
	  <lb/>supply their immediate necessities.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> Those who represent the <name>Indians</name> as
<lb/>barbarians, roving through interminable forests,
<lb/>and having no permanent place of abode, must of
<lb/>course fill up the outline, with such unfounded
<pb n="176"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="P4v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">176</mw>
<lb/>assertions, which are in full keeping with what
<lb/>is said of their miserable habitations, and scanty
<lb/>clothing. Nevertheless, the spacious dwelling
<lb/>to which our adventurers were invited and the
<lb/>entertainments given them, proves how well they
<lb/>understood, all that can make life agreeable and 
<lb/>pleasant.</p>
        <p><label type="speaker"><persName>Elizabeth</persName>.</label> Do you really think, mother, that
	  <lb/>the <name>Indians</name> were acquainted with the method of
	  <lb/>making wine?</p>
        <p><label type="speaker">Mother.</label> They unquestionably knew how to 
<lb/>express the juice of the grape, which according
<lb/>to the opinion of some celebrated medical men,
<lb/>is not only extremely grateful to the taste, but
<lb/>highly nutritious, previous to its undergoing the
<lb/>vinous fermentation, when it becomes extremely
<lb/>deliterious in its effects. It has been constantly 
	  <lb/>asserted, by the first <name>Europeans</name> who came to
	  <lb/>this country, that the <name>Indians</name> knew not the use
<lb/>of any liquor which possessed the quality of in­
<lb/>toxication. Yet, since we have introduced the
<lb/>use of ardent spirits among these unfortunate
<lb/>people, it has proved most destructive in its ef­
<lb/>fects: as those who have commerce with white
<lb/>people, appear but little able to resist its allure­
<lb/>ments; except indeed some of the southern na­
<pb n="177"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="P5r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">177</mw>
<lb/>tions who, as I have informed you, have shown
<lb/>a superior degree of firmness.</p>
        <p>The first adventurers to this country were uni­
<lb/>formly treated with kindness by the natives,
<lb/>who willingly administered to their wants, till
<lb/>they were fatally convinced that their own exis­
<lb/>tence depended on expelling the intruders.
	  <lb/>Those who landed on the coast of <placeName>Virginia</placeName>, at
<lb/>first directed all their efforts to procure gold,
<lb/>and thus neglected to provide for their own sub­
<lb/>sistence, by cultivating the soil. They insisted
<lb/>that the natives should supply them with corn on
	  <lb/>their own terms, and when the <name>Indians</name> protested
<lb/>that they had parted with all they could spare,
<lb/>and were even in want themselves, the settlers
<lb/>sent armed parties to compel them to comply 
<lb/>with their demands; and when any resistance
<lb/>was made they deemed themselves at liberty to
<lb/>burn the villages and towns of the natives, and
<lb/>to kill and make captives all who could not es­
<lb/>cape. Nay, in many instances, the principal
<lb/>chiefs and sovereigns were enticed into the for­
<lb/>tified places of the whites, and there detained
<lb/>till such a ransom was given as they chose to
<lb/>demand, and the most exorbitant conditions
<lb/>complied with. In one instance they burned
<lb/>the wife and children of a prince, because he
<pb n="178"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="P5v"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">178</mw>
<lb/>would not yield up all his property and rights to
<lb/>the invaders of his country.</p>
        <p>One of the adventurers, writing to a friend,
<lb/>says—<quote>Though we have not yet discovered
	    <lb/>mines of gold, as the more fortunate <name>Spaniards</name>
	    <lb/>have done in the <placeName>New World</placeName>, or destroyed so
<lb/>many of the natives, yet we have found a country
<lb/>abounding in all the necessaries and luxuries of
<lb/>life, and it has been our policy in many instan­
<lb/>ces to preserve the lives of the natives, that we
<lb/>may thus enjoy the fruits of their industry, as 
<lb/>we find it almost impossible to make our own
<lb/>people attend to the arts of husbandry.</quote></p>
        <p>I have found the account of these base trans­
	  <lb/>actions in <persName>Smith's</persName> <title><placeName>Virginia</placeName></title>, which I have
<lb/>abridged as much as possible, consistently with
<lb/>the sense of what is related. The same insidi­
<lb/>ous policy, though not so openly avowed, appears
<lb/>to have been adopted by all the settlers of this
<lb/>country. Nevertheless, we are assured by some
<lb/>grave divines, that the prophecy shall be fulfilled,
<lb/>and all nations pay homage to the prince of
<lb/>peace; <quote>and although,</quote> they say, <quote>the red men
<lb/>have refused to become converts to our faith,
<lb/>we know they are fast disappearing from the
	    <lb/>face of the earth, while civilized christian men
<lb/>are occupying the goodly heritage they once
<pb n="179"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="P6r"/>
<mw type="pageNum" rend="align(outside)">179</mw>
<lb/>possessed, in peace and security.</quote> Is this a
<lb/>cause of exultation to the followers of the pure
	  <lb/>and holy Jesus? Surely it savours more of <name>Ma­
	    <lb/>hometanism</name> than <name>Christianity</name>.</p>
      
    </body>
    <pb n="180"/>
    <milestone unit="sig" n="P6v"/>
    <back>
      <div type="advert">
        <head rend="case(allcaps)">School Books and 
<lb/>Stationary</head>
        <advertisement rend="case(allcaps)align(center)">
          <p rend="post(#rule)first-indent(0)"><persName>W.</persName> &amp; <persName>S. B. Ives</persName>,
<lb/>2 &amp; 4,
<lb/><name>Chase Building</name>, <placeName>Washington Str.</placeName>
<lb/><placeName rend="case(mixed)">Salem</placeName>, <placeName rend="case(mixed)">Mass</placeName>.
<lb/>Have for Sale a General Assortment of
<lb/>School Books,
<lb/>Blank Books,
<lb/>Stationary,
<lb/>Fancy Articles, &amp;c.</p>
          <p>They also execute all kinds of
<lb/>Book, Job and Fancy
<lb/>Printing.
<lb/><hi rend="case(mixed)">Book-Binders</hi>
<lb/>of every description.</p>
        </advertisement>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>